各位北村家,弟兄姊妹,堂慶蒙恩(Blessings to brothers and sisters of MPAC's family)
各位弟兄跟我說生日快樂(There was a brother who said to me happy birthday)
都是我們今天一齊的生日(It's actually birthday for all of us today)
今天我們一齊來到錦恩(Today we give thanks together)
我都跟大家分享錦恩的事(And I want to share with you things of thanksgiving)
去思想神的恩典(To think about the grace of God)
也都去思想特別是神給我們的救恩(And to think especially about the salvation God has given us)
很多時候弟兄姊妹都會自稱是蒙恩人(A lot of times you would say that we are those who have received grace or we are blessed)
很多時候我們有弟兄姊妹奉獻在徵信錄裡面就自稱是蒙恩人(And often in our offering envelope)
我們會說我們是神給的恩典(We put in we are blessed or we received grace)
我們的身份就是蒙受恩典的人(And that is our status, we have received grace)
我們是蒙受神恩典的人(We have received grace from God)
一位年長的弟兄(There was an elderly brother)
在他年長的時候(And when he was quite elderly)
他講述自己一生(And he was talking about his life)
講述了很多很多神給他的恩典(And he was talking about all the blessings and grace that God has given him throughout his life)
然後他最後說(And then he said at last, at last)
在這麼多經歷中(In all his experiences)
我仍然覺得最大的恩典(I still feel the greatest grace)
就是我信了耶穌(Is that I have believed Jesus)
他領受了神給他永恆的生命(He received the eternal life from God)
是最大的恩典(Is the greatest grace)
當我們讀到聖經而忽所書的時候(When we read the Bible)
講到神的恩典(When he was reading the book of Ephesians in the Bible)
阿彌陀佛