There's a rhythm that most of us fall into, going through the motions of our lives.
Stay busy, stay distracted, stay numb, sleepwalking through life.
But what if there's more?
More than just getting by, more than just existing, a life that is fully alive.
We need a holy interruption.
This Labor Day weekend, thousands of young adults will gather in Dallas, Texas, to sing,
to listen, to find joy, to seek the presence of God together.
Hosted by The Porch, we are calling on the name of the Lord to transform our generation,
to awaken our hearts to renewal, to awaken our lives to what truly satisfies.
Join voices like Kylan Perry, Matt Chandler, Jenny Allen, The Porch Worship, David Platt,
and Christine King, and step into a space where faith becomes real, where truth cuts
through the noise, and where you encounter God in a way that changes everything.
This is your wake-up call.