>> Let's sing it together. We're going to sing it together.
>> Let's sing it together.
>> Where can I go from your spirit?
Where can I hide from your face?
Where can I flee from your presence?
Where would I go? Where would I go?
If I rise to the heavens, you're with me.
If I fall to the depths of the sea,
even there it's your hand that will lead me
wherever I go, wherever I go.
Wherever I go, you go with me, you go with me.
Father, and Lord you search me.
How you know me.
You perceive my every thought from afar.
In all my wandering, still you love me.
King of glory, you pursue my anxious heart.
Even when I'm not your faithful,
even when I doubt your truth holds,
even when I'm lost, you won't let me go.
And when my heart is dry, your grace flows.
No matter where I run, I'm not far from home.
Yeah, I may be weak, but you're able.
Even when I'm not your faithful,
your faithful.
like a good, good father,
yeah, you're faithful.
And every season, even when I'm not your faithful.
And where can I go from your spirit?
Where can I hide from your face?
Where can I flee from your presence?
Where would I go, where would I go?
If I rise to the heavens, you're with me.
If I fall to the depths of the sea,
even there it's your hand that will lead me.
Wherever I go, wherever I go.
Sing that again.
And see, where can I go from your spirit?
And where can I hide from your face?
And where can I flee from your presence?
Where would I go, where would I go?
If I rise to the heavens, you're with me.
If I fall to the depths of the sea,
even there it's your hand that will lead me.
Wherever I go, wherever I go.
Even when I'm not your faithful,
even when I doubt your truth.
Even when I'm lost, you won't let me go.
Oh, Father, no, you won't let me go.
When my heart is dry, your grace flows.
No matter where I run, I'm not far from home.
Yeah, I may be weak, but you're able.
Even when I'm not your faithful,
your love's gonna find me in every season.
When I'm not your faithful,
your grace's gonna find me in every season.
Oh, you're faithful.
This I know, this I need.
When I'm not your faithful.
Oh, you're faithful.
For you knew my history,
and yet still you adopted me.
With all of my baggage,
still you claim me as your own.
Now I'm home in the love of the Father.
I belong in the heart of the Father.
I belong in the love of the Father.
And I'm coming back, coming back, oh.
I'm coming back to where I belong.
Will you got there to you?
Ooh, I'm coming back to you.
I'm coming back to you.
You're my first love.
That is who you are.
God, you're my first love.
I've tasted and I've seen,
and nothing else can satisfy my heart.
No, nothing else can satisfy my heart.
So I'm coming home, I'm coming home.
So now I'm coming, I'm coming back to you.
Hear your children.
I'm coming back to you.
You receive me as I am.
Broken as I am.
I'm coming back to you.
I'm coming, I'm coming back.
Here I am, father.
Will you receive me in all of whose I am?
I'm coming back to you.
I'm coming, I'm coming, I'm running.
So here I come running.
Oh, here I come running, running.
Here I come running, running.
And I won't look back, no, I won't look back.
Here I come running, running, running.
Here I come running, running.
I won't look back, no, I won't look back.
Here I come, here I come running, running.
Here I come running, running.
And I won't look back, no, I won't look back.
Here I come, here I come running, running.
Here I come running, running.
I'm coming back to you.
Sing it out.
Ooh, 'cause I have decided to follow Jesus.
And I have decided to follow Jesus.
I have decided to follow Jesus.
No turning back, no turning back.
I'm never looking back.
I'm coming, one more time, to you.
Sing it from your heart.
I'm coming back to you.
In the state I'm in right now.
[BLANK_AUDIO]