(Cantonese)
Jesus is the true light of Christmas.
(speaking in foreign language)
Complete darkness.
Physical darkness.
(speaking in foreign language)
Spiritual darkness.
Disappointment, failure.
(speaking in foreign language)
Other than God.
,
behavioral darkness.
(speaking in foreign language)
Darkness of hopelessness.
Can you become better?
(speaking in foreign language)
Darkness of anger.
Darkness of bitterness, resentment, failures, defeat,
disappointment, discouragement.
(speaking in foreign language)
Darkness of guilt and fear.
They see a great light.
(speaking in foreign language)
A source of light.
A wonderful counselor.
(speaking in foreign language)
Extraordinary, miraculous.
Wonderful counselor.
(speaking in foreign language)
Mighty God.
Everlasting father.
(speaking in foreign language)
Firm foundation.
The true light of Christmas.
(speaking in foreign language)
[BLANK_AUDIO]