Imagine with me for a moment a church.
This is not a church in the singular, on its own and distinct, but a church in the plural,
united across a nation, joined in purpose, focused on building up God's kingdom one
life at a time.
It is a church that has at the heart of its DNA the grand narrative of the redemptive
story of Jesus Christ, and that celebrates in the freedom and grace that such a story
brings.
This church is not constricted by the walls of a building, but actively engaged in the
community it is planted in, desiring for God's kingdom to take root and bear fruit in local
soil.
A church that sees salvation as holistic, transforming God's people for God's work
and equipping a generation to represent God's heart to the poor, the weak, the oppressed
and the persecuted.
Imagine this church committed to seeing the family as integral to all that it's called
to be and do, involving intentional, committed and authentic relationships across all levels.
It is the sort of place where both the young and the old feel cared for, supported and
equipped.
A church where people of all backgrounds and traditions come to feel at home, a cultural
mosaic that honors and embraces a richness in diversity that marks us as the body of
Christ.
It is a church that is willing to innovate and express faith creatively, reflecting the
boundless limits of God's creativity as glory to Him.
A place where people gather, hungry for the presence of God and passionate to see this
invade all aspects of their lives, where they seek to develop an intelligent, spiritual
faith rooted in God's word and driven with prayer.
A church that does not make its Sunday services the exclamation mark of its existence, but
instead the comma in its ongoing sentence, a time of service, love and engagement that
inspires and emboldens all equally for the conversation that lies ahead.
A church that cares, disciples, rebuilds, renews.
This is our city.
This is our church.
This is our home.
Good morning everyone and welcome to the Christmas Day service.
It's so good to have you.
We have lots of reason to be thankful and joyful.
We have a lot of exciting things planned, but before we do that, I want to invite you
to turn to your neighbor and say Merry Christmas.
Yes, Merry Christmas everyone.
Well, I want to invite everyone to stand and I'll pray for us and then we'll sing joyful
Christmas songs.
Let me pray.
Heavenly Father, we thank you so much for sending Jesus.
Jesus, we thank you for coming to us because you love us to rescue us, to show us your
love, to lay down your life for us so that we can have joy, that we can know you.
And today we just want to lift up these songs and give you praise and say thank you Jesus
for coming.
Thank you that you love us.
Thank you that you give us new life and that we can know that.
Thank you that you give us peace that we can experience.
So we pray all this in your name, Jesus. Amen.
The herald angels sing, glory to the newborn king.
Peace on earth and mercy wild.
God and sinners red with blood.
The herald angels sing, glory to the newborn king.
Joy the triumph of the skies with the jubilant hosts proclaim.
Christ is born in Bethlehem.
Hark the herald angels sing, glory to the newborn king.
Christ my highest heaven adored.
Christ the everlasting Lord.
All on high behold him come.
Offspring of the Virgin's womb.
Held in flesh the Godhead see.
Held in mind a deity.
Christ the Spirit meant to dwell.
Jesus our Emmanuel.
Hark the herald angels sing, glory to the newborn king.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
[MUSIC - "THE STAR SPANGLED BANNER"]
Oh, come all ye faithful, joyful and triumphant.
Oh, come ye.
Oh, come ye to Bethlehem.
Come and behold him, Lord, the King of angels.
Oh, come let us adore him.
Oh, come let us adore him, Christ the Lord.
Sing choir.
Sing choirs of angels.
Sing in exultation.
Oh, sing all ye citizens of heaven above.
Glory to God.
Glory in the highest.
Oh, come let us adore him.
Oh, come let us adore him, Christ the Lord.
Oh, Lord, we greet thee, born this happy morning.
Jesus, to thee be all glory given.
Word of the Father, now in flesh appearing.
Oh, come let us adore him.
Oh, come let us adore him, Christ the Lord.
Sing it again.
Oh, come.
Oh, come let us adore him.
Oh, come let us adore him, Christ the Lord.
[MUSIC - "WE'LL PRAISE YOUR NAME FOREVER"]
Sing, we'll praise.
We'll praise your name forever.
Christ the Lord.
Just some voices.
We'll praise your name forever.
Christ the Lord.
Let's give him a shout of praise.
Hallelujah.
God, we praise you.
[APPLAUSE]
[MUSIC - "GOD, YOU ARE WORTHY OF ALL PRAISE"]
God, you are worthy of all praise.
Jesus.
Sing, all the saints.
All the saints and angels bow before your throne.
All the elders cast their crowns before the Lamb of God.
Let's sing, all the saints.
All the saints and angels bow before your throne.
All the elders cast their crowns before the Lamb of God.
Let's sing.
Lift it up.
You are worthy of it all.
Yes, you are.
For from you are all things.
And to you are all things.
You deserve the glory.
We're singing.
Oh.
All the saints.
All the saints and angels bow before your throne.
All the elders cast their crowns before the Lamb of God.
You are worthy.
You are worthy of it all.
Yes, you are.
Worthy.
Oh.
For from you are all things.
And to you are all things.
You deserve the glory.
Sing again.
You are worthy.
Oh.
You are worthy of it all.
For from you are all things.
And to you are all things.
You deserve the glory.
Oh.
You are worthy, Jesus.
Yes, you are.
Let's sing it out.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it sense to rise.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it sense to rise.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it sense to rise.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it-- let's sing it again.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it sense to rise.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it sense to rise.
Day and night.
Night and day.
Let it sense to rise.
Day and night.
Night and day.
You are worthy of it all.
Oh, you are worthy of it all.
For from you are all things.
And to you are all things.
You deserve the glory.
Let's sing it out.
Just the voices.
You are worthy of it all.
Worthy God.
For from you are all things.
And to you are all things.
You deserve the glory.
Yes, Jesus, you are worthy of it all.
We praise you and we thank you that you have come because you
love us, to rescue us, to give us new life,
to put us on a different trajectory,
to give peace where there was no peace,
to give hope where we had lost hope,
to give comfort where we felt like nobody could comfort us,
and also to remove any shame that we are carrying.
So we thank you for your love.
We celebrate you today on Christmas that you have come,
which is the greatest sign of love.
So we pray all this in your name, Jesus.
Amen.
[applause]
Good morning.
You may all have a seat.
So I know that last time when Pastor Tim preached,
he gave you guys a pop quiz.
And I'm just going to follow up that tradition and give you guys
a pop quiz as well, okay?
I know that last time Pastor Tim gave you guys a pop quiz,
and so here it is.
How many sheep were there when the angel showed up to the
shepherds?
How many were there?
Take a guess, take a guess.
99, I heard someone say.
Three, three.
Any other guesses?
How many?
Five, five, five.
Okay, so in a minute you are going to hear very biblically
correct -- no, I'm joking, no.
You are going to watch a really excellent performance by our
fantastic kids at K4C.
Let's give them a round of applause first.
[applause]
They have worked really hard, so during the show,
please sing along with them, please clap along with them,
give them the encouragement that they deserve.
And I hope that whatever happens,
we're all going to have a great time.
And now, without further ado, let's introduce our amazing kids.
[applause]
Greetings all.
Now please take a seat.
We'd like to give you a small Christmas treat.
This play is about Christmas.
We'll do it in a rhyme.
Some people have lines while others will rhyme.
So don't forget cameras.
Please take a snap and always remember to sing with us and clap.
Our play will begin with a girl who's called Mary,
a lovely girl who heard something scary.
[baby crying]
Mary, you are going to have a baby boy,
and you will call him Jesus.
Wow, what an exciting day.
[laughter]
Meanwhile, Caesar and Rome made a decree.
You must all go home.
For Joseph this month off to Bethlehem town,
so they rode on their donkey all the way down.
Everyone has to go back to their hometown.
[applause]
Where's the star?
There's supposed to be a star, right?
When they got to Bethlehem, the birth day was looming,
but they couldn't find any hotel with a room in.
[background chatter]
Do you have any room?
My brother has a room.
You can stay in my stable.
He's here, Joseph said, and Jesus was born in a cold,
cattled shed.
[singing]
[applause]
So now we see heavenly angels appear to shepherds
who were worried and shaking with fear.
The angel said, hurry, I bring you good news.
Quickly, get moving.
No time for a snooze.
I bring you good news.
Today in Bethlehem Jesus is born.
You will find him in a manger.
Glory to God.
Glory to God and peace on earth.
[applause]
Three wise men lived far in the east.
They followed the star to get to the feast.
Let's visit the newborn king.
We need to get him gifts.
Let's follow the star.
It will take us to the baby.
They all gathered around.
The new baby boy.
Everyone welcome to share in the joy.
From angels to donkeys, from shepherds to kings,
share in joy.
Everyone shares the joy that he brings.
No one snapped out no matter how small.
Happy Christmas to one and to all.
[applause]
We wish you a merry Christmas.
We wish you a merry Christmas and a happy new year.
Good tidings we bring to you and your kin.
A great gift of something important.
We wish you a merry Christmas and a happy new year.
We all sin against God, so our relationship with God is broken down.
We say hurtful things to each other,
so there's a lot of breakdown in relationships with other people.
And even our relationship with creation is broken down,
because we were called to be stewards of creation,
but yet we treat God's beautiful creation as just something we can do whatever we want to with.
And so what I want to do is I want to actually set things in the larger story of the Bible.
So first, this is a story in four acts.
It's a mini overview.
The first one is God says he created the world, creation,
and that it was good what he created.
And he also said that when he created humans, that it was very good.
It was the pinnacle of God's creation, because they're made in God's image.
But then we're told that sin enters the world.
It's known as the fall, where people rebel against God,
and they struggle to trust God, that God really means it well with them.
And so they did what God asked them not to do,
and that's what we know as the fall, the sin fall.
Now, as already shared, this sin has impacted everything, every fabric of society.
And it's not just that we ourselves sin,
it's also that there are sinful structures that cause people to be oppressed and suffer and injustices.
And so when we talk about Jesus bringing good news and being the Savior,
he has come to rescue us from our brokenness, from our sin.
And God's Word also says that we ourselves cannot do it.
We can't do it out of our own strength.
There's nothing within us.
We can't try harder to be a better person.
It's not about putting in that little bit more effort.
God's Word says you cannot do it.
You cannot fix your sin issue yourself.
Now, some of us might wonder, am I even a sinner?
What is that?
So I want to say a little bit more about that.
Sin means missing the mark of what God desires of people.
And that means it can be even things we do in our heart.
It's not just that we murdered someone or something like that,
though that also, of course, is a sin.
But it can be like having judgmental thoughts, envying other people,
acting selfishly when we know what is good.
And so Jesus has come to rescue us from our sin, to forgive us our sins,
and to invite us into his family.
And that's why we celebrate Christmas and we're like, "Wow, this is amazing."
The King of Kings humbled himself, became a little child to start his rescue mission
so that we can move from being estranged from God to become family of God
and be in that relationship and experience this peace, this joy, this life
that Jesus only gives.
Jesus really puts us on a different trajectory.
Before we know Jesus, we're enslaved to sin.
That's what God's Word says.
But when Jesus comes, he rescues us from sin.
He breaks us free.
And then we can learn to live a different way
because of Jesus being at work in our lives.
And we can rely on him.
He gives us the grace and the strength to become more loving people,
become the people he created us in the first place to be.
And so this is the incredible news of Christmas.
So there is room in God's family for all people.
It's for everyone.
Nobody is too far away.
Nobody is too broken or too messed up that they are outside the scope
of Jesus' rescue and love.
Nobody.
So that means that Christmas is also good news for every single person
because we can receive this gift of salvation, this gift of new life
that Jesus gives when we place our trust in him and believe in him
and turn away from our way of living apart from him.
Now, I was watching Instagram.
Anyone?
Scrolling.
Sometimes you get stuck in that endless scrolling to another thing.
And there was an image that I want to leave us with.
There was a family that asked this little boy to unpack a gift.
And so he unpacks it.
He opens up the package, and he gets out a picture frame.
And on the picture frame was a family picture, but he was not in it.
And then there was a note that said, "Next year, we want you to be part
of this family picture."
And so the kid was trying to figure out what this meant, and it was like,
his name was Connor.
"Connor, we want to adopt you.
We want you to be part of our family."
Now, on Christmas, what Jesus is saying is, "I want you to be part of my family.
I want to adopt you.
I want to welcome you in because he loves us, and there's room for every
person in God's family."
And so that same gift is extended to us, and it's just up to us, you know,
whether or not we receive it.
So this, indeed, is the great news of Christmas, that Jesus has come,
that he has addressed our sin issue, that he forgives us, gives us new life,
and that he invites us to be part of his family because he wants you to be
part of his family picture as well.
And so as we celebrate Christmas today, as you celebrate with friends and
family, I want to encourage you to take some time to just express thanks,
if you know Jesus, to what Jesus has done, or to talk about Jesus if you
don't know Jesus yet and what Jesus means.
And to, yeah, thank God for the greatest gift of all.
And so what I'd love to do is pray for you, but I also want to invite the
worship team to come back up as well.
So let me pray for us.
Jesus, we thank you so much that you didn't leave us stuck in our sin,
but you chose to come in a way that we can receive you as a child, as a
little baby, vulnerable, though you are the King of kings.
And you came to ultimately to lay down your life on the cross for us and to
rise from the dead so that we can be forgiven and become new creations in you.
And so we thank you, Jesus.
We worship you, and we are just humbled and moved and touched by you,
that you love us so much.
And we thank you that you make us part of your family, that you give us a new
family to belong to, and that we can know your love, your acceptance, and
also the new life that we have in you with peace and joy and hope that we do
not know without you in the same way.
So we give you all the glory, and I pray this in your name, Jesus.
Amen.
[Piano music]
So what better way would it be to wrap this Christmas up, this Christmas
service with another carol?
And I think as we were singing "O Come All Ye Faithful" earlier, I was just
really moved when we were singing "O Come Let Us Adore Him," and we'll
praise his name forever.
So let's all stand.
[Piano music]
Let's sing.
♪ O come let us adore him, O come let us adore him, O come let us adore him, Christ the Lord. ♪
Sing it again.
Let's sing that one more time.
O come.
♪ O come let us adore him, O come let us adore him, O come let us adore him, Christ the Lord. ♪
Sing one more praise.
♪ We'll praise his name forever, we'll praise your name forever, we'll praise your name forever, Christ the Lord. ♪
Sing it again.
♪ We'll praise your name forever, we'll praise your name forever, we'll praise your name forever, Christ the Lord. ♪
Yes, Jesus, we praise your name forever.
We thank you for the day.
May you be with us as we're going to enter into the cookie feast and enjoy cookies with each other.
And just wish each other a Merry Christmas.
We pray this in your name, Jesus, amen.
Merry Christmas, everyone.
Hit it.
I'm ready.
[music]
Hey, go over there.
You can go.
[music]
Go buy the cookies over there.
♪ I want to wish you a Merry Christmas, I want to wish you a Merry Christmas from the bottom of my heart. ♪
♪ I want to wish you a Merry Christmas, I want to wish you a Merry Christmas, I want to wish you a Merry Christmas from the bottom of my heart. ♪
♪ Feliz Navidad, Feliz Navidad, Feliz Navidad, prospero año y felicidad. ♪