Have a seat. Hey, we're really excited. We're continuing our series in public faith. If you've
become into the Vine for a little while, you'll know we're in this series where we're looking at
how we're not to be ashamed of the gospel and how our faith in Jesus should not just shape what we
do for 90 minutes on a Sunday like this, but actually should be transformative in every area
of our life and that we are in a window at the moment of grace in our city. And now more than
ever in the history of our city, we should be reaching out with the faith, reaching out with
the gospel, reaching out with the hope of Jesus. And through this series, we're going to be looking
at doing that in a myriad of different ways. We're going to be looking at what that looks like in our
workplace, what it looks like in our spheres of influence, but also as we're looking at today
in our families. And I'm really excited we got Pastor Promise with us today. Can we get our
hands together as Promise comes? So why don't we stretch out our hands? Let's pray for Promise.
Yeah, Father, we thank you for Promise, for Kayla, for the kids, for this incredible family that
you uprooted from the US a number of years ago, brought to Hong Kong and have made Hong Kong
their home. And Lord, we're just grateful that as they are here in this community, Lord, we get to
benefit from their love, their family, their relationship. And Lord, I know that you've
blessed Promise with great gifts. And one of those is to preach and teach your word. And Lord,
we're just grateful that we get as a church community to sit and to hear, but not to look
to the man, but to look to the God behind the words. And so Holy Spirit, would you fill Promise?
Would you strengthen him? But Lord, we open our hearts to the to the wonders of what you would
want to do right now by the planting of the seed of your word in us. And we thank you for this in
Jesus name. Everyone says amen. All right. Good morning, everybody. How y'all doing? Good, good.
I'm just glad you know what how y'all doing means. You know, as an American, when I say y'all,
I wasn't sure if it'd be like, what's happening? Anyways, as Andrew said, I am Promise, one of the
pastors here at the Vine, and I get to oversee all of the creative items that happens here. And
it's quite a lot of fun, a lot of joy. I also get to preach here every so often. So let's dive into
it. All right. Is that okay? You guys ready? Are you awake? Are you hungry? Okay, cool, cool. You're
awake. Good, good, good. So we're in week four of our sermon series here at the Vine on public
faith, a series that is designed to help us consider our spheres of influence and think
around how does the gospel shape and prepare me to be an example in the places that I go,
in the people that I'm with, in the spaces that I'm in. Public faith is an idea of both demonstrating
and displaying what it is that we truly hold value, what we think is most important, our faith
in Jesus. If you were to summarize it into one little phrase, it'd be this, the question of how
are we living externally what we believe internally? All right. That is the question that kind of sits
central around this public faith series. Pastor Andrew, a couple of weeks ago, would have opened
up this whole series reminding us of the state of the world, which is chaos and craziness and so
many things happening. And it's a challenging place. To be fair, the world's always been
kind of chaotic, and there's always been a bunch of crazy things happening, nothing really different
in that space. But we're now heightened, have a heightened awareness of the levels of brokenness
within our society, within our culture, within our world. And the question that we have to ask
ourselves is how do we respond to that? As Christians, what do we bring to that story?
How will we live? And I think for a lot of times for us, we look at the big picture and it's like,
okay, well, you know, how do I live my public faith is how I live and work and how I live when
I'm outside and making sure I don't kick the old lady on the MTR if they make me mad or things like
that. We think of our public faith as kind of the external bit, which is true, but perhaps there's a
place in our life, an area and an aspect of our lives where we hold the greatest influence.
Perhaps there's a part of our life that we've overlooked a little bit,
where the way that we live publicly can actually dictate and shape and bring the good news of
Jesus into a life. This space, of course, is within our families, it's within our children.
I think it's quite easy to overlook this area, but today we're going to spend some time really
diving into what it looks like to be a Christian in the home, to be, have a public faith within
our family, specifically to our kids. I am a parent of two young children and I have to be honest,
when I first became a father, I made a deal, not just with myself, Jethro and Emma heard it too,
I said I would not be the pastor who would use my beautifully, beautiful children as a
demonstration for every sermon intro. And I have not. I will not be the pastor that will show you
how beautiful my kids are. And they're beautiful. I mean, they are spectacular looking, right?
I have held back, but then this sermon series came up and Andrew, maybe he knew, he was like,
you know what, promise you're going to preach on parenting. And I'm like, oh, if there's a moment
to show you guys how cute my kids are, if there's ever the opportunity for me to display my beautiful
children, today is it. So I've held back for four years, but today the gloves are off. Let's take a
look at the screen. Look at how beautiful little Elias James Armstrong is and Remy Aloysius.
Next slide. There's more, don't worry. Hold your applause. Look at this. Look at Elias,
just smiling. Look at Remy just being perfect, little bow in her hair. Keep going. I said I
held back for four years, guys. We have another slide. Come on, let's show some more. Look at
Elias. He serves, he volunteers. You can volunteer too. He could be a model. I know it. He plays
soccer. And then of course we have to give Remy her own shout out. So last slide. Look at Remy.
She can drive. Like, come on guys. She's only one and she can drive a whole car. The girl's
incredible. Okay, okay, okay, I'll stop. Sorry. I do this kind of making fun of my father-in-law,
who's probably watching today, Ron. But every time, every time he gets up to preach,
the sermon isn't about parenting. But he finds a way. He is unashamed about making sure his
grandkids show up in every photo and every sermon. So every time there's a sermon, these kids are
there. So this is for you. And I finally get the chance to do that today. Anyways, to the actual
sermon. Let's get back to the point. The idea of parenting, parenting is such an interesting
concept. We are in a world that is surrounded with resources about how to raise your kids well.
Whether it's podcasts or books or more books or diagrams or whatever it is. There's so many
ways and people with so many opinions and everyone has an idea of what it looks like to raise your
kid well. So does our faith. You know, the Bible actually gives us not a formula. We don't follow
formulas in scripture. But the Bible gives us a dynamic framework on what it looks like to raise
our children well. And it's something we have to hold on to because in light of the craziness of
the world, we are tempted to either fully withdraw and try to escape, thinking that's the best form
of parenting. But surely there must be a better way, right? In light of the chaos, some of us
think it's best to just try to over-legislate and make the world look a certain way and force Christ
onto it. Surely there must be a better way to parent. And in the light of how the world looks,
some of us feel the temptation to just give in, just do what it loves us doing, just fall in line.
Surely conformity is not what we're called to within our faith with our kids. So when we take
a look at scripture, we find ourselves in that tension because to be honest, all of those things
are viable options. All of those things, it's natural that we're drawn to them. We have to
turn our attention to the place, to the author who designed it all. And so we'll look today and
see exactly what is it that God has designed for parenting? What is it meant to look like? What is
he hoping that our parenting actually produces? Because parenting in public faith may not be,
you know, the first thing you think of, but there is a way in the way that we parent that we can show
people who we believe, what we stand up for. So how can the way we parent display
our faith to our families and those in our communities? Well, so in the scriptures,
where we find this is found in Ephesians 5 and 6. Across Ephesians 5 and 6, Paul does something
incredible. He doesn't just talk about one topic. He looks at a couple of things, kind of all in
order together with similarities behind it. The things he addresses first are husbands and wives,
and then he follows up and addresses slaves and masters. And then lastly, he will address children
and their parents. And if you look closely, you'll notice that one of each of these pairings
has something in common with the others. Within that Greco-Roman culture,
one person in both of these pairings had the upper hand. One of these has the benefit where the other
doesn't. One of these has more resources. One of these has more influence, more status. One has,
and one has not. And yes, we're going to look at the details of parenting, but perhaps I don't want
us to miss what Paul is actually trying to get us to understand here, is that as Christians,
when we find ourselves in those positions as the one who has in relation to the one who has not,
how will we respond? Will we lord over them? Will we actively dominate them,
abuse the vulnerable and the used? Or will we just seek our best interest,
passively ignoring them and pushing them further down? No, surely the gospel shows us something
different than that. Christianity doesn't call us to look at the weaker and focus just on our
own things, and that's what Paul's going to look at in both of these areas. When he talks about
husbands and wives, the word he's going to give for how they're meant to respond and live with
one another is this idea of mutual submission, which is unheard of at that time. Mutual submission.
Again, one is greater, one is less, and he says mutual submission. Okay, take slaves and masters.
What does he say about those guys? Mutual respect and sincerity of heart and serving. Imagine a
master serving a slave. Unheard of at that time. This togetherness in each of these commands leads
us to this mutual, correlated responsibility that Paul's gospel centered on. And so when we get to
the idea of children, what does he say about our children and parents? How does he want them to
engage? Well, it says this, "Honor your father and your mother, which is the first commandment
with a promise, so that it may go well with you and that you may enjoy long life on the earth.
Fathers, do not exasperate your children. Instead, bring them up in the training and instruction of
the Lord." Let me pray for us. Jesus, we come before you this morning and we ask that these
not just be words, but we know that all scripture is God-breathed, and we know that your spirit can
help us understand. So we open our hearts and we say, "Help us understand. Help us see your intent.
Help us understand your heart. Give us the courage to respond to your gentle leanings as we study
your word. In Jesus' name, amen." So how can our parenting be a demonstration of our public faith?
So I grew up with this verse and my grandmother used to quote it to me, but let me tell you,
I didn't know there was a part two. I thought it was only honor your father and your mother. That's
all she ever quoted to me, right? So I knew this one well. She also quoted to me because it's the
only command with a promise and my name is Promise. So she was like, "You really need to learn this
one." No, but it actually says this, "Fathers, do not exasperate your children. Instead, bring them
up in the training of the Lord." For the record, before we dive too deep, he says, "Fathers," but
I don't want any mothers turning to their husbands and pointing all the responsibility to them, okay?
It's not saying only the dads, only the males are responsible. This is a joint effort. Paul is
speaking to the whole household, addressing fathers, but speaking to all of the guardianship,
okay? So we're clear on that, moms? We're all good? Great. I think it's very interesting what
Paul says here. Before he tells you what to do, notice what he does. He tells you what not to do.
Look at the flow of this structure. First thing he does is tells you what to remove. I think there's
a really deep wisdom in the idea of omission for growth. I think for so many of us in areas where
we want our lives to be better, the temptation is, "How do I add more stuff? What new steps do I do?
What other book do I read? What other podcast do I subscribe to?" But sometimes it's not about all
the doing. Sometimes it's about what you're not doing that ends up making the greatest influence.
I'm curious how our faith can look to those around us. How can it be a public declaration of what we
believe? Is there something in our parenting, in our families that looks different? Is there
something missing in our families that looks something like the gospel, that points towards
something of Jesus? Our parenting will look different if we consider what we need to omit
as well. And what is that omission? Paul says it like this, "Fathers, do not exasperate your
children." How many of you used the word exasperate this week? Didn't think so. It's not a word we
commonly speak about, right? I didn't really know what it meant. I couldn't really even say it
correctly. Karla and I laughed about it all week. I couldn't say it correctly, kept messing it up.
So we're going to give you some other words to consider, right? So other versions of scripture
would say, "Do not provoke your children." We're common with that word, right? Or even more simpler,
"Do not stir them up to anger." And the only other time that this specific verb is used in scripture
is in Romans, when Paul is talking about sin upon sin upon sin that stirs God up to wrath.
Heavy connotation. So what we get from the semantic range, what Paul is saying, he says,
"Do not remove this aspect. Do not do this." He is saying, "Do not provoke your children into a
specific state." I think it's very important that we need to recognize that there are things that
we could be doing that actually assist our kids down the wrong path. There are things we could be
adding onto their lives, whether it's expectations or hopes and dreams or desires that actually lead
them down the wrong way. Paul calls parents to consider, "Are there things that we're putting
on our kids?" And I think the honest answer is hard sometimes because we live within the world.
We don't live in a vacuum. We live within culture, and culture has expectations, right? Culture gives
us a pattern of how we ought to live. Sometimes cultures and our traditions, we're unaware of how
impactful they are. And sometimes the expectations of our culture, we subconsciously put on our
children, leading them into further anxieties, into further despair or insecurities or to not
feeling valued, independent of the things they can accomplish, specifically here in Hong Kong.
We live in a culture that is very honor-shamed. We want to decrease our shame. We want to hide
the things that look bad. We want to increase our honor and make sure that our public face looks
good. But how does that look? How does that lead us into conformity? Well, we don't want to stand
out. We don't want to be the one set of families whose kids didn't make it into a really good
primary school at age two. Or we don't want to be the one family whose kids is not on their way to
the UK or the US or to Europe or to whatever glorified place that we think is so incredible
to become a doctor or a lawyer. All those things are great, but we don't want to not have our kids
do that. That's super important to us. It's the pressure of the culture which impacts the
decisions that we make. It's oftentimes unseen and unspoken. There's two other aspects, I think,
that end up holding very big positions in Hong Kong. This idea of security, this idea of success.
We desire to be successful. Some of us work 24/7. We don't know what the idea of a work-life
balance is because to earn, to earn, to gain, to gain, to accomplish, to accomplish. This is...
Our city is a hard-working city. I'll give it that. We work hard in this city. We don't play
around, right? We get stuff done. But man, where's the line between hard-working and overdoing it?
And how does that impact the expectations we put on kids, on our children? We want to feel safe
from the threat of financial ruin, so we work 24/7. We buffer ourselves, record for ourselves
the things that we think will make us feel the most safe. This is only natural. We all do,
and it's not like the pastor promises like the good one here. We're all guilty of it. The temptation
is strong to be self-sufficient, having our own needs always met by ourselves, or at least
projecting the image that all is well. The subject of ourself being secure and successful is one of
the biggest motivators in our society. And what does that conformity oftentimes do when it tempts
us? Well, conformity in this case often looks like deprioritizing what our faith in Jesus would deem
top priorities. Conformity often looks like deprioritizing the things that God would say
should be the number one thing, the things that you don't miss, the things that you prioritize
and you put on top of the list. Within a culture, in a world where there's so many other tensions
and pressures, conformity can often look like switching that around a little bit,
shifting it a little bit to better reach those goals.
When we're faced with this type of conformity, the question we have to ask is,
will we conform to culture, or as scripture calls us to do, will we be transformed by the renewing
of our mind? We can't live outside of culture. The call is not to say that culture is evil,
but the call is to recognize the flaws and the brokenness that there is in such systems.
So we don't escape it, we don't run from it, we don't just sit and hurl critiques at it. At the
same time, we don't buckle. We cannot conform to it because when raising our kids, they will feel
the decisions that we make. We've got to be able to raise our kids in environments of
unconditional love and acceptance despite the hard-working nature of our city, despite what
they achieve. They've got to know that they are valued independent of what it does for our social
standings. So for the Christian parent, here's the question I want us to wrestle with. Are we
putting expectations and pressures and dreams on our kids that God has not?
I phrase it like this, referencing Matthew 11, where we're told that we come to Jesus weak and
weary and tired and exhausted, and Jesus puts something on us. God puts something on us. We
don't just come to God and he's like, "I'll take everything away and you're fine." No, he puts a
thing on us. He gives us a burden. He gives us a load to carry, but look at what it says, how God
describes this burden. Matthew 11 reads like this, "Come to me, all you who are weary and burdened,
and I will give you rest. Take my yoke upon you and learn from me, for I am gentle and humble in
heart, and you will find rest for your souls." Here's where it gets good. "For my yoke is easy,
and my burden is light." There's light in the darkness, and there's light in the light.
There's light and easy, and then there's all the things I just described about our culture.
Which ones are we putting on our kids? All right. We can't put expectations on our kids that God
doesn't put on us. We've got to be within the world, but not of the world. Understand and relate
to culture and traditions without outputting its pressures and its expectations on others,
especially our kids, because Christ didn't come to set us free so that we could put other people
in bondage. That's not the gospel. And then Paul would say this, after illuminating for us the
first idea of what we need to remove, what we need to omit, he would say this, "Bring them up."
Sorry. "Instead, bring them up in the training and instruction of the Lord." First word he says
is "instead" here, so you can read it as, "Do the opposite." All right? So don't provoke them to
anger. Don't stir them to anger. Instead, do the opposite of that. Bring them what? Up in the
training and the instruction of the Lord. These two words here, training and instruction. Let's
first break down training. Training is something that we might be familiar with. It's quoted as
a discipline. It speaks to the idea of a learned skill of control or to balance or restraint.
The Old Testament would speak of training in Proverbs 22, where it would say, "Train up a child
in the way he should go, and when he is older, he will not depart from it." In the New Testament,
Paul would continue this idea of training. Train yourself for godliness. It's a constant theme.
Training is important to understand because it's not just what you say. It's also what you do.
Training is a way of living by example. It's a show and tell type of thing. I'll give you a good
example. This past Saturday, Friday, Thursday, whatever day it was, we were celebrating Jethro's
soon-to-be wedding, having a little bachelor party for him. And the thing that we did was we went to
a spin class. Raise your hand if you know what a spin class is. I'm like the people who didn't
raise their hand. I had no idea what a spin class was. So maybe about two hours before I googled it,
and I saw bicycles, and I was like, "This is not for me. I don't work out. I don't exercise. This
can be terrible." So we get to the spin class. We get on our gear, get the little shoe things on. I
don't want to click in or anything like that. It's a horrible time. I struggle. My legs are tired. My
hips are tired now. I'm an old man. 35 is getting old, guys. Pray for me. I mean it. I feel old.
I've got grays, man. It's serious. Anyways, my point being, my point being that the training
is necessary to show you what to do. We had an instructor, a spin instructor, and she didn't
just tell us what to do. She didn't just say, "Get on your bike. Click this in." It wasn't all
spoken. Actually, the way that I learned of what to do was by watching her example. Like, she
actually got on the bike. She actually sweat with us. She kept going, kept doing a little dance or
whatever. And I was sitting there like, you know, under my breath, angry the whole time.
Being honest, Nathan could tell you it was a terrible time.
But the idea of training is that there has to be some form of an example. As parents,
it's not just enough to say, "Do as I say, not as I do." We actually have to show and make an
example of our lives, which is beautiful because this level of design by God is so particular.
You can't exemplify what you don't have. How are you going to be an example of what you don't got?
Like, imagine if she would have gotten on the bike and was, "After about two seconds,
I think we would have been done. We would have been out." I don't want to be trained by someone
who doesn't know what's happening, right? But we need you to actually have that example in your
life. To be an example, you have to first have the same priorities. You have to be in godliness as
well to train another in godliness. God is calling us as parents to make the time to spend with our
kids. I'm not going to hark on this too much, but in Hong Kong, we're busy, we're busy, we're busy.
Everyone is busy. And it's going to be very hard to be an example for your kids if we're too busy.
And we're busy for lots of good reasons. We produce a lot.
But if we're going to be examples for our kids, then we've got to actually be there. And we can't
outsource it to a good Christian school to be the one that trains our children in faith. We can't
outsource it to K4C once a week to train our children in godliness. We can't outsource it to
our aunties and helpers because we aren't there. We've got to decide what's important to us.
We've got to realign our priorities. This is what training looks like.
The second thing Paul talks about after training is the idea of instructing or teaching. Teaching
is a pretty simple concept that I think we all understand, so I won't hark on it too much.
But the idea of teaching means that you do speak. It is about the words that you say. It's about a
communication method. It's giving instruction on how to operate. And we know this is pretty
important from Deuteronomy 6, verse 6-7, where it says, "These commands that I give you from God
today are to be on your hearts. Impress them on your children. Talk about them."
I'm going to stop there. Talk about them. Impressing them on your children, how? Teach them.
Speak about it. Let the words of your mouth actually speak of the gospel that you align
yourself to, that you believe in consistently. Because our kids hear lots from us. Conversation
matters. If you were to ask our kids, "What do you think mom and dad believe just based off of
what they talk about?" Would they see mom and dad as a person that's really up to date on pop culture,
really stressing out about the anxieties of the world, really good at market research and analyzing?
Would they actually say anything about our faith? I mean, ask yourself, "What do I talk about around
them? What comes out of my mouth?" Because out of our mouth, the heart overflows. We've got to
actually speak about the things that we find valuable. God is calling us to speak. And I think
for me, I did the homework as well. And I was like, "What would Elias say if you asked him that
question?" He'll be here at the two o'clock, so you can ask him then. But I'm pretty sure he would
say that he loves photography cameras, that he loves Korean barbecue, which I had twice. It was
certainly so good. But there's so many things you talk about, sports and all this stuff and fashion
and yada, yada, yada. And I have to consider what am I actually saying to my boy? If I want him to
grow up in Christ, it can't just be my hobbies that he hears me. It's got to be the words of God.
So I encourage you to consider what it is that you speak to your children as well.
Last subject is the idea of the Lord. Who are we to instruct and train our children in? I've
already talked about the pressures and the things of society. We know that's not what we're meant
to train them in, but we have to recognize that we're tempted to do that because it's so prevalent.
But no, the things that we train our children in are the things of the Lord. And so it means
that we train and we teach our children about humility, about leadership that looks like
humbling yourself to serve others. It means that we train and teach our children, "Blessed are the
poor in spirit." It means that we train and teach our children that exploitation of the vulnerable
for our own benefit is wrong, that profit isn't king, that others matter, that we love our neighbor.
We love those who look different than us. We love those who have different ideological leanings than us.
This is the tenets of our faith. This is the expression of God's work in the world. So we've
got to be able to teach and train our kids in these ways. Are we teaching them Christ or are we teaching
them culture? In order to bring this to a very practical perspective, I've invited two people
from our community to come up and share with us some of their perspectives and how they live
a life. And so I'm going to invite to the stage Ivy and Nelson. Give them a round of applause, everyone.
[applause]
Hold on. So Andrew fell off the stage last week and we got it in the name of Jesus stage. Be good.
Be good. All right. All right. Show us again. Okay. So guys, this is Ivy and Nelson, everyone.
They are an incredible couple. Why don't you just go ahead and give us a brief, you know,
one-line introduction of who you are and your name. This is our second time doing it, so I feel like
Nelson's ready. All right. Good afternoon, everyone. My name is Nelson. I'm an early childhood educator.
Hi, I'm Ivy. I'm Nelson's wife. I'm also a teacher. I think I'm getting hungry.
All right. These guys serve, I've seen them at VBS serving with our kids. I remember the first VBS I
brought my son to. He was terrified to go by himself, but if Ivy was there, he stayed in the
room. So I feel like I'm deeply indebted to you. Thank you for that. Yeah. So I just want to ask
you guys a couple of questions just around what we've talked about so far to hear some practical
examples from what it looks like in your lives. The first question being, how do you see your
parenting as a demonstration of your public faith? It's just how we trained her. Okay. We
trained our daughter to be a responsible person. We have always said that, and still training,
but we also told her to put God first in everything that she does,
wherever it's like school or home or anything that she does. We try to be
a friend with her or supporting with whatever that she has to do, but
we always tell her that God really will direct her life.
Ivy, for you, the second question is in your home, what does it look like to put the right
expectations first? How do you even discern what is of God and what is not for your kids?
Okay. To know whether it's from God or not, we always pray. There's a lot of praying in my home,
in our family, if we don't know what to do, or even if we think we know what we do,
we are doing, it's praying. Right expectation, that's not always easy because we think we know
what we expect for our kids, but it's always God's plan that always comes through.
So we always have to pray about that. Yeah. So lots of prayer. Lots of prayer. That's a good
answer. And then I think this one is pretty important. What does it look like to prioritize
your life in a way that reflects your values that you believe in, especially when culture propels us
to prioritize being successful or being secure? First and foremost, we prioritize Jesus.
We prioritize praying and we prioritize family. We emphasize on praying because we pray
morning, nighttime. We don't get out of the house without praying for each other. So it's important.
Even if you're going to miss your bus. Yes, that's true. Yes. It's a struggle sometimes
because our daughter is a teenager and then she has strong feelings. Sometimes she has big feelings
that we don't invalidate her feelings whenever she's feeling something. We don't just shut it
down. We say, okay, we understand, but don't stay there. God is always with you. Yeah.
What about you, Ivy? For you, how do you feel? How does it look like to prioritize your life in a way
that reflects your values? Yeah. That also means saying no to old ways, old habits,
certain music that we don't listen to anymore. But he still listens to secular music. We still
enjoy it. But saying no, like no. I'm saying no now. I'm saying no a lot. Sorry. Yeah. But things
that we feel like don't honor or glorify God, then we have to say no to that. That's really good.
Thank you guys. Can we give them a round of applause, everyone? Thank you so much.
So I have them share and I share all of this because the idea of parenting is not an easy
thing. It comes with quite a lot of complications. I feel like most parents are doing their best.
We're trying extremely hard. So I just want to say, if there be a grace on you, this isn't meant
to be like a knock you over the hand so you're not doing it right. I recognize that it is
challenging being a parent. But I think the benefit that we have is that we have the Holy
Spirit to lean on. And something they shared about, we have prayer. Prayer being that silent
but probably most effective thing we can do. I was in Washington, D.C. this past summer with my
brother. We were both kind of like, I don't know, talking about our trauma together because it's
what you do these days. And we're just thinking about like, well, how crazy is it that we ended
up as pastors? Right? Like he's a pastor in the states. I'm a pastor here. My dad was a pastor.
My wife's father is a pastor. And his father is a pastor. There's a lot of pastors in our
lineage. Anyways, so we're trying to figure out how crazy is it that we're pastors given
the shady things that we were involved in as kids. Like, man, we had so many opportunities to really
go off the deep end. Like, sin was everywhere. You properly had to flee from it. There were so many
countless opportunities. I think back to my teenage years. My goodness, my university years.
Like, there is a God because I should not be a pastor. I should not be here. There are so many
opportunities to just completely lose it, completely mess up, to fall into God knows
what. And we're both trying to figure out because, you know, I'm the older brother. He's the middle
child. So I expect that of him. But he didn't expect that of me. And we're like, how did we
both end up in such challenging like childhoods and university days? And yet we're both like
pastors now. How do we say as Christians, what was the secret? And it wasn't our strength and
our ability to abstain from certain sins or our ability to just walk away or just say no.
We weren't strong enough for that. We didn't have that discipline.
We accredited to, we thought through it. We were like, what is it that happened so much,
more than anything in our lives? And it was the way that our parents raised us specifically,
my mother and her prayers. Y'all, my mom prayed a lot, a lot, a lot for me to end up semi-normal.
That woman prayed, y'all, like so many prayers. And I don't think I fully understood it. But man,
without those prayers, I don't know that I'd be standing here today. My brother and I could not
be who we are now without the investment of my mom's prayers. She prayed every single day at 5
AM. She would anoint me in my sleep. I'd wake up with oil on my head, y'all.
What was I dreaming about? I don't know. But this is what, growing up in an African home,
the prayer was serious. They prayed and prayed because we know that apart from Him,
we can do nothing, right? We have to be dependent on God. And that prayer shaped everything. I want
to share one prayer that was super impactful for me specifically. Every Monday night, my mom and I
and my dad would sit up at the top of the stairs next to my parents' door, and we would have a
Bible study together, go through Scripture, read it. I found it terribly boring because I was a kid.
But one of the things my mom used to make me do is that at the end of it, we would have to pray.
And the prayer would always be Colossians 1, starting at verse 9, going to verse 14.
This drove me crazy. I got tired of this prayer. But my mom used to, we would pray it first.
And then if you look closely, you'll see that a word that's represented a lot here, or that is
repeated a lot here, is the word "you." It's like, since we heard about you,
now we start praying for you, for God to fill you. My mom would take this prayer,
and she would substitute my name for every "you." So she would pray for this reason. Since today,
we heard about promise. We've not stopped praying for promise. We continually ask God to fill
promise with the knowledge of His will, through the wisdom and understanding of His Spirit gives,
so that promise may live a life worthy. And she'd make me pray this over myself as a kid, all the
time. I share this example because there comes times where we don't know the right words to
pray. We don't have the right spiritual language when it comes to our kids, and we just don't know
what the next step is. This is something that I've adopted in my family. And nothing really
makes me emotional, guys, but my kids, that's where it hits. And so praying for my children,
man, I can pray all day. And so I would pray like this. I would say, "For this reason,
since the day we heard about Elias, we have not stopped praying for Elias. We continually ask God
to fill Elias with the knowledge of His will, through all the wisdom and understanding that
the Spirit gives, so that Elias would live a life worthy of the Lord and please Him in every way,
bearing fruit in every good work, growing in the knowledge of God, being strengthened with all
power, according to His glorious might, so that Elias would have great endurance and patience,
giving joyful thanks to the Father who has qualified Elias to share in the inheritance
of His holy people in the kingdom of light. For He has rescued Elias from the dominion of
darkness, and He has brought Elias into the kingdom of the Son He loves, in whom we have
redemption and the forgiveness of sins." You don't have to be a pastor or a deep theologian,
have a seminary degree to do this. Perhaps this is your first step. It doesn't have to be Colossians
1, 9. That's just what my mom prayed for me, so I pray it for my son. But all of Paul's letters,
he starts off with these prayers. And imagine if you pray this daily over your kids. Or maybe you
start with weekly, once a week. Put their name in there. And maybe that can be your first step
in training and instructing your children in godliness. Amen? Let's pray.
Will you go ahead and stand with me, and we'll pray together.
God, we recognize Your designs. Your Holy Spirit speaks through Your Word.
We just want to hear You. Would You open our ears, God?
Spirit, in the way that only You do, gently yet clear, would You guide us in Your truth?
On the things that we prioritize, on the things that we value, Holy Spirit, would You remove
in us what needs to be removed? Would You train and instruct us so that we might train and instruct
our children well? God, I pray for parents who are here this morning who are struggling,
who are just trying to get a good night's sleep because they have young ones. God, I pray that
You would be their strength. That You would strengthen their hands and their feet. That You
would be their rest and their hiding place. God, for those of us who had families that were less
than ideal, and the examples laid out for us may not be what we want to copy, Holy Spirit, would
You remind us that God is a good father? That our first identity is children of God? That You
are a good father? That You father well? Would You turn our eyes to You to see Your example and to
follow that? For those of us trying to find what the next step is, whether it be for our kids or
our adult children, God, we need Your help. We don't want strategies alone. We don't want books
alone. We need the Spirit of God. We need the power of the Holy Spirit to be what strengthens
us and what we infuse into our children. So now, Holy Spirit, would You be our strength? Would You
be our rock? Would You help us build ourselves upon You? Would You be our focus, God? Would You
speak to us? Would You lead and guide us as we do our best? Would You encourage those here who are
parents who need encouraging that they're going to be okay and that they have help, that they're
not alone, that no kid is too lost for You, God, that You work in all things? Lord, would You just
give us the discipline and the strength to pray for our children, to trust prayer?
We ask You this in Jesus' name, amen.