I'm so excited to be with you this morning. My name is Andrew. I'm one of the pastors here.
So if this is relatively one of your first times at the Vine, we're so glad that you're here.
I'm really blessed. Sandra's in the house here today. Sandra and John founded the Vine,
led the Vine for many years. Thanks for being with us, Sandra. We love you. Justine is back.
So nice to see Justine as well. And I know that there are so many other people that are visiting
with us. Joe, my mate from the UK, sounds so British, doesn't he? You love him. Yeah, mate.
But we know also you may be new as well. So grateful to have you with us.
We're in part two of a three-part series on justice, and in particular on God's heart for
justice. And what we've been saying over these weeks is that what we're teaching in you last
week, this week, next week, are foundational messages for who we are as the Vine. We feel
here at the Vine that we've been called as a church to put justice in God's heart, to justice
and for justice at the center of what we do as a community. And so this is your home already,
or if this is going to become your home, then you're going to hear us talk a lot about the
realities of the poor and the broken and the vulnerable in our society, in our city, in the
situation that we're here with. And we're going to challenge one another to be the church to the city
that is around us. Last week, as we started this series, I started by giving you a theology of
justice. I wanted us to really understand how justice sits at the heart of the biblical
redemptive narrative that we have in Scripture. And so we literally went from Genesis to Revelation,
unpacking the idea that the gospel, and this is really important, church, that the gospel
is not just the restoration of my relationship with God, as important as that is. That's certainly
a central part of the gospel. What we see in Scripture, that the gospel is the restoration
of not just a broken relationship here, but also a broken relationship here. That if the gospel
truly brings shalom, then the gospel has to rectify the four broken relational contexts that we see
happen in Genesis 1, 2, and 3. And we looked last week, didn't we, that in Genesis 1 and 2, God
creates humanity as the pinnacle of his heart, labels humanity as the image of God, and then
defines for humanity what is right and wrong. We said last week that God is the one that defines
for us what is right and wrong. And then God creates four relational contexts by which we
express the right and wrong of the Father. That's our relationship with God, our relationship with
ourselves, our relationship with others, and our relationship with creation. So in Genesis 1 and 2,
we see these beautiful relational contexts created. And at the end of Genesis 2, God stands
back from that, and he says those words, he says, "This is shalom." This is the way things were
meant to be. The world is now designed and is flourishing in the way in which it was created
to be. And then, of course, we saw Genesis 3, the intaking of sin, Satan's tricking of humanity to
think that they shouldn't just be image of God, but they can be gods themselves. And in taking
that fruit, what we see straight away is that humanity now begins to define what is right and
wrong. Where in Genesis 1 and 2, God defines what is right and wrong, in Genesis 3, humanity begins
to take on the ability or thinks that it has the ability to define what is right and wrong. And we
said last week that when humanity defines what is right and wrong rather than the divine,
we will always define it in a way that benefits ourselves, like myself, not you. Like I will
define it in a way where I will have an advantage over others and where there'll be self-preservation.
So last week, we saw Adam throwing his wife immediately under the bus when God shows up.
That brokenness of relationship begins to happen, and we begin to create right and wrong in the way
that we want it for the benefit of ourselves, and injustice is born. And then we saw, of course,
that God begins to restore this through the calling of a nation, Israel through Abraham.
We saw that importance of justice and righteousness, the reality that those
things work together within that nation, and yet also the idea of wickedness. And we said last week,
didn't we, that the wickedness or the way of injustice is wicked, and the wicked in the Old
Testament basically are willing to disadvantage the community for the advantage of themselves,
whereas the justice and righteous are willing to disadvantage themselves for the advantage of the
community. And so you get this beautiful picture in the Old Testament of what Scripture calls us to
in this idea of justice, but it's just beginning to be modeled for them. And then we see the
Exodus, and in the Exodus is that model that begins to happen. God takes his oppressed people
in compassion. He advocates on their behalf. Then he acts to bring them out of their slavery,
and he provides for them that great place of future flourishing in the promised land. And so we see
the Exodus story as God's model. He's beginning to show his people what this justice journey
can look like. But again, we saw in the Old Testament that there's this cycle of injustice,
that even though God is beginning to model it, even though God is beginning to redefine the
right and wrong for his people, the people are so steeped in sin, it so easily has entangled them
that they realize by the end of the Old Testament that they can't do it. They can't fix that
relationship with God. They can't fix the relationship with themselves. They can't fix
the relationship with others, and they certainly can't fix the relationship with the broken world
around us. And so there's this crying out at the end of the Old Testament, right? There's this
desire for God to step in and do what only God can do, because humanity cannot do it.
And then Jesus, this beautiful incarnation, fully God and fully human, the spoke that is
driven in that wheel of injustice to borrow Dietrich Bonhoeffer's beautiful picture.
And Jesus, because he's fully God and fully human, he is the spoke because he's fully God,
but then he's able to deal with sin because he's fully human. And being those two things together,
he begins to model for us a new way. Again, advocacy, again, work in action with his
miracles and the way that he serves and he teaches. And then that moment on the cross,
the moment on the cross where he gives his life so that we might know the fullness of life,
where he pays that price for the redemption of our sin, the blood poured out, the sacrifice
once and for all so that sin no longer has the final say. And then in his resurrection, the
creating of a new community, the church, a community that he fills with his spirit and
sends out into the world to now be his hands and feet, to disciple the nations, to bring them into
a new way of thinking. And all of the New Testament centers this on this idea of the gospel,
that the gospel is not just about the restoration of my relationship with God alone, as central as
that is. But as that relationship is also then healed and restored, then I have a restored
relationship with myself. I no longer consider myself a slave, but I am a child of God. I then
have a restored relationship with those around me. I've been brought into a family together,
and now there is peace amongst us as a community. And then because creation has been groaning,
but now it will no longer groan because Christ on the cross has paid the price and creation itself
longing for its own redemption and the gospel, if it is the gospel, if it is a gospel that brings
shalom, if it's a gospel that deals with the brokenness of sin, can't just fix this. It has
to also fix this, fix this, and fix that. That's the whole gospel. That was all last week in about
five seconds for you. Okay, so if that was helpful for you, or you're like, I need to understand that
a little bit more, can I invite you to go back next week, last week and have a listen to that
message. But basically, that's what we taught. There's a biblical mandate for justice. It sits
at the heart of the gospel. It's the restoration of all of those broken contexts. So now we stand
here in week two. And here's the question we should all be asking. If that is true, how should
we now live? Like, how do I now live in this world if that's the gospel? If we here at the Vine are
going to say we're people of the gospel, if I'm saying that being a person of the gospel is to be
involved somehow in the restoration of four of those relational contexts, how do I now live?
Like, what should be my agenda? What should be my priorities? Like, what should I be focused on in
the here and now? I'm not just waiting till I die to go to heaven. Like, I've got something to do now.
God's peeled the curtain back at the end of all things in Revelation 21 and 22. And He's shown
us a picture of every knee bowing, every tongue and tribe confessing. He's shown us a picture where
sin is no longer present, where the leaves of the trees are for the healing, where there's that
one tree of the tree of life, no more the tree of the knowledge of the new. He's peeled it back,
and He's saying to us, "Live on behalf of that vision now." So if God's heart is the restoration
of all things, the renewal of all things, if God's heart is justice, how should we now live?
I want to challenge us by saying this as direct as I can. You cannot call yourself a Christian
and remain distant to the injustice in society around you.
You cannot call yourself a Christian if you're not on behalf of the gospel.
And if the gospel is the restoration of all of those broken relational contexts,
and if justice sits in the heart of that, and if that's where God is taking us at the end of all
things in Revelation 21 and 22, if we're not on behalf of that now, you should stop calling
yourself a Christian. Because being centered in Christ means that I am centered in a context by
which it is painful and dying and hurting and sin is doing stuff in it. And I stand as a person with
Christ in humility, knowing I'm not the answer for everything. The world is never going to be
perfect until Christ comes back. We're living in this now, but not yet. But that does not mean I'm
mute. It does not mean that I haven't got something to say. It doesn't mean that the
gospel is to wait until he returns. No, the gospel has action now. And this call upon us as a people
of Christ is a wonderful thing. Paul, when he writes to the church in the New Testament, have
you ever noticed this? Right at the start of the letter, he doesn't just say this as it's like a
greeting thing. He says, "You are in Christ in Ephesus." Or he says, "You're in Christ in Colossae,
in Christ in Philippi." It's basically Paul's way of saying, "Don't you realize that your relationship
with Jesus is not just in Christ, you're in Christ in a context. You're in Christ in a city.
You're in Christ around a whole bunch of people that are desperately in need of the gospel. You're
in Christ in Corinth, in Christ in Philippi. And I want to say to you, if you live here in this city,
you're in Christ in Hong Kong. Not just in Christ, as amazing as that is, but God has planted you here
in Hong Kong. He did not do that by mistake. None of you, whether you're here for two weeks,
two months, two years, two decades, are here in Hong Kong by mistake. Our city desperately needs
the gospel. There are injustices at work around us. And if we're going to call ourselves a Christian,
we're going to realize that our relationship with Jesus has something to say to our context.
I'm in Christ in Hong Kong. That should mean something.
I had the privilege a number of years ago of meeting with one of my justice heroes. His name
is John Perkins. And John Perkins was a contemporary of Martin Luther King Jr. and was very involved
with the civil rights movement in the 60s. And he was speaking to a small group of us pastors
at this conference I was at. And he said this incredible thing. He said that the church of
Jesus is always at its best when it is a community of hope wrapping its arms around a community of
pain. And if we're in Christ in Hong Kong, and if we're the people of the gospel in this city,
then we should be asking ourselves, we have the hope. And we just sung about it. The joy of the
Lord is our strength. Not our great ability to sort out all the problems in the world,
not our wonderful strategies. No, our strength is the joy of the gospel. The fact that we have
been reconciled to God, reconciled to ourselves, reconciled to others, reconciled to creation.
And we have that message for everyone. And that should motivate us. That should put something
inside of us. That should ask us to go, okay, we are the community of hope. I get that piece.
What's the pain? Because if we're to be a church that's wrapping its arms around the pain,
we need to know what is the brokenness? What is the injustice? What is the suffering? What is the
pain around us that we can wrap ourselves around? So what I want to do is just share with you
just some high level ideas about that for us and for our city. And I want to do that in the
framework of this idea of us and God, us and ourselves, us and others, us and creation.
Let's start with us and God. This one should move your heart immediately.
Latest government statistics would say 16% of our city believe Jesus, have a relationship with
Jesus, or would call themselves Christian. 16%. Now, if you just look at people who regularly
attend church on a Sunday, well done. Thank you. You're here. That drops to 8%.
Now, this is a statistic that should really move your heart. 84% of our city do not know Jesus. 84%.
The church has been in Hong Kong for over a hundred years. I mean, even longer than that.
I mean, there's 1700 registered churches in our city right now. And 84% of the people in
this city don't know Jesus. That should burn something inside of you. That should place a
holy discontent inside of us. That church is not about some holy huddle coming in and experiencing
what we've experienced here this morning, as great as that is. And we love gathering here.
But if this is all it is, that 84% is not going to change. What we do when we gather here is we
are sent ones. We come and we worship and we experience and we weep and we cry and we pray
and we fill ourselves with love so that we then go and serve the context we've been placed in.
That 84% should do something in our spirits. What about us and ourselves? One of the things
that we've noticed recently is the mental health related issues in our city more than anything.
And what you can see here is that one in six people in Hong Kong have what's called common
mental health challenges. One in six adults in our city. When you break that down to just youth,
six years old to 17, that's one in four. 60% of the global suicides in the world happen in Asia.
Hong Kong ranks third on a list, on that list. That's a list we do not want to be ranking on.
We rank third on that list, only behind South Korea number one, Japan number two.
Last year or in 2023, there were a thousand and ninety two suicides in our city. That should
should do something to us. On the mental health side, the WHO organization would tell you that
you need about 10 psychiatrists for every 100,000 people. Hong Kong currently has 4.1 psychiatrists.
I don't know what the point one is, that's weird. But anyway, 4.1 psychiatrists to every 100,000
people in our city. UBS did a research report recently and they looked at the average working
hours in Hong Kong. Hong Kong has 50 hours of average work week. The global average is 36 hours.
I want to plant a church in one of the cities where 36 hours is the...come on church.
We live in a city that is driving its people way, way too hard.
What about us and others? This is really important that we understand the poverty context of our
city. 20% of Hong Kong people live below the poverty line in this city. We always think Hong
Kong is a wealthy place. That's one point, almost 1.4 million people out of 8 million live under the
poverty line here in Hong Kong. When you take the poorest person in Hong Kong and the wealthiest
person, there is an 81.9x kind of difference between the two. Now, here's the crazy thing.
When you did that statistic in 2019, that difference was only 44%. So in the last, what,
five years, it's gone from being a 44% difference to an 81.9% difference. In other words,
Hong Kong is getting further apart between the wealthy and the poor. The Gini coefficient is
a global standard to help to kind of signify the wealth-poor gap. Hong Kong's current Gini
coefficient is 0.54. Zero would be perfectly equal, one being the worst. We're right in the middle,
0.54. But hear this, that puts us in the top 10 of places in the world in terms of the gap between
the poor and the wealthy. Right now, it takes 5.3 years on average for somebody to get into
public housing in Hong Kong. 200,000 people in our city are living in less than 100 square foot.
Now, here's the thing, special education needs. A lot of children in our city are
struggling under disability or special education needs. Currently, right now,
there are 50,000 people, children, that will require at least 12 therapy sessions a year.
That's a total cost of $430 million, and most of that money is not being made available in the
public sector. Now, this should shock us when we realize that Hong Kong's current financial fiscal
reserves is $724.8 billion, which will increase to $983 million by 2028. That's the prediction.
In other words, our issue is not resource, it's distribution of that resource.
And what about finally, us in creation? Have a look at this. Hong Kong currently produces around
about 4 million tons of what's called metropolis, it's kind of like metropolis social waste or
something like that. But it's basically the waste that we create, 4 million tons of it,
of which on average is 1.44 kg per person per day. I'm glad to report that Singapore is higher at 1.88
kg per person per day. But the joke hides the reality that we're still one of the highest,
that places us within the top 20 cities in the world. Now, here's the thing that should
really wake us as a church, as a community. 1.3 million tons of that is food waste alone.
A third of our waste is food waste. What that means is that we love to eat,
we love to order everything on the menu, and we do not eat it all.
I'm going to say that one more time because some of us, myself, needed to hear this. We love to eat,
we order everything on the menu, but we do not eat it all. And when we're giving a third of our
waste is food, that needs something for us to be really thinking about. On the positive side,
I want to say this. The government has done some great work in the area of recycling and
are continuing to do a good work in the area of recycling. Right now, about 32% of our created
waste a year is recycled here in Hong Kong. That's not where we want it to be overall,
but that is much better than the less than 12% some five years ago. So Hong Kong has done a
good job and the government has policies in place to try to change the recycling dynamics of our
city. In terms of pollution, 20 days last year were dedicated as like dangerous levels of pollution.
We're currently ranked about 63rd, I think it is, out of a global index of 138 countries when it
comes to pollution. So pollution continues to be a challenge in our city. Now, the reason why I want
to show you some of those things is because it's really important that we understand what is the
pain that we need to be wrapping our arms of hope around. But when we see statistics like that,
it would be easy for us to feel a bit despondent. It'd be easy for us to feel like, "Whoa, that's
like a lot of bad stuff. I don't know how to respond to those statistics, Andrew. I don't
know what to do. I'm feeling pretty weighed down by it." And oftentimes what happens for us when
we hear stuff like this is that we retreat further rather than press in. And I want to say that, yes,
the statistics are quite strong, but we have to hear this. We are the community of hope. Like,
if anybody has the answer to this, then surely it's the local church and its partnership with
the many NGOs that do great work in our city. That should be the starting point for our thinking. Yes,
these statistics are shocking and they should shake something within us, but not shake us to
despondency, shake us to action. They should make us want to stand up more, want us to be more
Christian in our city, want us to live the hope of the gospel more. Now, you have to understand
that for justice to happen in areas of injustice in society, basically sociologists will tell you
that four things need to happen. Education, connectedness, adaptability, and resource.
These four things are central to any transformation of any brokenness in society. Education,
connectedness, adaptability, and resource. What we have to understand is that we're living in a time
where all four of those things are the best that they've ever been. So if these are the four things
that are helpful for us when it thinks about changing society and doing something right within
the society around us, we've got to realize that those four things, I mean, we've never been more
educated as a generation than right now. Our access to education and to information has never been
higher. In fact, all the statistics I just showed you on the screen, I got from AI.
Now, I want you, I checked the sources, okay, so it wasn't just like hallucinating AI, okay.
These are good statistics from AI, but I went to AI. I mean, we're the most educated generation
there has ever been. We have access to information like never before. What about when it comes to
this idea of our connectedness? We're more connected than we have ever been before. Now,
yes, there's a whole thing around being more connected, but never feeling more alone. That's
a whole nother sermon we'll come to at some point. But the reality is we're more connected amongst
each other. We have the ability to connect like never before. Adaptability, because we have this
education and connectedness, we are people of the world more than we've ever been in terms of global
citizenships. We understand culture and background and people better than ever before. We understand
the ways in which different nations operate better than ever before. So we are more adaptable
to the realities of our world than we've ever been. And finally, resource. I mean, you just saw
in even the statistics for Hong Kong, our issue is not resources. There's incredible amounts of
resources. There's more resource generated in the world than in any other time in history right now.
But that resource is not going to the places where it necessarily needs to go. So here's the thing.
While we might want to be despondent, we are actually better equipped now to rise up and do
the things that we can do to begin to shape the world to the gospel like never before. The question
then is how. How do we do it? We know we've got a theological mandate to do it.
The gospel tells us we should be doing it. We know that we are in Christ in context and we've
been planted here in Hong Kong. We've seen that there is pain and we are called to be a community
of hope. How do we do it? Like how do we do it? Not just on a corporate level, like an institutional
level, like a church level. How do you do it? Because every single one of us in this room,
we have a spirit of influence where there is some injustice currently at work. For some of you,
it might be your family. Maybe there's a breakdown in a relationship in your family right now and
it's causing a lot of suffering and pain within the broader family dynamic. Maybe for some of you,
it's a school that you attend or a university you're a part of and you see some things happening
there that break your heart. Maybe you're working for an organization or a corporate and you know
that there are practices happening within your business that you know is creating a bigger gap
between the wealthy and the poor. Or whatever it might be. For all of us, it will look different,
but every single one of us, we are in Christ in that company, in Christ in that family,
in Christ in that context and we have to do something. What is it that we do? Okay,
so to help you, I want to just, in the time I've got left, just show you a really short quick model
of how we can actually live more justly based on what we've been talking about. I want to do it,
of course, by looking at Jesus and this moment in Jesus's life. I think in this moment in Jesus's
life, Jesus models for us how we can approach our context, our spirit movements, whatever
justice issue might be there for us. In this beautiful moment of Jesus's life, he shows us
four things that he does and I'm just going to break these down real fast. This is out of,
I'm going to turn back to it, it's out of Luke chapter 19. This is his triumphal entry as he
enters into Jerusalem. Notice what it says here. This is Luke 19, starting in verse 41 to verse 44.
As Jesus approached Jerusalem, he saw the city and he wept over it and he said this,
"If you, even you, had known on this day what would bring you peace,
but now it is hidden from your eyes. For the days will come upon you when your enemies will
build an embankment against you and encircle you and hem you in on every side. They will dash you
to the ground, you and the children within your walls. They will not leave one stone on another,
because you did not recognize the time of God's coming for you." This is a significant moment in
Jesus's ministry. We know from the scriptures that Jesus had a long relationship with Jerusalem. In
fact, he was there at eight days old, meeting there, and Simeon and Anna prayed over him,
prophesied over him. We know that he was back there for his bar mitzvah when he was about 13,
where he stayed behind at the temple and his parents lost him, a nightmare for them,
and he had to be in his father's house, that whole thing. But we also know that from the beginning of
his actual ministry, Jesus has specifically stayed away from Jerusalem. He's been ministering in
Galilee and Samaria and the surrounding areas, but he's been staying away from Jerusalem. He's
been staying away from Jerusalem because he understands that when he gets to Jerusalem,
things will begin, things will precipitate towards the cross. He knows because of that,
he needs to make sure that he does the work that he's been called to do before he gets there.
The turning point in the gospel of Luke is when Jesus says to the disciples, "Who do people say I
am?" The disciples respond, they say, "Well, Peter responds. He says, 'You're the Christ. You're the
Messiah.'" And then Luke records for us that it was from that moment that Jesus sets his face towards
Jerusalem, walking, wanting to now be and reconnect with his city. And here Luke describes the moment
where Jesus crests up the hill of Mount Olives and looks upon his city for the first time in what was
probably a number of years. And it says here he does four things. I want to show you what these
four things are because these become the kind of nucleus of a model for justice for each one of us.
The first thing Luke says is that he approaches. Now that might sound like not a big deal on itself,
but I want you to think about this. Jesus, again, he understood that when he gets to Jerusalem,
things are going to kind of happen that will lead him to his death. He understands that when he gets
there, the people in the triumphal entry who were shouting, "Hosanna, Hosanna," would later be the
ones that would be shouting, "Crucify him." He knew that what he was about to say and do around the
temple was going to basically give people the excuse that they needed to try to get him hung
on a Roman cross. But Jesus still approaches. And this is really important because Jesus understands
the pain that is about to come, but he doesn't stay away. In other words, Jesus makes a priority
of proximity. He says, "I'm going to come to this city now at the right time in the right way,
but I'm going to approach it even though I know it's going to be painful, even though I know it's
going to be hard, even though I know I'm going to get rejected, even though ultimately it's going
to lead me to my death, and everything inside of me would want me to stay away and just judge
Jerusalem from Galilee. I'm not going to do that." And he puts himself in a place of proximity with
his city. For some of you, there's a justice issue, an injustice in your family, an injustice in your
workplace, and it scares you to think that you might need to be involved in it. And that's
understandable because these things can be tough and scary. But what Jesus models for us immediately
is proximity. The whole gospel is a relationship gospel. And one thing that Christians are really
bad at is talking on behalf of the poor without knowing any of the poor. Talking on behalf of
the vulnerable, the trafficked, the marginalized, without even knowing any of them, having never
met them, having never seen them, having never put themselves in a place of understanding their
suffering and their pain, but just standing back and saying, "Well, I guess I should speak for them."
But then we speak for them in dangerous ways. Jesus draws near. Some of you, it's going to be
painful to draw near, but we have to always put proximity over productivity. Productivity without
proximity leads to pain. But when we are close, when we approach, we find ourselves in a place
where we can begin to do something. What does Jesus do? Well, the next thing it says is that he sees
Jerusalem. I love this because at first, this is physical. He's just come up and he's crested
the Mount Olives and he looks upon his city. Now, what he would have seen, I've actually done,
you can go to Jerusalem and actually do the walk that Jesus did. And you go up there and you see
the olive trees that are still there around the area of Mount Olives. They're still there to this
day. And then you can look on the view that Jesus had. And it's relatively similar. There's still
the walls of the old city there. There's the old city on Mount Zion. Now it's a mosque, of course,
but in Jesus's day, there was the temple right there. So you can kind of get a sense of what
Jesus was seeing. And he crests and he physically sees what's before him. Now, what I've done for
you here in this message is I've enabled you to crest a hill and physically see some things that
are happening in Hong Kong. Statistics, stuff that's important for us to be aware of, stuff
happening in mental health in our city, stuff happening in the pollution index and all that
stuff. So all that stuff we went through, that was us physically seeing what's happening in our
city. Does that make sense? Now, here's the thing, though. If that's all we do, just physically see
the stuff that's happening in our city, educate ourselves and get good statistics, that's all
helpful. But if that's all we ever do, we're no better than a secular NGO. The thing that makes
us Christians is we do what then Jesus does, which he doesn't just see physically, but he sees
spiritually. Because he looks over his city physically, but then he sees prophetically
what's going to happen to that city in 70 AD. He sees Emperor Nero coming in and destroying many
of the Christians, killing many of the people. And he says, if only you knew the peace that comes
before you now, but it's hidden from you. So he doesn't just see the physical realities. He sees
the spiritual stuff and not just the spiritual bad stuff, but also the spiritual good stuff.
The hope that is there. And what we're modeled here by Jesus is that we're called to approach,
be proximate, be in relationship. But we're also called to see physically, educate yourself,
learn about the issue, know the statistics, but then pray and say, Lord, what breaks your heart?
Because I see that there are 60% of the global suicides in Asia. And I see that Hong Kong is
third on that list. And that does something to me. But Lord, I come to you because I want to see this
issue from your eyes. Now, I want to get a burden in my heart for what breaks your heart. We sang it
earlier, didn't we? Give me a heart that is after your heart. That's the seeing spiritually,
not just physically. Otherwise, we're no better than a secular NGO.
And we're the church that has the hope of the world and the gospel of life.
Then Jesus does this next thing. Luke describes him as weeping. He weeps.
Now, the Greek word that Luke uses is kaleo. It literally means loud wailing or
or big sobbing. Like, in other words, Jesus is not crest that hill and look at Jerusalem and go.
He crest that hill and remember, he's surrounded by people and he starts wailing. And I can imagine
him shaking his fist and he's crying. Maybe he falls to his knees. We don't know exactly what
happened, but there's a kaleo taking place in this man. He's not just wiping away a couple of tears.
He is publicly travailing for his people. He's feeling something inside of him for their pain,
their suffering, their struggles. A man who's about to experience the greatest pain of all.
He's first kind of on his knees on behalf of people that are suffering. This is the idea of empathy.
I want you to see this because this is really important. When we approach and we see,
and if we stop at see what we've experienced is sympathy. Oh, OK. Yeah. Andrew showed some
statistics today about suicides in Hong Kong, man. Yeah, that. Yeah, I'm kind of bummed about that.
You know, like, like, that's not great. Yeah, man. You know, I'm glad I know that now.
But that's just sympathy. Jesus moves from sympathy to a place of empathy.
Empathy is like, I want to feel what those parents have felt when their child has killed themselves.
I want to feel what what the what those that are trafficked into our city are feeling in terms of
what's going on in their life. I want I want to have some. And look, you cannot have empathy unless
you approach. Are you following this? You can't have this unless you've done a bit of this.
You've got to understand the issue, but then you've got to make sure that you feel it. This
is where prayer also becomes very important. We weep. Now, that doesn't mean some of us will
actually literally weep, but we can weep in our spirit as a holy discontent inside of me.
That this world is not as Christ would want it to be, that there is not the shalom that Jesus died
on the cross for. And that moves me. That does something to me. And I cry out in that place of
pain to the one that can only fix it. So this weeping of Jesus was central.
To this work of justice that he was about to do, but notice he then speaks.
Now, this is really great because eventually Jesus, then after weeping, after approaching
and being proximate, seeing physically and spiritually and empathizing, he then moves
into what I would say is compassion. See, empathy without action is just empathy.
Empathy with action is compassion. It's like we've, we've taken this place of empathy and
we've begun to actually do something, work, something, say something, be something, act in
a certain way, suddenly have different consuming habits, suddenly recycle more at home, whatever
it might be. It might be a small thing or a big thing, but we've begun to, Hey, I've approached
this issue. I've seen it physically and spiritually. I felt something for it. There's something in my
spirit that's not right about it. I brought it to Jesus. I'm praying, but I'm also now going to
speak, act, do something that aligns myself to being a person of the gospel. One that restores
all of those break on relational context. That's what I want to do. So Jesus provides for us,
I think simply and beautifully this model that we can all apply into our lives, whether it's a big
issue or a small issue, something in our family, something in our workplace. The first thing we
should do is I want to approach, but here's the problem. A lot of Christians make the mistake we
make. We approach and we jump straight to speak. Oh, we love to do this as Christians.
Like we like to show up somewhere and approach something and just tell everybody what we think
about it. I tell you what, there is a lot of damage that has been done over church history
by Christians that have approached really important issues and just begun to speak and have
bypassed what Jesus models for us. Jesus didn't just approach his city and begin to declare
something over them, even though he had every right to do so. Jesus shows us something. Now,
here's the next thing though. A lot of Christians might approach and then educate themselves about
the issue and then they jump straight to speaking. That's even worse because this one is ignorance
and there's some damage that can be done through ignorance, but I tell you what, this is judgment
and a lot of damage is done through the church through judgment because it's like I've approached,
I've learned, I've seen there's a physical, there's a spiritual and now let me tell you
what God thinks about your sin. Let me tell you what God thinks about your brokenness
and we become a church that wags its finger. Jesus doesn't show up to his city and he's got
some pretty strong things to say to them. He's about to go to the temple and like whip people
around, okay? Like this is not safe, cuddly Jesus time. He's got some strong stuff to say,
but I want you to see something. He does not approach, see, and then jump straight to speak.
Jesus weeps. He feels something. He allows to put himself in the pain of the people that he sees
spiritually. He feels that emotion inside of him so that he knows, man, this is what the pain is
like. This is what the brokenness is like, man. I'm not going to stand from a distance and judge
with a finger. I'm on my knees because I feel it with them. I feel the longing inside of them for
their freedom. Lord, would you bring them free? But notice also, Jesus doesn't just stop at the
weeping. I think we do this as a church as well. Oh, we come in on a Sunday, Lord, save our city,
and then we never share the gospel with anyone. See, the problem is we can get paralysis by
analysis. Are you with me? And we can get paralysis by being over-emotional. Jesus goes
all the way through that, and then he speaks. He allows the thing to impact and affect him,
and then he stands up and he says, "Oh, Jerusalem, that only you knew."
And then he begins to act in ways throughout the whole week that would reinforce the gospel
that he's bringing the hope of the world, and then he goes to the cross, and then he rises,
and he changes everything. My friends, whether you have a problem in your family,
whether you see an injustice at work, whether there's something in those statistics where
you're like, "I want to learn more about that," can I say that this applies to it all?
Don't be distant. Educate yourself, but don't forget to pray. Feel what it is that's going
on for the people of our city. Learn from their perspective. Hear their voices. Understand their
pain, and then by the guidance of the Holy Spirit, do what he calls you to do. Approach, see, weep,
speak. When we do that, we begin to show the world the whole gospel. Amen? Amen.
All right. Can I invite you to stand? I want to pray for us here this morning.
I wonder whether you just quieten your heart, open your hands,
just allow the Holy Spirit just to speak to you. Lord, I want to pray that you would show each
person here just one thing in their sphere of influence. Maybe some of you in this room,
you know what it is immediately, where there's an injustice around you that you know the Holy
Spirit might be wanting to use you in. But perhaps for many of us, we're not aware immediately. Just
take a moment. Come, Holy Spirit, come. Father, I pray that you would speak. I pray that you would
show. Lord, I thank you that every single person here, they're not perfect. They're not going to
have all the answers. Oh, they're going to make mistakes along the way. I've made plenty.
But Lord, I pray that they would approach, see, weep, and speak with courage and boldness
as your Spirit leads them. Lord, I pray that this would change those statistics that we looked at
today. Lord, we're not satisfied with just 16% of our city knowing you. Lord, would you bring revival
in Hong Kong? Lord, we're not satisfied with the mental health issue. We had a viral pandemic. We
have a mental health pandemic now. Lord, would you do help us to be people who weep with our
brothers and sisters that are struggling in this time? We thank you for work like Oasis and other
things that the Vine does to help in that space. But Lord, would you give us a fresh voice?
Father, I want to pray particularly for the weeping for people in this room.
Not a weeping that leads to sorrow, that leads to retreat,
but a weeping that is a godly sorrow that catalyzes into action.
And Father, as we find that within us by your Spirit, not made by our own strength,
Father, we thank you that empathy moves to compassion.
And we thank you that in whatever area that you might be leading us into, we can play a part
for the whole gospel in our city. Lord, I pray that this would be a fire lit for the Vine
in the season that we're in. May it be for your glory and your glory alone. And everyone here says