Can we give our worship team a great thank you.
So good to see you guys and welcome to the Vine
if this is your first time, have a seat.
We're glad that you are with us.
Welcome Upper House.
(congregation laughing)
I'll be here all week.
Welcome everybody online.
We're so glad that you guys are tuning in as well.
We know that people are tuning in from all over the world.
You might be in Hong Kong right now.
You might be somewhere else.
We're so glad that you're watching this weather live
with us in this moment or catching up
at a time that's convenient for you.
We pray and believe that through technology,
God moves just as much and just as powerfully
as if you were in this room.
So we are grateful for you.
Thanks for tuning in today and for each one of you.
Who's been here for most of the series
for the different spirit series?
Let's have a look at your hands.
Most of you.
All right, that's the majority of people here.
That's wonderful.
That's great.
We're finishing that series today.
And I wanna speak to you about your courage
and your strength.
I actually believe that the number one thing
that the Holy Spirit wants us to finish this series with
as a way of launching us into the next thing
is by reminding you about your source
and your need for courage and strength.
So let me start by sharing with you
something out of my own life.
I have a phobia.
It's actually a clinically defined phobia.
My phobia is that I'm afraid of the ocean.
Yeah, I know.
It's pretty sad.
I've struggled with this fear for the majority of my life.
I don't mind, to be honest,
being on a boat floating on the ocean.
I don't mind maybe like walking on a beach,
putting my toes a little bit in the water of an ocean.
But the idea of swimming in an ocean
fills me with absolute terror.
Now, I'm not exactly sure how this started,
but it might've been at the moment
when at the age of eight years old,
my parents allowed me to watch the film "Jaws."
Anyone else seen "Jaws" here?
Do not let your children watch "Jaws."
I was eight years old
and I spent the whole movie with my two pillows
in front of my eyes,
but I couldn't stop looking away
from this ferocious water-based mammal of a shark
eating everything in its path.
By the way, I also have a minor phobia to cello music.
And the whole time I was filled with such dread, such fear,
and that impacted my whole childhood up to this day.
Now, when you grow up in Hong Kong,
being afraid of the ocean is a bit of a problem.
There's over 200 islands that make up Hong Kong.
And when you're young here,
I spent the majority of my weekends
hanging out with friends on junks or whatever it might be,
and they'd all be jumping off the top of the boat,
they'd all be swimming around,
and I'd be the nerd in the rowing boat,
rowing next to them, afraid to get in the ocean.
This was my childhood, seriously.
At the age of 14,
my parents decided that the best way
to spend a family holiday
would be at a beach resort in the Seychelles
in the middle of nowhere,
a small little island surrounded by water.
So we went there,
and I remember going into the lobby of this hotel,
and right there on a big board,
as you came in the lobby, was a sign.
It said, "Sign up for your one-day scuba diving experience."
And I thought to myself,
maybe this is the way to overcome my fear.
Maybe if I could just get the courage in me
to sign up for this one-day scuba diving experience,
then I would go out into the ocean,
I would see that the ocean is filled
with all these beautiful things,
that it's perfectly safe,
and this would set me free from my fear.
So I said to my mom and dad,
"Can I sign up for the one-day scuba diving?"
They said, "Are you mad?
"You're phobic of the ocean."
I said, "Yes, this is psychology.
"It's called flooding.
"You flood yourself with your terror,
"and you realize that it's not that bad,
"and you overcome it."
My mom was like, "Where do I sign?"
(audience laughing)
They signed me up for my one-day scuba diving experience.
Now, this experience existed in this way.
You had a one-hour classroom of lectures.
You then, for about two and a half hours,
were gonna scuba dive
in the bottom of the swimming pool of the resort.
And then after you've done that, after lunch,
you would go out on the boat,
and they would take you out about 200 yards offshore.
They would drop the anchor rope,
and what you would do is you would swim down the anchor rope
into about 30 meters of water,
swim around for about 20 minutes,
back up the anchor rope,
and that was your one-day scuba diving experience.
The one-hour of classroom lectures
consisted of this as a summary.
"When you're in the water,
"do not have a moment of uncertainty."
(audience laughing)
This was all that I was planning to do in the water,
was to have lots and lots and lots of moments of uncertainty.
We then went into the swimming pool,
and I discovered in the swimming pool
that I was actually a really good,
skills-based scuba diver.
I could take off my mask,
put it back on again, and get all the water out.
I could take my regulator out and sort of swim around a bit
and then put the regulator back in,
and I could do all the safety drills that were needed.
My skills as a scuba diver were good.
We then had lunch, which consisted of food
that I do not remember because I did not eat any of it.
I was so nervous, my stomach was going in knots,
I couldn't handle it.
Right after lunch, we stepped down onto the beach
with all of our scuba gear.
And I'm standing there, there's the boat,
and there's this massive ocean in front of me.
And I'm thinking to myself,
this is the worst decision I have ever made.
And I literally pray, and I say,
Jesus, if you are Jesus,
I need some courage to step on this boat.
Somehow, I got myself on the boat.
As we start to go out from the shore,
they pair us up with a dive buddy,
something very important.
I was paired up with a Frenchman
who was probably about 26, 27 years old.
I'm an English person who's 14.
He seemed very old and scary to me.
And as he's sitting next to me,
he doesn't speak a lot of English.
I don't speak much French,
but he can tell by looking in my eyes, I am terrified.
And so he's staring at me,
and I can see that that's making him a little bit,
like, this is my dive buddy, right?
He goes, (speaking in French)
Was that all right?
Was that French?
Yeah, all right, okay.
(audience laughing)
I don't know what that is in French, but anyway.
And I was like, okay, all right, all right.
We get out about 200 yards.
They let the anchor rope down.
Everybody starts jumping in the water
like this is the best day of their lives.
My French buddy gets in the water
and he starts to drift out towards the anchor rope.
I realized that if I don't go now,
I'm going to leave him to the terrors of the ocean.
Somehow I get in the water,
I drift over to the anchor rope,
and my French friend, he gives me a French thumbs up.
I don't know what that is, but it was like, voila.
(speaking in French)
He starts to go down the anchor rope, right?
And I'm like, if I don't go now, I'll lose him.
I might lose my way.
So mustering all the courage I could find,
I start to let the air out
and I start to descend down at the anchor rope.
I get five meters down
and I see a movement on my right-hand side.
Now, when you're scuba diving,
you can't just go, oh, what's that?
So I'm there like.
(audience laughing)
And a shark swims past me on my right-hand side,
swims down towards the other scuba divers
and slowly drifts off into the horizon.
A shark.
I've been in the water less than five minutes.
I haven't been in the water since I was eight years old.
This classifies as a moment of uncertainty.
Now, what a brave person would have done
was to swim down, grab my French buddy,
tell him, "Shark," you know,
get him up out of the water and into freedom and safety.
Sorry, but I let my French guy go.
I was so overwhelmed.
I swam as quickly as I could to the surface.
Luckily, I was only about five meters down,
so there wasn't any worries.
I got right to the surface.
I was panicking.
I swam as fast as I could back over to the boat.
The Seychelles boat boy, he grabs me by my arms.
He yanks me up and he pulls me onto my back on the boat.
And I rip off my mask and I rip out my regulator
and I'm about to go, "Shark, shark!"
And he leans over me and he goes,
"Hey, man, did you see the dolphin?"
(audience laughing)
Dolphin?
"Hey, man, did you see the dolphin?"
I don't know why he's Irish.
He just sounded Irish then.
I'm like, "Yeah, yeah, yeah.
"I saw the dolphin.
"Did you see the, I wanted to come back
"to make sure you saw the dolphin.
"Did you see the dolphin?"
(audience laughing)
I think it's quite interesting how we humans
have a tendency to turn dolphins into sharks in our lives.
We just spent seven weeks looking at a story of Israel
who, because of fear, turned a dolphin into a shark.
God had given them this amazing promised land,
this place for them to go and inhabit
and to conquer and to take,
that he had literally rolled out the red carpet for them,
a place filling with milk and honey,
grapes that looked of the promises of God.
And they were so afraid of the giants in the land
that they came back, those 10 spies,
with a report that stirred up such fear in the camp
that they felt like they were going to be devoured
by the shark in that place.
I mean, it blows my mind that in my fear,
God thought the best thing for me,
let me help Andrew overcome his fear.
I will send him, literally rolling out the red carpet
of aquaness, I will send him a dolphin.
Peace-loving, beautiful, (imitates dolphin)
dolphin.
And in my fear, I turned dolphins into sharks
and we see that Israel suffers in the same way.
And for 40 years, note this, 40 years,
that fear has an impact on their lives.
For 40 years, they have to wait for a whole generation
to be released from Israel.
A whole generation that doubted God,
rebelled against him because of the fear,
decided that that wasn't the way it was,
turned that dolphin into a shark, 40 years,
that God purges that out of them.
And at the end of that 40 years,
Moses is still alive somehow, really old now.
And he realizes that he's about to die.
And in the moment of understanding
that death is right near him,
the Holy Spirit leads him up a mountain,
a little bit like how the Holy Spirit led him up a mountain
of Mount Sinai to receive the law.
This time, leads him up a mountain called Mount Nebo.
Mount Nebo is in modern day Jordan.
And from this mountain, you can look out
and you can see the promised land.
In fact, I had the great privilege
of traveling to Jordan just two years ago,
and I was able to stand right where Moses stood,
looking out on the same geographical view
that he would have seen.
And I took a photo, I want you to see this.
This is what it looks like.
So Moses is standing there and he's looking out
and you see all the green that is there.
That's the fertile land, that's Canaan for Moses,
modern day Israel for us.
And you can see maybe just,
if you look at the middle of the screen,
just a little bit to the right,
there's a bit of blue dot there.
That's the Sea of Galilee.
I mean, you can see all of the incredibleness
of the Holy Land right there from Mount Nebo.
And Moses would have looked over there
and would have realized,
I am not going to go into that place.
And instead, the Spirit speaks to him
and he decides that he's going to anoint
and appoint Joshua to go
and be the one that would lead Israel into the land.
Joshua, one of the two spies
that didn't turn the dolphin into a shark.
One of the two that went into the land,
believed the grapes, even though he saw the giants,
came back with a report and said,
it is exceedingly good.
That one who is now 40 years older,
stands next to Moses
and I think there's a mixture of feelings on him.
Like me standing before the ocean that day,
there's Joshua standing before the River Jordan once again,
looking onto the beauty of that promised land.
And I think he's nervous and excited.
He's conscious of the mistakes
that had been made in the past.
And he's filled with excitement
for what God is about to do in the future.
I wonder if you've ever felt like you're standing
in one of those moments in life.
Joshua's moments.
Over the last seven weeks,
as we've looked at numbers 13 and 14,
we've told you the story of Caleb, haven't we?
Caleb's been the center character.
Caleb is the one with the different spirit,
Caleb and Joshua, but Caleb took center stage
and we spoke about his wholeheartedness and all of that.
And that was great.
But now we're at a point where they're about to cross in
some 40 years later and the narrative shifts away
from Caleb.
In fact, Caleb's hardly heard of again,
but Joshua takes center stage now.
And I want you to see what takes place here.
You see, wholeheartedness had gotten them
to the point where they're on the edge of the land,
but it would be courage and strength
that would make them conquerors of that land.
Are you with me?
The wholeheartedness got them right there to the edge,
but it would be courage and strength
that would bring them in.
And now Joshua is wondering, how do we take the next step?
How do we actually move from a place of waiting
to a place of action?
I want you to hear this church.
40 years of waiting.
And now they're at this moment where waiting must turn
into action.
And I believe here in Hong Kong, in the hour that we're in,
in this moment of our city,
it's time for us to stop waiting.
I think waiting finishes and we have to now move forward
in action.
And the one thing that we're gonna need
more than anything else,
as we step into the place of action, strength and courage.
I wanna say this right over you, right here at the start.
I believe God's got something so important
that is you shaped, you unique.
And I believe that what he's calling you to
is so important and so beyond your natural abilities.
If it wasn't, he wouldn't be calling you into it.
That you're going to need more strength and courage
for what's ahead.
And so I wanna unpack this message for you today
to help you to understand what strength and courage
might mean for you in your situation, in your context,
what it might mean for us as a city
in our time here in Hong Kong right now.
Does that sound all right?
And I wanna go to this passage where God,
just before Joshua takes his first step,
says some very important things to him
about this idea of what strength and courage is.
This is found in Joshua 1, verse one.
After the death of Moses, the servant of the Lord,
the Lord said to Joshua, son of Nun, Moses' aid,
Moses, my servant is dead.
Now then, you and all these people get ready
to cross the Jordan River into the land
that I'm about to give them to the Israelites.
I will give you every place where you set your foot,
as I promised Moses.
Your territory will extend from the desert to Lebanon,
from the great river to the great sea on the west.
No one will be able to stand up against you
all of the days of your life, for as I was with Moses,
so I will now be with you.
I will never leave you or forsake you.
I want you to see the important thing
that God does with Joshua in this moment.
First of all, he doesn't mince his words.
He tells him straight up, Moses is dead.
Now that would have meant something for Joshua.
That was his mentor, his leader, the one he has followed,
the one he's obeyed, the one he's actually been an aid to,
the one he's given his life to.
God says, that guy can't be your support anymore.
Moses is dead, but then he says this really important thing.
He says, now I want you to get ready
to cross the Jordan River into the land
that I'm about to give to you, the Israelites.
He says this, Moses might be dead,
but the mission I have for you is not dead.
I want you to follow this.
The man himself has died,
but the mission of God has not died with him.
That God's mission is bigger and broader
than the individual.
That's important for some of you to sit here and hear.
That you might think that everything is formed
and shaped around you.
No, no, God has broader and bigger plans
than just the one person.
The vine is not about Andrew.
This church and your faith is not about your leaders
or your pastors.
There is a much bigger, broader thing.
Moses is dead.
At some point in the near future,
I won't be your senior pastor anymore.
And the anointing and the power will shift to someone else.
And God's work will continue
because God has a plan for his people.
And that plan involves people,
but is not linked so much to people
that when those people make mistakes,
when those people don't do right,
when those people disobey,
that the whole thing is thwarted.
Some of you need to realize
that the mission you're caught up in
is way bigger than you realize.
Now, why is that important?
It's important because what God's doing in this moment
is he's creating the foundation for Joshua's courage.
He's basically saying to Joshua,
it's not about you, buddy.
It's not your mission.
It's not your idea.
It's not your strength.
It's not what you're going to do.
No, it's my mission.
I've always decreed this.
40 years ago, I wanted you to do it.
And out of rebellion, you didn't.
And now 40 years it's taken,
but that mission has not died.
It's my will, my way.
Your courage comes from actually realizing
that it's not about you.
'Cause if it is in our courage,
we're gonna have a tendency,
listen to this,
of turning dolphins into sharks.
So God says to Joshua, this is going to happen.
Are you with me?
Not only that, but he says, I'm with you.
We're in this together.
Partnership moving into the land.
You see, you need to understand
that courage always comes from mission.
In just the same way as faith always comes from challenge.
Courage is always linked to mission.
I'm not gonna stand in front of you today
and ask you to be courageous for courageous sake.
I'm gonna ask you to be courageous for something.
And it's that something,
it's how you define that something
that'll be the foundation of your courage.
The thing that wakes you up in the morning
and you say, I'm a child of God.
The thing that wakes you up and says,
I have something to say to this city,
to my company, to my family, to my spouse.
The thing that wakes you up in the morning
and says, because of the gospel, there is hope.
That something that curves through your veins
and pumps your blood and makes you excited
to be alive in Hong Kong
and a Christian for the gospel and in time.
That thing, you need to discover what that is.
'Cause it's that thing where you'll find your courage.
It's linking that thing to the bigger thing
that God is at work in that will help you know
and feel that God is with you.
Is this making sense?
You okay?
Feels really quiet in here.
Is that all right?
Good.
Notice what happens next.
Thank you, baby.
Baby's like, yeah, go for it, preach it.
Verse six, be strong and courageous
because you will lead these people to inherit the land
that I swore to their forefathers to give them.
Be strong and very courageous.
Be careful to obey all the law my servant Moses gave you.
Do not turn from it from the right to the left
that you may be successful wherever you go.
Do not let this book of the law depart from your mouth.
Meditate on it day and night
so that you may be careful to do everything written in it.
Then you will be prosperous and successful.
Have I not commanded you?
Be strong and courageous.
Do not be terrified.
Do not be discouraged for the Lord your God will be with you
wherever you go.
Three times, notice this.
God says to Joshua, be strong and courageous.
And you need to know, God does not have a speech impediment.
God is intentionally trying to drill something
into this young man, well, he's not young, he's old,
into this old man,
it's 'cause I see so many young people in this room.
He's trying to drill something into this person
and he's trying to say, you need to be strong and courageous.
Be strong and courageous, be strong and courageous.
It's that important.
And so I stand over you as divine church.
If you're a part of this church community,
then there's an authority in this place
for us to be in relationship spiritually as well.
I stand over you and I say for Hong Kong, for this hour,
be strong and courageous.
Before you take one step,
find the courage and the strength
to join me in missions in this hour.
It was important for him to hear it
before he took that step.
I feel in my spirit, it's important for you to hear it.
There are some of us in this room
who are in danger of turning dolphins into sharks
because we're still a little bit consumed by the giants.
God's rolling out a red carpet, I believe, for you
in whatever it is that God is releasing you into.
And he's saying, be strong and courageous.
Do not fear.
There are three specific things
that God says to Joshua to be strong and courageous about.
And I wanna tell you that these three specific things
are the things that I think all of us
need to be strong and courageous in,
regardless of what the something is
that God has called us to,
regardless of whatever mission is on you,
regardless of whatever call is upon your life,
regardless of whatever's going on in your life right now.
These three things that God calls Joshua
to be strong and courageous in
are, I believe, three fundamental biblical principles
of things that all of us need to find courage in
if we're going to move forward
in the mission of God in our lives.
Here's the first one, verse six.
Be strong and courageous
because you will lead these people to inherit the land
that I swore to their fathers to give them.
The first thing is leadership.
We have to be strong and courageous in leadership.
And before I say anything else,
when I talk about leadership,
I'm not talking about me or my title here at the Vine.
I'm not talking about the leadership of the Vine Church.
I'm not talking about your boss in your office.
I'm not talking about the leader of your family.
I'm talking about you.
You are a leader
'cause God has given you a sphere of influence,
some place where you have some sort of influence,
some sort of authority.
For some of us, it's a big influence and a big authority.
For some of us, it's a smaller influence
and a smaller authority.
God does not look at those two things differently.
He doesn't think, "Oh, the leaders of more are the better."
So every single one of us has leadership authority
because we are the children of God
living the kingdom of God in the brokenness of this world.
So I want you to hear leadership about you.
Now, God turns up to Joshua
and he understands that Joshua's got a difficult job,
that leading Israel is not an easy thing.
And so he comes to him and says,
"You need strength and courage for your leadership
in what's ahead."
I think it's very obvious to us
that in our world right now,
we are suffering from a failure of leadership
over the last couple of years.
I think if there's one thing
that this world is really struggling with,
it is finding good leaders.
Instead, what's happened is somehow politically,
somehow within the boardroom,
somehow we've redefined leadership to be this,
that leadership now, the characteristics of leadership
is so often name-calling.
It's so often character assassination.
It's so often shaming.
It's so often manipulation of the media.
It's so often trying to push people
to extreme points of view.
And if you're not on my side of the extreme point of view,
you're a hater and you're the enemy.
Leadership has become incredibly divisive.
And for some reason,
people think that that's how power is given now.
And before we as Christians begin to point out too much,
the speck in everybody else's eyes,
we need to stop and realize there's a big, huge plank in ours.
Over the last 2000 years,
the church has suffered many times
for a failure of leadership.
Just in the recent six months,
we've seen celebrity pastors, famous NGO leaders,
Christians who have fallen from grace.
That fall impacts all of us.
It's hard, isn't it?
For all of us when we see that.
And we realize that this failure of leadership
is happening both in the world,
it's happening also in the church,
and we're all a part of it.
And God is standing over his people and he's saying,
who's gonna be strong and courageous in leadership?
I mean, who's gonna be willing to stand
for godly principles in how they lead in their office,
in their family, in their school?
Who's gonna stand for authenticity?
Who's gonna stand for vulnerability and humility?
Who's gonna make a stand to love the other as yourself?
Who's gonna be the first person willing to say, I'm sorry?
Like who's gonna be willing to step forward
with the kind of leadership that we see in Jesus Christ?
That kind of leadership takes a huge amount of courage.
Because everything else around you is going to tell you
that the way you get influence and power these days
is by doing the name calling, and the character assassination
and manipulating the media and doing all these things.
And for you to say, no, I actually believe
with a different spirit that there's a different way.
That actually maybe if I'm more grace-filled
and grace-loving, things might change.
So I think there's people in this room
where in the very near future,
you're gonna have to have courage
to stand up in your boardroom
and to stand against a policy that puts profit over people.
Some of you in this room,
you're gonna have to have the courage
to stand in your classroom,
or as a parent, stand over your child
and stand for biblical values that are at threat.
I think there's some people in this room
where you're gonna have to stand over that relationship
that's broken in your life,
and you're gonna have to exhibit some godly leadership
and say, you know what?
I'm also responsible for this breakdown.
I've made mistakes.
Would you forgive me
that there might be a rising up of the church
to take on an idea of what strong and courageous leadership
might truly look like?
Let me put it this way.
If we have any hope of moving the needle in Hong Kong
and helping this city heal from all of its pain
over the last couple of years,
if we have any hope of seeing people come together
in this city in more unity,
any hope of being able to build a new character
and a new identity for Hong Kong in the years ahead,
it will come if we rise up
with a strong and courageous leadership
that holds boldly forth the idea of integrity and hope
that is found in the person of Jesus.
Like we are being called right now in this hour
to hold forth that kind of hope.
Where are the leaders?
They're sitting in this room.
Be strong and courageous.
Here's the second thing.
Verse seven, be strong and very courageous.
Be careful to obey all that the law
my servant Moses has given you.
Do not turn from the right or to the left
that you may be successful wherever you go.
Do not let this book of law depart from your mouth.
Meditate it day and night
so that you may be careful to do everything written in it.
Then you'll be prosperous and successful.
The second thing you're going to need strength
and courage in is obedience.
It's going to be really difficult to remain obedient
to the ways of Jesus in this fast changing world
that we're in.
And God understood for Joshua
that disobedience had led Israel
into a 40 year wandering in the wilderness.
A 40 year of wandering around
before they were ready to go in.
And God knew that if there was one thing
that he needs courage in, it is to be obedient.
Obedient to God's word, obedient to God's promises.
He wants to speak that life into him.
Notice God doesn't ask him to be more obedient.
God challenges him to have courage in his obedience.
And this is so important for all of us
because I think in some ways
that's where we need the courage
to actually stand for what it is that we believe.
To actually stand for the things of Christ
in a broken world.
To actually offer the obedience to the Lord
despite whether that obedience might lose that promotion,
might cause us to lose some friends.
Obedience to Christ takes courage.
And it takes courage in this world like never before.
Christ is gonna call you at some point in the near future
to let go of things that are ugly in you
that you don't wanna let go of.
That will take courage.
God's gonna call you in this near future
to take a stand for the gospel
when it seems that that's now socially unacceptable to do.
That will take courage from you.
Some of us might lose jobs
because we hold on to values and morals
that are contrary to what our companies are doing.
That will take courage from you.
And I've been saying this for this whole year,
I'm gonna keep saying it.
When you're in the reality of the worst moment of your life,
somebody else's faith is not gonna cut it for you.
It's your faith and the courage that you have
to take a moral stand, a spiritual stand,
a stand in faith and say,
this is what I believe God's doing in this city
and I will align all of myself to it.
So where does the courage come from
to be obedient to God like that?
Well, notice what Moses says in verse,
sorry, Joshua says here in verse eight.
Oh God, actually.
Do not let this book of the Lord depart from your mouth.
Meditate on it day and night
so that you may be careful to do everything written in it.
God says, this is where your courage comes from,
knowing the word.
Like I'm not asking you to fabricate some courage,
but if you're gonna have courage
to be obedient to what I'm saying,
that courage is gonna come from knowing what I'm saying,
from understanding my heart, understanding my promises,
making those, meditating on those,
thinking about them, praying about them,
using them on your lips,
speaking them out over one another,
standing in front of each other,
reminding each other of gospel stories of a centurion
who can change your life.
Like these are the things, meditate, speak
on the word of God.
You will need courage in the years ahead here in Hong Kong.
And your courage will come from your dependency
and familiarity of God's word.
We've done like five messages this year
about the scriptures and the importance of God's word.
I wonder if you're seeing a repetitive theme
here at the Vine.
It's time for us to know it, soak in it, read it,
memorize it, have it,
because the sword of the spirit will be needed,
which is the word of God.
Be strong and very courageous.
Here's the third and final one.
Verse nine, "Have I not commanded you?
"Be strong and courageous.
"Do not be terrified, do not be discouraged,
"for the Lord your God will be with you wherever you go.
"Do not fear and do not be discouraged."
Two things that God is saying to Joshua,
you need courage, not to be fearful,
courage, not to be discouraged.
Now, I dealt with fear a few weeks ago in this series.
I did a whole message on the fear cycle, the faith cycle.
I'm not gonna speak about fear this morning,
but if that's something that you didn't hear,
go back online, grab it and listen to it.
I wanna talk now then briefly about discouragement.
We don't talk about this a lot, I don't think,
in the church, but discouragement has such an impact on us.
Discouragement happens when you've made a mistake
and you feel bad about it,
where you have regrets of things that you've done
in the past and those regrets begin to shape
who you are in the present.
Discouragement is like a heaviness that comes upon you,
like you're wearing some big, heavy cloak.
And God shows up to Joshua,
and God knows that in Joshua's life,
he has suffered discouragement.
He knows that Joshua has been with the people
wandering for 40 years.
He knows that Joshua has made mistakes in his past,
that Joshua is not perfect.
And he knows that those mistakes
are trying to hold him back.
You see, I think God realizes
that the brokenness of Joshua's past
has the potential to hold him back
from the freedom of his future.
And so God comes to Joshua and says,
"You need to have courage
"in overcoming your discouragement."
So let me preach on this for one moment,
because I think this is important
for some people in this room.
It's like you're carrying around sadness and regret
and guilt and shame from stuff that you've done in your past.
And that is now coloring who you are today
and the direction you're going in the future.
And guess what?
It is not easy to let go of your past.
It will take courage for you
to overcome the heaviness of your mistakes.
It's gonna take great courage for you
to be able to overcome the heaviness
of the mistakes that you've made.
But I tell you, the number one thing
that will move you into freedom
is not to walk into your future facing backwards,
looking back on all the stuff that's broken and wrong
and done and thinking that you're on plan B.
The number one thing that will release you
into God's mission is the courage
to let go of what you don't need.
Let me say it this way.
The first step in getting what God needs
is having the courage to let go of what God doesn't.
Come on, church.
The courage to let go of what God doesn't need in your life.
The things that you're carrying
that he's long forgiven you for.
The things that you're still dragging around
that he's like, "Why is that still with you?
"That is gone, whiter than snow.
"I've washed you clean.
"Yeah, that was a bad thing.
"Yes, there are consequences.
"I've wiped it out of my memory.
"You are moving forward now,
"forgiven and restored as a person of Christ."
And I wonder whether we would have the courage
to not let the enemy win with discouragement.
Some of you are sitting here and you're like,
"Wow, that sounds like a lot of work."
And you're so discouraged,
and I felt like this sometimes in my life,
so I understand this.
You're so discouraged that you don't even know how to start.
You don't even know if you have the energy to start.
"Wow, it sounds like a lot, Andrew,
"to have to face the brokenness of my past,
"have to allow all those emotions to come,
"have to give that to God.
"That sounds like a huge amount of work."
And you know what?
There is a process often in finding freedom
from the things that have so oppressed us.
But I read a quote this week that really encouraged me.
I hope it encourages you.
Let me read this to you.
"Courage doesn't always roar.
"Sometimes courage is the quiet voice
"at the end of the day saying,
"'I will try again tomorrow.'"
Isn't that beautiful?
Like, "I'm gonna get back in the water
"with my scuba gear the next day,
"and I'm gonna really try my best
"to not turn a dolphin into a shark.
"I will take courage that I'm working on a mission
"that is God's mission, not mine."
And as Joshua is trying to let go of his discouragement,
I want you to see where he can find the hope to do that.
Right at the end of verse nine,
"God will be with you wherever you go,
"no matter what's going on for you,
"no matter where you are, I will be with you.
"Feeling completely in despair, I will be there.
"Struggling with the pain of your mistakes,
"I will meet you there.
"Holding back on your depression,
"not knowing how to move forward with joy,
"I'll meet you there.
"Upset because you cheated on your spouse
"and you've never really dealt with the guilt of it,
"I will be there for you.
"But you will need to be courageous
"to maybe admit some things,
"reconcile some things, bring your hurt to me."
So God turns to Joshua and he says,
"The hope will come because I haven't given up on you.
"I haven't left you, I haven't forsaken you.
"I'm right here with you, so be strong and courageous."
There's a moment in the New Testament
where the disciples are really struggling.
They've watched their best friend murdered on a cross.
They've seen him raised, they've talked to him.
They've heard his hope for them.
They know he's about to ascend up into the heavens,
but they're struggling with the reality of what comes next.
What do we do when our risen Savior is no longer with us?
And I want to read you some words
that Jesus speaks over his fearful disciples.
He brings them up a mountain,
much like Moses and Joshua standing on a mountain
overlooking the promised land.
Jesus brings the disciples up to a mountain
so that they could look over the Greco-Roman Empire.
And here's what he says to them in Matthew 28.
He says, "All authority in heaven and earth
"has been given to me.
"So now go and make disciples of all nations,
"baptizing them in the name of the Father and the Son
"and the Holy Spirit, teaching them to obey
"everything I have commanded you.
"And surely I am with you always
"to the very end of the age."
I wonder if that sounds like anything.
That God shows up to Joshua and says,
I want you to move forward.
Be strong and courageous as you lead.
Be strong and courageous as you experience obedience.
Be strong and courageous to overcome your fear,
overcome your discouragement.
I will always be with you.
So Jesus stands in front of the disciples
and in relation stands in front of you and I
here in Hong Kong in this hour.
And he says, "You too be strong and courageous
"for there's a mission also for you.
"Go into the world, make disciples."
That's my mission.
It's bigger than any one person.
It's bigger than any one church,
but in partnership together, we can go.
Go into that world, make disciples,
teach them to obey, baptize them,
immerse them in the character of the Father,
the Son and the Holy Spirit.
And as you do that, guess what?
I will be with you.
So be strong and courageous.
As we finish this series, we don't finish the mission.
We start it.
And this is your moment to step up and step forward,
to move from waiting to action.
The Holy Spirit would say, "Be strong and courageous."
Would you stand with me?
I wanna pray for you.
And I wanna encourage you if you're comfortable
just to open your hands as I pray.
I wanna commission you for the something
that is in your life.
For that thing that you are a leader on
and over in your life.
For that thing that gets you up in the morning,
for that thing that makes you excited,
for the joy that sits in you,
for that call for the mission of God
to go into the world and make disciples.
And whatever that may manifest in your workplace
or in your family or in your community,
you have a unique God-shaped passion on you
that no one else can do and fulfill.
And so I stand before you today.
And as God stands over you, He says, "Lead well."
He says, "Obey my word."
And He says to you, "Overcome fear and discouragement."
"Be strong and courageous."
Father, our hands are open before you,
your people in this city, in this place, in this hour.
Father, I pray as we finish the series
that you would release over each person right now
the courage to stand for you in a broken world.
I pray you would release the courage
to lead in ways that honor the gospel.
I pray, Lord, you would give each person in this room
the courage to stand for you when others aren't.
I pray, Lord, you give the people in this room
the courage to not turn dolphins into sharks,
the courage to leave behind their regrets
and their shame and their failures
and to move forward, not perfect, but forgiven.
Father, fill them with courage.
Father, fill them with your courage.
Bring them alive in joy and boldness
and the authority that comes from the Holy Spirit.
Send them into their workplaces and schools,
into their families, into their communities,
their spheres of influence,
with a boldness that holds forth the gospel for this time.
We will not be afraid.
We will see the grapes.
Holy Spirit, we will repent when we need to.
God, we want the whole of our hearts to be with you.
Father, we want to know you, be in relationship with you
more than the things that we do, Lord.
And we need strength and courage for the fight.
So fill us again with faith.
(gentle music)
Allow the Holy Spirit to speak to you now.