(audience applauding)
- Tim, I just feel for you that you come across,
you're a big man physically, right?
But this season, God is making you
into the big man spiritually.
You know, so actually, let's not be just pulled off
by just looking at him.
God is doing something inside of him, right?
And might be the fasting, right?
But this is your season,
and God is making you into a spiritual giant
as well as a physical giant.
Can I have amen to that?
- Amen.
(audience applauding)
- Good.
Well, happy new year to everyone.
Salud, Falak.
It's great to be here.
A new year is a new opportunity.
Vine Church, Yunlong,
you are about to enter into a new season.
It will not look like what you've known before.
God says, "I will do a new thing."
As someone who's had a relationship with the Vine Church
for almost 30 years, I am indeed honored and privileged
to be asked to say a few words on this special day,
New Year's Eve.
And may I just say right up front,
what a wonderful year it's been.
From those months, those wonderful months preparing at EIS.
You'll remember those forever, won't you?
It's amazing.
The prayer walks, the social events, the barbecues,
the Vision Sunday, generous offering.
We're here today because on one Sunday this year,
people were moved to give enough money
to actually finance this church.
The official launch and this wonderful building.
Beyond any of our wildest dreams,
my first words, however, may be misconstrued
as me being a bit of a killjoy.
Almost as you say, putting a dampener
on this joyous occasion.
But I need to say them nonetheless.
The church is not a building.
You're allowed to say amen, by the way.
Any Pentecostals here?
Yeah, good.
Church is not a building.
The church is not a building.
The word that Jesus was quoted as using
that we translate as church, ecclesia,
has nothing to do with a church building.
But I think this conversation only goes to illustrate
the confusion that many of us face
with church being regarded as a place,
as a building we go to, rather than a thing we are.
But in a sense, it doesn't matter
whether we meet in a beautiful crystal cathedral
or an old scout hut.
The church is us, the people of God.
And I believe that this highly impressive building
here at Ho Sun Lee is a conduit,
a conduit for us meeting together to thank God,
to thank God for his faithfulness and goodness
at the vine for almost 30 years
and for this amazing past year here at Yuen Long.
But equally as important is to seek him
for his presence in the present
and to ask his guidance for the future.
I believe this is one of possibly
the most significant times in church history.
Give or take a percentage point,
around 94% of Hong Kong's population
are currently not part of any church.
Does that make you feel good?
It doesn't make me feel good.
Many in our city, especially the younger generation,
have lost hope.
We're seeing an increase in those suffering
with mental health issues
and an alarming rise in teenage suicides.
And in case you haven't noticed,
our poor seem to be getting poorer.
What can we do?
My friends, mark my words.
This building is significant,
but not as an aquarium to keep the fish in,
but as a launching pad for the lifeboats.
Can I say that again?
A launching pad for the lifeboats.
Down those stairs and out there.
I see this building as an equipping center,
equipping the saints to man the lifeboats
to be sent to the lost,
the lonely, those who've lost hope.
And I believe there are many fish
to be caught right here in Yuen Long.
I declare today that Yuen Long is a freaking village.
- Amen.
- An ocean full of fish ready to be caught.
As I prayed this week, I saw a picture.
I saw it in two halves.
The first half was about today.
The people of this church were gathered together
and we were like young eaglets in an eagle's nest.
Safe together, nestling in the mother's arms.
They were in close community with each other.
And I think that describes the Vine Yuen Long very, very well.
You enjoy wonderful community.
But in the second scene, the eaglets had grown.
And I saw squadrons of eagles swarming out from Hong San Lee
to the people of Yuen Long,
to the people of Hong Kong and beyond.
This building is to be that nurture place.
This building is to be that nurture place
where, oh yes, you enjoy community
and please go on enjoying community.
But where you are also prepared, trained,
equipped to be sent to where the church of Hong Kong
really is, in our offices, in our schools
and the housing estates of our city.
And in that respect, I wanna share a verse.
It is the motivating verse for this message.
It is my prayer.
It is my dream for this church in 2024.
And I believe that this verse describes you.
The people who call Vine Yuen Long their home church.
It's Psalm 1,3.
That person, Tim,
that person, Darius,
is like a tree planted by streams of water
which yields its fruit in season
and whose leaf does not wither,
whatever they do, prospers.
Now, read my lips for a moment.
There is no room in this church for spectators.
Or to be on any church, to be honest.
Christianity is not a spectator sport.
The Psalmist has already told us this in verse one.
Blessed is the one who does not walk in the step
with the wicked or stand in the way that sinners take
or sit in the company of mockers,
but whose delight is in the law of the Lord
and who meditates on his law day and night.
And can I just back up what Tim said about the fast?
Fast is not about what you give up.
Fast is about what you gain.
Meditate on his word day and night.
And I will come back to blessing at the end of my talk.
But this got me thinking.
Everybody sort of wants a successful life.
Church is always talking about having successful ministries.
But what is it?
The promise of success here is qualified by the context.
Whatever they do and whatever they do will be determined
by living in obedience to the scriptures.
Whose delight is in the law of the Lord
who meditates on his law day and night.
That is what will prosper.
And what I wanna do now is move from,
churches often talk about doing preaching verse by verse.
It's very popular in churches.
I'm gonna move to something
which I'm gonna call word by word preaching.
And I wanna end up with six definitions of success.
This is my prayer for you for 2024.
And they are all in verse three.
And they are all linked to the sense
of a tree being planted by streams of water.
And you will love this.
They all begin with the letter P.
Ironically, the world might come up with the same six P's.
But I want you to see them through the lens
of a tree planted by streams of water.
Through as it were Psalm 1,3 tinted glasses.
And the first P is this prominence.
It says like a tree.
Trees are prominent.
To be prominent is to be widely known.
We are to project outward from the line
we started in our faith.
A tree is a prominent part of nature.
And I wanna say to you,
it is not wrong to be prominent in the world.
Billy Graham was friends with 13 US presidents
from Harry S. Truman to Donald J. Trump.
It is time to let our faith be known.
Can I repeat that?
Always move forward.
We are to be bold like a tree.
Just like a tree is always growing, so should our faith.
No one's faith can stand still.
It either goes forward or backwards.
The second P is permanence.
The word is planted here.
This quality of the Christian life is crucial.
We need to be permanently planted in God's word.
We need to be permanent with our faith
and not let anything shake us.
We've been singing about that all morning.
Not let the things of the world shake us.
We are to be rooted by the word of God.
Rooted by the words of God.
That means if a decision comes up, a problem or a doubt,
we should always refer to God's word for assurance.
This permanence gives us security.
There are just too many Christians out there
who float in the wind
and compromise their faith with the world.
We are to stand firm with security and permanence.
Then there is position.
This is important.
It says here, planted by streams of water.
As important as it is to be planted,
we must make sure we don't plant ourselves
outside in a field that's gonna be chopped down
by lumber workers.
We are to plant ourselves by streams of water.
Water nourishes and feeds the tree
to grow strong and permanent.
Just like the tree has water,
we need God's word and God's Holy Spirit
to nourish us, to feed us, and to counsel us.
We need God's word, but we need God's Holy Spirit.
The fourth P is productivity.
The word here is fruit.
It will bear fruit.
When a tree is healthy, drinking water,
and firmly planted, it doesn't only grow,
but it bears fruit.
If we are reading and meditating on God's word,
if we are being constantly filled with the Holy Spirit,
if we are positioning ourselves in the correct area
and firmly plant ourselves,
we too will bear fruit for Jesus.
By our fruit, people will be able to tell
what really matters to us.
I wanna ask you a question.
What is the fruit of your life?
Do you have any fruit?
Is your fruit sour or sweet?
What type of fruit is your life producing?
The fifth P is perpetuity.
It says the leaf does not wither.
We are to be in a state of being perpetual.
That is never ending for eternity.
Our leaf does not wither when life gets stormy.
We had a few typhoons this year,
haven't we in Hong Kong, T10.
What happens to you when your life gets stormy?
We need to look at trials.
We need to look at the typhoons in life
as a test that will only make us stronger.
We cannot fold to harsh times and bad weather.
The leaf of God does not wither and we are the leaf.
My friends, do not give in.
There will be times in 2024
when every one of us will feel like giving in.
Do not give in.
My last P is prosperity.
It says whatever they do will prosper.
If we abide in God, everything we do will prosper.
We may not always see it that way or even ever see it.
We must choose what we want our ministry on earth
to be about.
Is it to be about us
or is it to be about the generations to come?
We need to leave a legacy for Christ, not our name.
That's my 2024 challenge to you.
Who are you leaving a legacy to?
Who's coming after you?
Who are you sowing into?
I want to encourage each one of you to find someone
that you can actually regularly find time
to sow into their lives.
My 2024 prayer for you is for an intellectually
excellent mind.
One is that is informed,
one that makes important distinctions
when a less mature mind fails to do so.
One that has deeper and deeper insights
into issues of importance.
Be planted by streams of water.
Simple, be planted.
Who are the people you're spending time with?
Where are you getting fed?
Be saturated in God's word
and saturated in God's Holy Spirit.
And you will be blessed.
Our church will be blessed.
And most importantly, our city will be blessed.
Our city will be blessed.
What I want to say as I'm moving towards a conclusion
is I want to bless you.
I want to bless you dear church
for the past, the present and the future.
As we come to the end of an eventful period in our history,
the last word many of us might use
to describe this period is blessing.
In fact, some other words might come to mind.
And yet blessing is an important aspect
of our Hong Kong culture.
We see the character fuk or fu everywhere.
Meaning prosperity, fortune, good luck, happiness.
It's most popular amongst the young children
and the unmarried when we get to licy time
at Lunar New Year.
But fuk or fu can also mean blessing.
And we as Christians use it in our vocabulary
with phrases like (speaking in foreign language)
God bless you.
And blessing is also an important aspect of our faith life.
It's mentioned over 400 times in scripture.
In his song 10,000 Reasons,
Matt Redmond encourages us, doesn't he?
♪ Bless the Lord, oh my soul ♪
♪ And all that is within me ♪
♪ Bless his holy name ♪
From Psalm 103.
In the New Testament in Ephesians one,
we read, "Blessed be the God and father
"of our Lord Jesus Christ, who has blessed us in Christ
"with every spiritual blessing in the heavenly places."
Now that's a lot of blessing.
But it leads me very nicely to highlight three blessings
that the Bible mandates.
I wanna take them one at a time.
The first one is this.
We are to bless God.
As Christians, we surely say God blesses us.
Even in these difficult past few years,
God's blessings greatly outnumber the trials
that came with virus, political unrest,
and financial instability, without belittling
or making light of the hardship that many of us have faced.
But what does it mean that we can bless God?
If God is perfect, how can we bless him?
To bless God simply means to praise him
or to honor his name.
The Hebrew word translated bless in the Old Testament
literally means to kneel,
indicating the idea of honoring the Lord.
We do not add anything to him when we bless him,
yet we worship him as our appropriate response
to say his greatness and his love for us.
As we saw earlier in the Psalms,
we often find verses that speak of blessing the Lord.
Another example is found in Psalm 104, verse one.
Bless the Lord, O my soul.
There it is again.
O Lord, my God, you are very great.
You are clothed with honor and majesty.
So that's the first thing, we're to bless God.
And secondly, we are to bless each other.
We know that we have been so greatly blessed.
So many of us have been given so much,
material goods, adequate incomes,
families, friends, jobs, homes.
Being part of the vine year long
is in itself a huge blessing.
That's just for starters.
If you are a Christian, then whatever your circumstances,
you have been given the greatest gifts,
faith, hope, and love.
You have been blessed with the means of grace
and hope of glory.
If you have Christ, you have been given everything
that is eternally worthwhile.
So the big question is why?
Why have I, why have you been so blessed?
And the answer to that question is found in Genesis 12,
verses two to three.
We call it the Abrahamic covenant.
This is God's promise to Abraham.
God said to Abraham, now bear in mind
when God said this promise to Abraham,
Abraham was about 90 years of age, right?
His wife was barren and he had no kids, right?
And he said, "I will make you a great nation
"and I will bless you and I will make your name great
"so that, so that,
"so that you will be a blessing.
"I will bless those who bless you
"and the one who curses you, I will curse.
"And in you, all the families of the earth shall be blessed."
God was saying to Abraham and is saying to us today,
"I bless you, you bless others."
Simple, I will bless you, yes.
So that, so that you will bless others.
Can I challenge you today and every day
to ask God, who can I be a blessing to today?
A smile, can we try it by the way?
Yeah, you can smile, good, a smile.
Do you know what it can mean so much?
A kind word, an act of service.
Oh, by the way, can some people in Hong Kong
start pressing the door open button on the left
instead of door close button?
That's a blessing.
Have you noticed, right?
The door close button's worn out, right?
The door open is pristine, right?
No, nothing's on it, yeah.
Start blessing people by holding the lift for them.
That's a very simple one, right?
A compassionate heart will share God's love
with those who perhaps may be feeling overwhelmed
by circumstances.
So we have to bless God.
We're to bless God and we are to bless each other.
And thirdly, we are to bless our city.
There's almost an amen there, good, I like it.
Proverbs 11, 11 says, "Through the blessing
"of the upright," that's us,
"Through the blessing of the upright,
"a city will be exalted."
Wow, stick this on your fridge.
Hong Kong is our home.
Its people are our family.
If we were to begin each day with a short prayer
to bless Hong Kong, bless its people,
and oh yes, bless the vine.
And bless every other church in our city as well
at the same time.
I believe that we would very soon see a change
in the spiritual atmosphere here.
Dr. Ed Silvozo, a friend of mine,
in his excellent book, "Prayer Evangelism,"
how to change the spiritual climate
over your home, neighborhood, and city,
lists four steps based on Jesus' instructions
to the 72 disciples in Luke 10.
He says this, "Number one, bless them.
"Number two, fellowship with them.
"Number three, take care of their needs.
"And then, at the bottom of the pile,
"proclaim the good news."
Step one is blessing.
Dr. Ed describes it as speaking peace to them.
He says, "Bless, befriend, care, share,
"bless, befriend, care, share."
How often do churches do it the other way around?
We organize programs, courses, activities,
where we should start by blessing.
So let's begin today.
I wanna finish by praying a priestly blessing upon you.
It's called an Aaronic blessing,
after Aaron from the book of Numbers.
And we sang the song earlier, inspired Carrie Jobe
and Cody Cairns to write the song "Blessing."
There's been sung all around the world in many languages.
In fact, at the first service, we sang it in Cantonese.
We're gonna sing it again in a few minutes.
And I invite the band to come back and you to stand, please.
I wanna give you the reference point.
It comes from Numbers 6, 24 to 26.
It says, "The Lord bless you and keep you.
"The Lord make his face to shine upon you
"and be gracious to you.
"The Lord lift up his countenance upon you
"and give you peace."
You might remember at the beginning of the sermon,
I started a little bit controversially
by talking about the church building.
And I'm gonna finish on a similar controversial thing.
I love this song, but whenever I hear it sung in church,
we always sing it wrong.
I see what I see, we sing this song.
I see congregation members with their eyes closed,
maybe their arms raised singing to God.
This is not meant to be sung to God.
We are meant to be singing this to each other.
It is not, "Bless the Lord, O my soul."
We might do that afterwards.
So what I'm proposing in line with my three points,
all good sermons have three points,
is this, in a moment we're gonna pray a prayer
to bless God.
It's right to do that.
Then as we sing the verse, "The Lord bless you."
The Lord bless you.
I'm gonna suggest we just sing it to each other.
Ivan.
♪ The Lord bless you and keep you ♪
We sing it to each other.
Now this is a little bit strange, you know,
particularly those that are Englishmen,
you know, don't like this sort of thing.
The Lord bless you.
We're gonna sing this to each other.
We're gonna rejoice in this as we sing it to each other.
In 2024, we're going to a new year
and we're singing over each other,
"Lord bless you and keep you."
For the second time we sing it,
we're gonna face the outside world.
We're gonna face you and Long.
For one easy way we go there,
I know you and Long's that way and that way,
but we've got stairs here.
And we're gonna sing out over you and Long.
You and Long, the Lord bless you.
Yeah, we're gonna do it.
We're gonna sing over our beloved city.
By the time you get to the amens,
and there's loads of those,
anything might be happening.
But what we're gonna do is this.
We're gonna bless God.
We're gonna bless each other.
And we're gonna bless our city.
Can I hear amen to that?
That was three of you.
Let's try it again.
Can I hear amen?
Let's pray.
Now this is the bit you can close your eyes for.
I'm just telling you.
You haven't got to look at anyone else.
Dear God, we bless your holy name today.
Thank you for your goodness.
Thank you for your crown of steadfast love and mercy.
We recognise all that you have done for us as a church
and for every church in this city.
And all that you continue to do now
and all that you will do in the future.
In Jesus' name.
Amen.
Bless you.
Let's get ready to sing.
To each other.
Wow.
Ready, here we go.
[MUSIC]