[ Music ]
>> As we continue to finish the course of the four years of graduate school, we're going to be having some students come in and do a lot of reading and classroom.
And then we're going to be doing some readings, a lot of the times we do like a conference meeting, but we're going to be doing a lot of reading and classroom.
We're going to be doing a lot of reading and classroom.
So, I guess the only way I can explain a little bit about the course, the way I would say it, is I thought as long as you're reading well, you can do a lot of reading.
And I think that's the way I would say it.
So, to sum up,
what I would like to conclude
is that I don't know
I'm going to say my own words.
I'm going to be discreet
about what I'm going to say.
I'm going to say my own words.
I've been here since June of '14.
I'm going to say my own words today.
I'm going to say my own words.
[Music]
So, I'm going to say my own words.
I'm going to say my own words.
This exhibition is a work for me.
It's a work for me.
I'm not a work for me.
I'm a work for me.
So as long as there are no more people who are trying to kill you,
you're going to be constantly fighting for what you believe.
And the confession is the best way to find someone.
And the confession is not easy to do, but it's worth it.
And the confession is where the hate is really at its worst.
And it's worth us to be there.
I think that's the best way to sort of organize the force of the transition to violence.
So we are trying to get the truth out of this.
We are trying to reach out to the people who are not going to be the best for them.
So we're trying to be a school for them.
And I tell you that we've got to get people to the right and the right is good.
And we have to get people to the right who are going to be the best for us.
We are the only people who are going to have the right to support someone who's expecting to screw them.
So I think it's really important that we focus on the best,
not on the hardest thing we can do, but on the things that matter.
These things that matter, that cause you, that work for you,
those things that make your heart sing,
those things that make your body move, those things that change.
Because it's not just about the things that matter.
We've got to focus on the thing that is important,
that the best is always the best.
That's why I don't like to watch the big things.
I like to watch the small things.
I like to watch the big things.
[Music]