When she was talking about having passion and all of that,
I really admire her passion for workout as well.
She loves exercise and she would, you know, go on workouts.
While I struggle to go on workout once every three months,
I join the gym next door.
But I have promised myself that I will go after VBS.
And then my next statement was,
I'll go after I preach this Sunday.
Hopefully tomorrow I'll bring you good news that I will go.
Right?
I don't have the motivation to get changed into my work
workout clothes.
And I really need that empowerment,
that motivation, as you can say.
And I think that when I,
and reminds me of my younger days,
when I was studying in university,
I joined a Christian choir and it was one of the wildest
thing I've ever done up to that point in my life.
And you go, Christian choir?
Wild?
How they go together?
But if you mix in a bunch of 20 year olds,
it's a whole different story.
There was this year when I first joined the committee
of that Christian choir,
and I was tasked to do a musical for,
not only for that university,
I was in Baptist university, right?
Not only for the university Baptist choir,
we had to join another university's Christian choir
to do something together, to put on a musical together.
Well, doing a musical on its own is really hard
because all the garments, all the props,
look at this, all the choreography, everything.
You can actually see me there,
but I hope that you don't see me
'cause I look really different.
Everything, you have to do it from scratch.
And not only that, I have to work with another university.
What about the scheduling?
What about the cohesion, you know,
the communication between the two conductors?
What are the dynamics like?
And if you still think this is still tame, listen,
I have to do this without WhatsApp.
There's no WhatsApp group, there's no AI, there's nothing.
Okay, so I often tell my K4C class, I'm really old,
I'm like 84, because I remember the first year
I was in university, I'm really embarrassed to say this,
I have to hand in my homework through a floppy disk.
For those of you that don't know what a floppy disk is,
it is that little icon on the Word document
where you wanna push save,
and you see this weird square, right?
That weird square was a floppy disk.
It was from the ancient day, and I have to,
you can only save around two to three documents
in a floppy disk.
So it was really fun.
It was fun to have, you know,
a production using just word of mouth,
just call, just trust that person.
When I schedule something, you will be there.
I couldn't double confirm you through my WhatsApp, right?
If you don't show up, I don't know how to contact you.
And I so vividly remember how overwhelmed I was
when in the meeting,
when I was tasked with this responsibility.
How could I possibly handle everything?
It was my first time being in a committee member,
and now you're telling me that I need to run
this whole thing.
They have chosen the wrong person.
They have made a huge mistake.
But that's the thing.
Jesus gives every one of his volunteer a task
that can feel just like that daunting sometimes.
In Acts 1.8, right before Jesus ascended to heaven,
Jesus said, "You will receive power
"when the Holy Spirit come on you,
"and you will be my witness in Jerusalem,
"and in all Judea and Samaria,
"and to the ends of the world."
Can you imagine how overwhelming it is
for the first disciples?
The small, ordinary group of men and women
were told to bring the message of Jesus to the whole world.
No social media, no microphones, no Bible app,
just their voices, their stories,
and the promise of God's power.
And honestly, that could feel overwhelming for us too.
For many of us, it's not easy or natural
to talk about our faith,
especially with people close to us.
Maybe you feel nervous to bring up Jesus in your family
because you don't wanna cause tension
or to be misunderstood.
Maybe you feel awkward sharing your faith with friends,
worrying that what they will think about you,
maybe they think that you're very pushy, maybe at work.
You wonder if it's even possible or wise
to share what you believe.
Our series of Uncharted
led us to examine the unchartedness of our early churches
and the season our church is in.
Just like those first believers,
we are finding ourselves stepping into territory
we have never been before,
facing new challenges, new opportunities,
and sometimes new fears.
The early churches didn't have a step-by-step manual
for what to do next.
They were called to trust God
and they have to follow the Spirit's leading
and to share the message of Jesus in places and ways
that was unfamiliar and even risky.
In the same way as a church family,
we are navigating our own uncharted waters.
Maybe we're starting a new ministry,
reaching out to new people,
or simply learning to trust God in our journey.
In situations where we feel uncertain or overwhelming,
just like the early disciples,
we might feel small, unprepared,
unsure of how to move forward.
But the good news is we are not alone.
In the first week, our elder Deborah shared with us
about what it means to wait in active faith.
Waiting isn't just about sitting around doing nothing.
It's a posture of hope and expectation.
The early believers didn't wait passively.
They trusted in Jesus' promise and the Holy Spirit
and their waiting was filled with purpose.
And then last week,
Pastor John spoke about what it means to,
to remember the word, receive, thank you,
to what it means to receive.
The waiting was finally over.
Through Christ, God sent us the Holy Spirit,
not just to gather in the upper room,
but as a gift for everyone,
men and women, young and old,
people from every nation.
It's a gift for all.
And today, we're gonna talk about what it means
to be empowered by the Holy Spirit.
As the theologian, Gordon Fee, has said,
"The gift of the Spirit is not given
"so that believers may enjoy
"a private spiritual experience,
"but so that they may participate
"in the life and mission of the church
"as the new people of God."
There is a purpose and mission behind this gift.
The Holy Spirit empowers us
for what God is calling us to do.
We're not left alone to face this daunting task.
We are empowered together by the Spirit
to live out God's mission in the world.
But what is our mission?
As Acts 1.8 says, before Jesus ascended to heaven,
He said, "You will, we will be His witness in Jerusalem
"and in all Judea and Samaria,
"and to the ends of the world."
It was clear that the mission to the disciples
was to be Christ's witnesses,
not just in Jerusalem, but till the end of the world.
But this mission wasn't just for them back then.
It was for us too.
We are called to be Christ's witness today
in our home, in our workplaces.
But what is a mission?
What does being a witness mean?
When I was younger, I attended a local church
where every few months, all the community groups,
everyone would go out to hand out gospel tracts.
Do you know what are gospel tracts?
There they are.
They are small pamphlets that explain what the gospel is,
usually with a simple story.
It's very in your face, right?
They explain what the gospel is,
usually with a short story or Bible verse.
We would stand around the parks and bus stops
and wait for people.
Imagine that you were given out a bunch of these
and you have to stand around bus stops.
And then when the people get off the bus
from work or whatever, we have to go,
"Hi, I'm June.
"I'm one of the Christians around this area.
"Have you heard of Jesus yet?"
That, to an introvert, is so cringey
that every time they made me go,
I'll be like, "I don't feel well today.
"I cannot go today.
"This is going to be so cringey
"if I have to walk up to someone sitting,
"enjoying their sunny afternoon."
And I go, "Hi."
So creepy.
But when I told my pastors back then,
she would say, "Oh, but you should not be ashamed
"of the gospel.
"You need to be the witness."
Is that what being a witness is?
I wonder at that time.
Later, during my university years,
the pressure looked a little different.
Remember, I was organizing the musical in my second year?
I was also motivated by my peers,
not by my parents, by my classmates,
to have a high GPA.
That means like the annual average score
for that year, right?
And because that is the way to be a good witness
to my friends and family.
Do you know what my GPA was
in the first year, first semester?
Generally, people get 3.5
because it is the easiest semester
and everyone wants to get a high one
so that by the end of the third year,
they have something to sit on, right?
Everyone gets around 3.5 or something.
I also got a three.
I got a 2.3.
That was really, really bad.
Honestly, and so,
but the pressure motivates me.
Not only the pressure motivates me,
I actually have a friend, my classmate,
who's also my dormitory flatmate.
She would get up at five o'clock
in the morning to study.
As a university student,
I didn't get up at five.
I tried to, but that motivate me.
So actually, I raised my GPA
from 2.3 to 3.1.
And over that time,
I realized that I was reducing
to being a witness,
to just having good behaviors
or impressive achievements.
That mindset brought a lot of pressure.
I felt like I constantly had to live up
to some perfect Christian standards.
And when I inevitably fall short,
it left me with a sense of shame and guilt.
But the most difficult place to be a witness,
for me, has always been at home.
My parents, more than anyone, know my flaws.
My laziness, my procrastination,
and those rebellious moments.
Trying to be witness in my own family
has often felt impossible
because they see the real me
and not the church me.
If I'm honest,
sharing my faith at home
is the most difficult.
So what is being a witness?
In the ancient world,
a herald was a messenger
sent from the battlefield.
Imagine a city full of anxious people
waiting to hear who had won the war.
And then the herald finally arrived
and shouted the good news,
the victory, to these people
and everything changed.
The whole city rejoiced.
The future looked different.
The Greek word for this word,
this joyful announcement,
is called euangelion.
The same word we use for gospel
or the good news.
This is the picture
that the first Christian used
when they talked about Jesus.
They believed that through his death
and resurrection,
Jesus had already won
the ultimate victory
over sin, death, and evil.
The victory is real.
It has already happened.
But just like history,
imagine World War II, right?
For example,
even after the enemy
was defeated in their homeland,
many places still lived under occupation.
The news of the victory has arrived,
but the effects hadn't reached
every corner yet.
People in those places
lived in the in-betweens.
They knew victory was won,
but the old powers
were still in the present for a time.
And that's the world we live in.
That's the world we live in.
We've heard the good news
that Jesus has won,
but we still live and experience pain,
suffering, and injustice.
The effects of his victory
are not fully here yet.
We live in this tension,
this already but not yet tension.
So what does it mean
to be a witness in Christ?
It means being like the herald
who brings the news of victory.
It means living, speaking,
and making choices in ways
that show people
Jesus has already won.
Even while we wait for the fullness
of his victory to come,
our lives become signals to the world
that a new reality has begun.
Even in a world that hasn't yet seen
the final peace,
we live as a people
who know that the outcome is secure.
And how can we do something
that seems impossible?
That seems impossible, right?
We are living in this injustice.
We're experiencing pain and suffering,
and we have to show people that,
no, the victory is done.
We are set free from our sin.
We are set free from our pain.
There can be justice in this place,
but I don't see it yet.
Nor my friends have seen it yet,
but I have to live and speak
and make decisions and choose
as if the final victory
is here already.
How can we do something
that seems near impossible?
But before the commission,
there was the promise.
You will receive power
when the Holy Spirit comes on you.
You will receive power.
We are empowered by the Holy Spirit
to live out this command.
We're not doing this
out of our own strength,
nor we should be.
We have access to the Holy Spirit,
who is our ever-present help.
We are empowered.
Peter's life and his sermon
after Pentecost is a demonstration
of how the Spirit empowers us
for this mission.
Just look at, can you recall
some of what Peter has gone through
before the Pentecost,
before Jesus died?
He boldly walked on water
for a moment,
and then sank in fear.
He tried to defend Jesus
by cutting off soldiers' ear,
acting impulsively.
Most painfully,
he denied even knowing Jesus
three times.
In all of these moments,
Peter's action was driven
by what you called
self-reliance zeal.
This means that he was relying
mostly on his own energy,
his own ideas of what should be done,
and his own desire
to prove his loyalty to Jesus.
It was courage fueled
by his own effort,
by trying harder,
by pushing forward,
by reacting in the moment.
But no matter how sincere he was,
it wasn't enough.
His courage kept running out
when the pressure was on.
Peter was passionate.
He wanted to be faithful,
but over and over again,
he found himself falling short,
sinking, falling,
acting out of fear or confusion.
He was just like us,
full of good intention,
but often lacking the strength
to follow through.
Don't know if you've ever felt that way.
We wanted to do something good
for people, to serve them,
but accidentally,
not of our own choosing.
We hurt them by forcing our thoughts
and ideas over them,
by questioning them too hard.
That was absolutely me.
When I was younger,
in my university year,
I had a friend who is like Eeyore
in Winnie the Pooh.
I know, I know.
I feel so sorry for him too.
Like, he is a Christian.
We have been together in the church
for many years,
and he would come and say,
"Hi."
And I go,
"What do you like?
You know, you don't have to."
Also, he served in church a lot.
He is in the production team.
He also lead worship.
He also do a lot of stuff,
but he just felt so broken
and so tired all the time,
and nothing brings him joy.
In my heart, I really want him
to be joyful.
I believe that as you're a Christian,
you should be,
you can be joyful.
This is the life that Jesus
has given to us.
That was my intention.
But at the end of the day,
he go, "June, can you not ask me
any more questions?
Can you just stay away from me
for a while?
You are pushing me too hard."
And I realized that no matter
how good my intention is,
I was hurting him.
I was pushing my idea
of what a Christian look like
onto him.
It was good intention,
but falling short.
But then we see Peter
after Pentecost.
In Acts 2.25,
we see that Peter was not alone.
He was filled with the Holy Spirit.
Peter stands in front
of a huge crowd
and preached by citing Psalm 16.
He says,
"David said about him,
'I saw the Lord was always
before me,
because he is at my right hand.
I will not be shaken.
Therefore, my heart is glad
and my tongue rejoices.
My body will also rest in hope,
because you will not abandon me
to the realm of the dead.
You will not let your Holy One
see decay.'"
Here is what Peter is doing.
He's looking back at what
King David wrote in the Psalms,
and he realized David
wasn't just talking about himself.
David was pointing forward
to someone greater,
the true Holy One,
who would not stay dead,
who would rise again.
Peter saw that Jesus
is the only one that truly fits
what David describes.
Jesus is the Holy One
who died but did not see decay,
because God raised him
from the dead.
Peter's sermon at Pentecost
wasn't about condemning
or passing judgment,
telling them off that,
"You should have known
the Bible said so clearly."
He wasn't judging them
for not knowing.
No, Peter was one of them.
He was a Jew who had grown up
with the same hopes
and same dreams,
waiting for God's promise
to be fulfilled.
Just like everyone who listens
to him that day,
Peter had wondered,
"When will the Messiah come?
Who is going to fulfill
all that God promised
to King David?"
His heart was full
of the same longing,
the same question
as the people gathered around him.
But now,
filled with the Holy Spirit,
Peter boldly announces
that the answer to those hopes
and those dreams is Jesus,
the Son of God,
the true descendant of David,
and the long-awaited Messiah.
Peter's message
was deeply personal.
He wasn't delivering
cold theology.
He was sharing
the fulfillment
of his people's greatest hope.
He stood not as an outsider,
but a fellow seeker
whose eyes had been opened
by God's grace.
This is what it means
to be a witness.
To be a witness
is not simply to declare facts
or argue people into believing.
It is much more than that.
Being a witness,
as Peter shows us,
means stepping into the world
of the people we are speaking to,
understanding their fears,
their hopes,
and their deepest question.
It means that allowing
the Holy Spirit to fill us
so that our words come out
not from pride or distance,
but from genuine compassion
and shared humanity.
For us today,
being witness of Jesus
is more than just sharing a message.
It is about living it out.
It looks like really listening
to the people around us,
our friends, our colleagues,
our classmates,
getting to know their stories
and looking for ways
to connect them,
their questions and struggles
to the hope we have found in Jesus.
It is living with humility
and being real.
It's not about acting
as we have got it all together
or that we're better than others
so that we can tell you
about who Jesus is,
but being honest
as people who have found hope
and healing in Jesus
and want to share that with others.
Peter was not alone.
The Holy Spirit empowered Peter
to see the hearts of the people,
to see the hearts of what the people need
so that he could give them
the hope that they need.
We are empowered by the Holy Spirit
to do the same.
When our colleagues annoyed us,
you have a colleague in mind,
when our colleagues annoyed us,
instead of our usual frustration,
we're empowered by the Holy Spirit
to understand.
It doesn't mean that we have to go suffer
and go, "Yeah, you annoyed us.
Let me just suffer."
But we are empowered
by the Holy Spirit to understand.
When our friends shared
about their problems,
we are empowered by the Holy Spirit
to direct them to the hope
that Jesus has for him or her.
What is really amazing about Peter
is that he was just
an ordinary fisherman.
He wasn't known for being
a great speaker.
In fact, before Pentecost,
Peter was often impulsive.
He made a lot of mistakes,
and sometimes he was even scared
to admit that he knew Jesus.
But once the Holy Spirit came,
everything changed.
The same is true for us.
We may feel inadequate, unqualified,
or unsure of what to say.
Yet, this is not in our own strength
or eloquence that matters.
Whether we are making
godly decisions at work,
befriending someone who feels
left out at school,
or choosing to communicate
with love and patience at home,
these are all visible expressions
of our inner conviction
that Jesus reigns.
Each act of faith,
each moment of kindness,
reflects our trust
that Jesus has already won
and victory over sin
and that by His Spirit,
we can live differently.
It is not out of our own strength
that we can go and force
ourselves to be kind
and force ourselves to do more.
It is the Holy Spirit
that is with us
so that we're able to understand
and we want to choose
to live differently
because we are empowered
by the Holy Spirit.
Moreover, Peter's courage
wasn't something he drummed up
from within himself.
He didn't suddenly become eloquent
because he tried harder
or studied more.
Instead, the Spirit filled him,
gave him the words,
and gave him the insight
from God's Word.
So much so that when he spoke,
his message could cut straight
to the hearts of the listener.
The Spirit empowered Peter
to be bold through his revelation
in his word.
Look at Acts 2, 22-23.
Fellow Israelites, listen to this.
Jesus of Nazareth
was a man accredited by God
to you by miracles,
wonders, and signs,
which God did among you through him.
As you yourself know,
this man was handed over to you
by God's deliberate plan
and foreknowledge,
and you, with the help of wicked men,
put him to death
by nailing him to the cross.
In just a few words,
Peter brings together two big truths
about the cross,
truths that are both comforting
and challenging.
First, Peter wants everyone to know
that Jesus' death was not a plan B.
It was not an accident.
The cross, like things,
it's not like things got out of control
or maybe it's God's original plan backfired
so he had to come up with a backup.
No, it may look that way,
may look that way,
especially when you see Jesus being betrayed,
arrested, and nailed to a cross.
From the outside,
it might seem like everything went wrong,
like evil and chaos won that day.
But Peter made it clear,
this was never plan B.
Jesus' death was not a surprise to God
or a mistake in the story.
Peter says Jesus was handed over
by God's deliberate plan
and foreknowledge.
That means God already know exactly
what he was doing all along.
The cross wasn't God's scrambling fix to a problem.
It was always the plan to save us.
What looked like the defeat
was actually God working out his greatest victory,
even in the darkest moment.
God was in control,
turning the very thing that would have,
turning it into the very thing
that would have rescued us.
But Peter wouldn't let the crowd off the hook.
He said, "And you,
"with the help of the wicked man,
"put him to death."
So yes, it was God's plan,
but it was also human sin
that nailed Jesus to the cross.
It was jealousy, fear,
rejection that led to his crucifixion.
The religious leaders schemed,
the crowd shouted,
the Roman soldiers carried it out.
And yet, even though God used their actions for good,
they were still responsible for what they did.
God's plan doesn't excuse our guilt.
God's sovereignty and our responsibility go hand in hand,
and we can't always explain how that works,
but both are true.
Now, here's where the Holy Spirit comes in.
As Peter is preaching,
it is not just a history lesson or theology lecture.
The Holy Spirit is at work.
His empowerment is at work,
taking those words and pressing them
right into people's hearts.
In Acts 2, 37, it says,
"When the people heard this,
"they were cut to the heart."
It was not just about knowing it was my responsibility.
It was something that actually were impressed in their heart,
and they felt for it, they felt about it.
They have a feeling to it,
and that's what the Spirit does.
He brings clarity into,
clarity about who Jesus is,
and conviction about where we stand with God.
It's like the lights come on,
and suddenly it's personal.
The crowd didn't just understand the message,
they felt it.
They realized that the need for Jesus,
and cried out, "Brothers, what shall we do?"
It was this moment of the Holy Spirit in you
that brings clarity into our heart.
And when we sit, and when we are reading the Bible,
when we are praying, when we are interacting with people,
when we are listening in the sermon,
the Holy Spirit is in work, in us,
bringing us conviction,
and we shout to God, "Oh no, I've sinned against you.
"What shall we do?"
When you think back to the moment
you first put up your hand to receive Jesus,
or the time you felt deeply
that something in your life needed to change,
that wasn't your reasoning or your emotions at work.
It was the Holy Spirit inside you,
moving you, bringing conviction into your heart.
It's not a conviction to shame you or to guilt you,
as if you're letting God down if you don't get it right.
Rather, it is a conviction
that wakes you up to the reality of God's love
and beauty of what Jesus has done for you.
The Spirit doesn't just simply point out what's wrong.
He draws us towards what is right.
He opens our eyes to see Jesus more clearly,
and moves us to turn away from old patterns
and step into a new way of living.
This is conviction that comes not from fear or punishment,
but from hope.
Hope that change is possible, that forgiveness is real,
and that Jesus welcomes us into this new life.
So when you feel this gentle nudge to turn from old habits,
to embrace something new that God is calling you to,
recognize that it is the Spirit's loving work,
drawing you closer to Jesus and making you more like Him,
not by your own strength,
but by His empowering presence within you.
We are not left alone.
The Holy Spirit empowers us to be witnesses,
not in extraordinary moments,
but in the ordinary, everyday rhythm of life.
This is what makes our witness undeniable.
It is not about having it all together,
but about letting the reality of Jesus
shine through our real transformed lives.
The world can't ignore a life changed by God.
The world can't ignore you being changed by God.
The world cannot ignore the fact that in the old you,
the past you, you will feel agitated,
you will be angry, you will react in an impulsive way.
But then in that moment, you chose to quiet down.
The world cannot ignore that.
The world cannot ignore the fact that
I should make this decision at work
because everyone is doing the same,
but then you chose differently.
That decision, that turn,
your colleagues cannot ignore that.
Your classmate cannot ignore the fact that
when you go into the classroom,
you speak to those that were being ignored.
Your family members cannot ignore the fact that
usually when they shouted at you,
when they talk mean things about you,
you would slam the door.
They cannot ignore the fact that you chose to listen.
We do not need to do anything great,
but in our every moment, in our every decision,
we choose Jesus because He has won.
He has freed us from comparison.
He has freed us from self-centeredness.
We can embrace this new life and this new hope.
And if you have not received it yet,
you do not need to be guilt-tripped by doing this.
It is not something that we will judge,
oh, you're not doing that.
That was a Christian.
No.
Before the commission, there was this promise.
Before you need to do the action,
remember you receive this new life first.
You receive this grace that God has given you first.
You receive it first, and then you be witness
of what the grace, the love, the freedom
that you have received to show people
in your family, in your workplace, and in your home.
We may feel ordinary.
We may feel unprepared.
But God delights in using ordinary people,
people just like me and you, maybe,
to carry out His extraordinary mission.
He doesn't ask us to do it alone
or to muster up our own strength
or to pretend we've had it all together.
He simply asks us to trust Him,
to seek His presence in His word
and in our quiet time with Him,
to receive His Spirit, to receive His grace,
and to take the next step as witness right where we are.
What if we truly believe that the Spirit is with us
in every conversation?
What if we believe that the Holy Spirit
will empower us in every act of kindness,
every moment when we choose to love,
to forgive or to speak up for what is right?
What if, as a church, we lean in together,
allowing the Holy Spirit to transform our weaknesses
into testimonies, our failures into stories of God's grace
and our everyday lives into evidence that Jesus is alive?
Let's be the people where others see more
than just good intentions or nice program.
Let's be a people who live so honestly with such hope
that those around us can't help
but see the reality of Jesus in us.
Let our lives be undeniable proof
that Jesus' victory is real,
that His Holy Spirit really does change everything.
You are called, you are empowered, and you are sent.
And I don't know where you are at with Jesus right now.
Maybe at this moment, if you ask yourself, you go,
actually, I don't have a relationship with Jesus.
That was the prayer I prayed at home, in the bathroom,
a few weeks after my father passed away.
I was a Christian for most of my life
because my grandma was a Christian.
She made every single one of her sons
and in-laws to go to church.
I also went to church when I was really young.
But when my father passed away,
it forced me to ask this question,
God, are you there for me?
And it made me realize that I don't really
have a relationship with Jesus.
I know a lot about Him,
but I don't have a relationship with Him.
And today, if you have to be honest with yourself,
do you feel you have a relationship with Jesus?
So right now, I would like the worship team to come up
and I would like to give a moment for you
to reflect on this.
And just to be honest, God is a loving God.
He knows it already, but there is power
when we bring things into the light.
Maybe at this moment, you do not have
a relationship with Jesus, but He is calling you.
So with every eyes closed right now,
with every head bow,
I would like you to speak to Jesus.
He loves you.
And He wants to.
And He wants you to be honest with Him.
And in this moment, if you know that you may not
have a relationship with Him, but you want to,
you want to receive this grace,
you want to receive this love,
you want to receive this abundant life that He promised,
and you want to turn away from the old way of life
because that has not been working out for you.
You have tried, you have used your own effort,
your own way of living, and it did not work.
You were hurting yourself, you were hurting people
around you, and you did not have a relationship with Jesus.
I'd like you, just at your seat,
that you want to receive this Jesus in your life
to put up your hand.
(gentle music)
He loves you, and He waits for you in every single moment.
I see that hand, thank you.
Maybe you are a Christian,
but you have not been relying
on the Holy Spirit's empowerment.
You have all the good intentions,
but when you're trying to show people that Jesus lives,
you fell short.
I want to pray for you.
If you are one of those people that you want to be empowered
by the Holy Spirit today to live out the victorious life,
the reality that Jesus is alive,
I would like you to open up your hand
and to receive this Holy Spirit that empowers you
to live victoriously, to live differently.
Jesus, we thank you, because today,
someone here has made a decision to follow you.
I pray that by your grace and your power,
that you are going to fill him up with the Holy Spirit
to empower him to turn from his old ways and to run to you.
I pray that as he make his decision to receive you,
that you will give him and honor him
and know that you will give him an abundant life.
Thank you for dying for us on the cross.
Thank you for forgiving our sin.
Today, we turn away from our past way of life
and to turn to you, Jesus, and we thank you.
For this new life that is ahead of the people,
and we pray in Jesus' name, amen.
And I pray for the people
who also wants to be empowered by the Holy Spirit today
to live a life of victorious life,
that in every single moment,
that we are going to know the presence
of the Holy Spirit with us.
In our action, in our speech, in our decision,
your empowerment is real.
Your presence is undeniable.
And today, we're going to learn to seek you.
We'll learn to be with you in all that we do.
And we are thankful for that.
And in Jesus' name we pray, amen.