Well, it's good to see you all and to be back. I am excited about Christmas
I'm excited about introducing Christmas traditions to my baby girl Ellie
In Germany, they have a tradition
It's a Christmas calendar, but it's not the chocolate calendar
It's like it's a calendar that has big pockets and every day. There's actually quite a significant gift in there
So so I'm ready, you know, I'm that's my one decoration
But
But hey, hey, it's good to see you
Now when I was in university and I feel like I've been talking about university a lot. So it's like far far in the past
I
Did what university students do I studied I played basketball and I hung out with my friends
Now there was one semester or one season
Where I really studied a lot
Like all the time and my friends they went on these exciting road trips event of Vancouver
You know Canada on a road trip
Need all sorts of stuff, but I didn't go because I needed a study or I felt like I needed to study
And so I missed out on on all these fun trips. I missed out on hanging out with my friends and when I look back
at that time I
Actually think that I chose the wrong thing
Because I
Should have spent time with my friends instead of studying now. I know I'm in Hong Kong. I
am aware there's a lot of you know parents from Hong Kong here and
I did
I I do believe studying is important. I did study
You know, I was a good student. So I actually got good grades, but what I'm actually talking about is I studied excessively
Because there was a fear inside of me somehow that I needed to do more
You know order to do well and it actually kept me from really enjoying my friendships
And it kept me from having better relationships my friends
Now luckily, I didn't do that throughout all University, but I did it for a part of my studies
But isn't that interesting how we can invest ourselves in the things that we think are so important at
That moment in our lives, you know take all the time we take all the energy
maybe even a lot of resources and
Then when we look back at those things
We realized that they really did not matter that much or that they're really not that important
So
For me it was
Studying excessively didn't improve my grades
Lower the quality of my friendships. I mean that was basically it
For a lot of us, I believe it's you know working excessively
Right. There's this saying I used to put as a screensaver on my phone that says nobody
ever
Regrets spending what wait, how does it go?
Let me get this right
Nobody
Well, let me just I'm not gonna I'm not gonna remember this basically it's the moral of the story
How about that the moral of the story is this that?
We add on our when we're at the end of our lives. We never wish that we would have spent more time at the office
Finally landed there right took me a while, but I brought I made it. Yes
Got a little confused there in my brain and
And and the thing is what you know, why do we work so much?
Is it sometimes maybe it's the police someone sometimes it's because we want, you know
promotion where we're chasing after
You know better better income for a family and and up to certain degrees that you know that that can be okay
But there is also like an excessiveness, you know to that a lot of times in us
Other ways that we might invest ourselves and things
Maybe there's some relationships that are not that important. But for some reason they absorb all our time and our energy and so we give
People all our time and energy instead of the ones that we should give it to
Now, I don't know what you're you know, investing yourself and what you're spending your time on what you're using your energy for
But what I want to explore with you today is how can we make investments that
Truly matter, you know, how can we how can we focus on?
Using our energy our resources our time and put it in the place
That actually is really important so that when we look back we don't have to say. Oh my gosh. What did I do?
I miss out on all these fun road trips
You know and we have to be bummed that's quite you know, I can get over that one
But there's other things, you know where there can be great regrets and we can miss out greatly
on of course also especially what actually God has for us and
So we're continuing our sermon series living the kingdom parables
We've been looking every week at one of the parables of Jesus
Part of it what we're looking to do is to be challenged by them, you know for Jesus to challenge us
in our attitudes and our thinking and
So that we can respond and align ourselves, you know to his kingdom values and we can shift our perspective
It can live differently in light of you know
Jesus teaching and
So I want to encourage us as we go no more into the message to actually to open your heart and say Lord
I want to be challenged by you. I want to hear from you what you have to say to me and
So actually let me pray for us. Let me pray pray over us
Heavenly Father we
We are here because we want to hear from you
We desperately need to hear from you
We want to have you speak into our lives and say yes to what you have for us because what you have is always the best
So will you prepare our hearts now to receive?
What you have I praise in your name Jesus. Amen
So we're in the gospel of Luke and I just want to set the context before we go into a specific parable so there is
The context is it actually says there's a thousands of people
Around Jesus and
Jesus is teaching his disciples. So it's kind of like he's teaching his disciples and everybody else is listening to him teaching his disciples
and
The topic that he's teaching on is actually on obstacles to discipleship
like things that keep you from following Jesus that can derail your in your journey of being a Christian and
the thing that that Jesus talks right before we get to the text that we're gonna look at is
he talks about fearing God about fearing man and he
Talks about being faithful to him even in persecution
you know, even when we face persecution that we are faithful to Jesus and
So then he moves to the next obstacle and that's where we're gonna pick up. So we're in Luke chapter 12 starting in verse 13
It says this
Someone in the crowd said to him teacher tell my brother divide inheritance with me
Jesus replied man who appointed me judge or an arbiter between you
Then he said to them watch out
Be on your guard against all kinds of greed
Life does not consist in abundance of possessions
So we're gonna walk through this piece by piece. So I'm not reading everything to you right now
But here's a man. Maybe he interrupts Jesus
Maybe just sees the moment when Jesus quiet for one second
He jumps in and he brings a request to Jesus and he asked Jesus to make a ruling over
Inheritance, I guess fight or conflict that him and his brother are having
Now, why does he come to Jesus with that?
Well, if you know, he addresses Jesus as a teacher
so
People around Jesus they saw him as a teacher with authority a teacher also of the law a rabbi and
At that time, you know all the rules regarding even inheritance. They were in the Torah. They were in the
first five books of you know, the Bible of the Hebrew Scripture and
So a lot of times rabbis and teachers they made actually rulings
You know, they made judgments and then made decisions help the community sort out things
Might that might be a little bit like a pastor, you know helping
two conflicting parties settle an issue
and
What's interesting though is the man that approaches Jesus if we pay close close attention
He actually doesn't
Ask Jesus to mediate
He wants Jesus to do what's on his agenda. He wants him to make a ruling that
Inheritance is divided, you know, so he comes to Jesus. He wants Jesus to fill his plans his purposes
He is actually not interested in anything else
he just wants Jesus do what he wants him to do and
What
one thing with with that is
You know
That he's not interested in restoring his relationship with his brother. He just wants to get his he wants to get his inheritance
He wants to get what he thinks is owed to him and there is no room for another perspective. He
He just wants Jesus do what he wants from you and Jesus, you know being wise being discerning
You know, he decides not to do a ruling not to do a judging but an instead
He actually turns around and he starts teaching everyone
So not just the man we asked some question not just the disciples, but he's speaking to the whole crowd
and
What he what he says to them is
We find in verse 15
He says watch out be on your guard against all kinds of greed life does not consist in abundance of possessions
I'll just imagine yourself you bring an issue to Jesus and
Then Jesus uses that as a springboard and starts teaching everyone around you and he kind of implies
You know that your requests involved some greed
Make makes us feel a little uncomfortable, right?
And but but why does Jesus bring it to everyone
Because greed it's a human issue. It's actually something that not just this man needs to hear about
It's something that everyone needs to hear about because we all to one degree or another
have heart issues, you know when it comes to possessions and money and
Inheritance and all those things and so Jesus addresses everyone
Now it's at this point in time. It's also important to remember when Jesus addresses something like that
He never does it, you know to shame or to put down
He does it because he wants to bring life. He wants to bring wholeness to an area in our lives that is broken
And he wants to do something new. He wants to do something better. And
So we just need to keep that in mind as we walk through the story
So Jesus starts warning us against greed and actually false narratives that we believe
He says in verse 15 life does not consist in abundance of possessions
But we actually believe that it does right we actually believe that life or abundant life
Exists in abundance of possession
And so he's starting to dress this the slightest
Narrative that we hold that if I only have this much money if I only have this house or this whatever
You know, then I will be okay, then I will live the good life
But Jesus, you know is saying that's not true
You know abundant life does not consist in these things
Well, let's continue in the story
verse 16
And he told him this parable the ground of a certain rich man yielded an abundant harvest
He thought to himself. What shall I do? I have no place to store my crops
Then he said this is what I will do
I will tear it on my barns and build bigger ones and there I will store my surplus grain
And I'll say to myself you have plenty of grain
Laid up for many years take life easy eat drink and be married
now
In this parable, you know, there's a rich man. We're not told why he's rich
There's no hint that he did anything unethical
You know, he didn't somehow do some shady dirty deals and screw somebody over
but we're just told he's wealthy and
then
There's another thing that happens. There's an abundant harvest on top of being already rich
His ground, you know from whatever land he owned is yielding just an absolutely incredible
Harvest much more than expected or would be usual
So he's already he's rich and now he gets this
extra stuff on top of it and
This creates a challenge for him, you know, what what is he going to do with it?
And it's interesting because we're actually let in on this inner dialogue in the parable where we can hear his thoughts
It's kind of scary, right?
If we could hear each other's thoughts
But we get to hear his thoughts
So good. It's that way around out the other way around
and and we get to listen into his own inner inner dialogue and so he is like
Oh, what am I gonna do? You know with all this extra crop because there's a problem. His barns are full. It's plural
Yes, you know multiple barns. He doesn't have one. He has multiple ones. And so he comes up with solution
I'm gonna tear them down. I'm gonna be bigger once I'm gonna store it up and then he concludes the whole thing was saying
That you know and when that's done he can enjoy his life and leisure and eat drink and be merry
That's his plan. You know, that's his conversation and
From from our perspective if we would not know that Jesus beforehand talks about greed if we just would hear the story in a different context
We actually would be quite impressed with this man. Wow, you know, here's somebody who can scale a business
Here's somebody who can be prudent and and build wealth
if there was a YouTube video or something like wow, you know skies like
He made it from like not having as much and he built his business empire, you know, that's impressive
Now because this is in the context of Jesus teaching and we know what comes before we know there are some issue
But what what what is it, you know, what what is the issue that Jesus is addressing here
Well, if you pay close attention to the inner dialogue, we start getting a hint at what the problem is and it actually reveals to us
You know some of the values and some of the motivations that this man is holding in his heart
So if you notice there's all these I and my statements
You know, it's all about him it's all about what he has done it's all his
It's like my crops my abounds my surplus myself
Actually a word transit here's myself is my soul
You know, it's all my my my I I I
There is no thought of every anyone else and there is no thought of God
You know, there's an absence of acknowledgement of God
So this goes in contrast, you know to what Psalm 24 one says says the earth is the Lord's and everything in it
the world and all who live in it, which means that actually
You know God has created everything and all that we have including our life our breath our health
Whatever possessions we have everything is a gift from God
Every single thing now we a lot of times think we did it ourselves
You know, but everything we have is a gift from God and this man, you know, there is no God in his equation
I mean he thinks it's it's all it's all him
So and this is where the twist comes into the parable
verse 20
But God said to him you fool
This very night your life will be demanded from you. Then who will get what you have prepared for yourself?
This is how it will be with whoever stores up things for themselves, but is not rich towards God
So while most of us, you know when you look at
This story what made me think Wow a prudent successful
Businessman who knows how to scale a business and accumulate wealth and do something good
God calls him a fool
You fool. It's quite a different verdict than we would expect, right?
It's also quite strong language right to be called a fool
So why why does God call this man a fool
Well, God calls this man a fool because all of his investments all of his wealth is directed towards himself
It's all for himself
There's no thought of neighbor
You know there it's it's all about himself
and
He just cares about himself. He just invests the money on himself. He doesn't think of anyone else
There's no acknowledgement of God
There is
He actually sees this money as a security
You know that
You can see that in his plans, right? He has a plans that like I will live the abundant life
I'm going to you know, eat drink be merry enjoy my wealth
So he actually placed his faith in his possessions
But he lacks faith in God
And he thinks that his possessions were given the security of his anxious heart
That the possessions will make sure that he's gonna be okay
But when it comes to the end of his life
they actually don't deliver and
The lie is exposed
That so many of us that we actually kind of believe right if we're honest
And then in verse 20 we find out that God tells him, you know this very night your life will be demanded of you
and it's actually interesting because a little literal Greek says your soul, you know before he says my soul and
Then now he says that even our life, you know something that we steward
And it will be demanded of you and then he asked a question and who will get what you have prepared for yourself
Who's gonna have your stuff
And at this time
It just shows the emptiness
the spiritual bankruptcy with which he stands before God, you know because
That's not his question anymore
He has different concerns on at this point
and
Then Jesus concludes by saying, you know gives like a wisdom saying he says is this is how it will be with whoever stores up
Things for themselves, but is not rich towards God. And so there's a contrast
there's like storing up things towards yourself versus being rich towards God and
he's
He's saying, you know
that's a consequence when we're just all about ourselves when you try to find a security and possessions and wealth when we
Maybe try to find power significance influence
We know whatever it is for people money means different things for people or possessions mean different things for people
And whatever is that we're trying to find in that it does not deliver if it's just direct towards herself
So Jesus then concludes that you know
This man made a disastrous investment and actually kind of ends open-ended because we don't know what he does
we don't know what he says now suddenly we don't hear his inner dialogue anymore and
Actually is meant for ourselves to think about you know, what's inside of our what's our inner dialogue?
You know, what are we saying to ourselves?
And so while the man the parable didn't acknowledge God at all
Many of us here we actually do not all of us, but many of us you do
But nonetheless, we're not immune to the chasing after riches and trying to secure a future
through the accumulation of wealth
We we also believe that false narrative even as Christians
Right that possessions they're gonna solve our problems. They're gonna give us security so we can finally rest not be anxious
Possessions are gonna give us significance people gonna listen to me. I'm gonna have influence
Possessions are gonna give us power so I can have an impact, you know, what whatever it is and
And we we believe that and they do to a certain degree
But in the end they never fully deliver and contrary to what Jesus says that life does not consist of abundance of possession
We think it does
You know, we actually believe that it does if you picture an abundant life what you picture
Exactly right and I have to be honest I picture the same thing
But what Jesus is trying to bring a corrective, you know to us
So money and possessions that their idols, you know, the idols of a heart and Tim Keller who's a was a well-known pastor in the US
He defines an idol this way an idol is anything more important to you than God
Anything that absorbs your heart and imagination more than God
Anything you seek to give you what only God can give
and
So in the in the parable, we see that this rich man. He is daydreaming
You know his imagination is stirred by his possessions and by his wealth
And he dreams of how this will give him security. How does will give him a relaxing retirement?
And
But but it reveals, you know that that's his idol
That's what he puts his faith really in and I think with us we've been talking about there's a lot of theoretical in our Christian
Faith we theoretically, you know believe that
Abundant life isn't God, but if we actually look at our life practice we see a lot of times
That we actually place our faith and other things
We actually place our faith and you know in our in our jobs or in in our bank account or whatever it is
Or your house that you own or working towards owning or whatever
And the man that came to Jesus, you know with a request about his inheritance
and he also thought that the inheritance is gonna deliver for him something, you know, whether it's that security again and
We all heard or maybe even experienced personally yourself like just horror stories of inheritance
You know where there's horrible fighting where relationships fall apart
We're just brokenness and just destroys and devastates families
And again, it just shows that we hold this idol in the heart
You know that we think this inheritance is gonna do something and we don't care about the religion
We just gonna we just want to get ours what we think is ours. It doesn't matter if the relationship is destroyed
You know and it's devastating
Now what's interesting when when we think about greed or a lot of times you don't think of ourselves
Like I've heard several pastors say nobody ever comes to me and confesses that they're greedy
You know, they can
People share all sorts of things
You know sexual brokenness
affairs
You know broken relationships. Well, whatever, you know like
Having cheated someone what whatever it may be
But what this shows is that most of us actually don't think of ourselves as greedy
We don't think it's our issue. We think it's the other person's issue and we can always find someone that we can point to you
right
Can always find someone else where you can say? Oh, yeah, it's their issue, but it's not my issue
But here Jesus he's he's exposing these inner dialogues and things in our hearts
He's actually but actually is all of our issue
You know and Jesus is calling us
To bring this issue to him
So that we can overcome this issue
By the power, you know of Jesus in our lives and that we can live lives that are rich towards God
not just rich towards ourselves
now I
Had a financial
transaction that I was trying to or like a business thing that I was trying to do and
It fell through in the last moment
And I was so angry
I'm a very relaxed person. I know a lot of you don't know me that well
I'm a very relaxed person. I don't get very angry most of the time and
But I was super angry and then as I suddenly realized my strong emotions, I was like, whoa
What's going on here? Why am I so upset?
and
The truth is you know, because I placed hope in this investment that it would do something for me
That actually only God can do
you know, I
Was I thought this thing will bring me security. I thought this thing will bring me significance, but it doesn't you know
That is only found in God
your significance your security
And so when our faith is and other things besides God it's it's hard to live a life that's rich towards God
Because we're trying to hold on to our possessions, you know
We can't be generous other people because we think these possessions are significant
so we should be grab onto them and we can't hold them loosely and
Also keeps us from doing a lot of times the things that Jesus asked us to do
Which maybe there's a brother or sister. He wants us to be generous to you
But if we think this thing will secure us we can't let it go
We can't be generous to that person
And
Jesus he wants to break the power of this grip of greed in our lives
He wants us to be free
Or you were saying what freedom
So we can be free to love other people
It can be free to reflect a carrot of God of generosity towards others
That doesn't just have to be about ourselves and we don't have to direct, you know
All this wealth or whatever it is to us and by the way
This can be anyone you can be rich or poor and and we still struggle with the same heart issue
You know, it's not about who has a lot or who doesn't have much we could we all struggle with with greed
It's a heart issue for all of us
and
And then Jesus actually we're not going to read further. I'm gonna tell you what happens afterwards. He talks about not being anxious
Because our loving father cares for us and to seek first his kingdom
and
Then all these things will be added unto you
you know, it's and
Isn't that amazing that actually God promises us that when we are generous when we live a life
That's you know of love and serving our labors and making investments in the kingdom
Then he will provide for us. He actually will give us what we need
It doesn't mean that we're you know, he's gonna not give us a yacht or something like that
But but he will provide for us what we need. He will take care of us
So seeking the kingdom, you know if we make that a priority in our lives it it means that we're willing to do God's will
And it means that we're following Jesus in all aspects of our lives
but if we're holding idols, you know, they keep us from doing that and
So Jesus wants to free us
So we can actually fully follow him that we can fully live for him and I just picture as a church wouldn't it be amazing?
if we all just grow in
seeking the kingdom and
In obedience to Jesus and living generous lives and growing in generosity. I think it's a process a lot of times
It's not like what's time it's not just from one moment to next that you completely change
What impact you know, we as a community could have for God's kingdom would be amazing. I want to see that
But but in order to do that we need faith
And we struggle to trust God that he will care for us and he will provide for us
So my sense for this that Jesus wants to give us faith faith
You know that he actually wants to today release faith on us
He wants to give us trust so that we can courage us and live for him that we don't have to live in fear
Because it's like, you know, we live by fear when we're holding on to possessions. We're living in fear
Because we think these things will deliver
But he's calling us the faith in him, you know that he loves you. He loves us
He loves our heavenly father loves his children, you know, he will provide for us
I was as I was thinking about as I was reminded of
Being in the US as a child. I couldn't swim and I was a little kid
We read some friends that lived in apartment complex
He had a swimming pool like, you know that people live there can use and
So I remember like running and jumping in a swimming pool, even I couldn't swim
It's not a good idea, right
But the reason why I could do it was because my father was there
Because he caught me because I knew I could trust him. I could rely on him
I could take the step of faith, you know and jump there because he would take care of me
He would help me get back to the edge of the pool. I even went on the diving board
You know and jumped in but it's just because I knew my father had my back and in a similar
way when we when we know
Just the father's love when when we know the saving love and care of Jesus in our lives it
frees us
to be generous and loving towards others
You know
We can have that same type of faith where we can just dive in because we know he loves us
He will take care of us. We can be bold
But if we don't if we don't know his love if you don't believe it if you struggle trust in his heart
So I also believe that today God wants to reveal his love to us
You know that that the reality of his love can break over our lives
That we can start living differently and we can start living generously
Beautifully abundantly and be rich towards God
And seek his kingdom first and make incredible
investments in this kingdom and
See God do things that have
Eternal, you know consequences that make an eternal difference
So, how can I be rich towards God and
Invest how can we be rich for us God invest ourselves in what truly matters?
One invite the worship team to come up
How can we take the step of actually living in this radical generosity
That Jesus called us to where we're not just about accumulating things for ourselves
We're not living in fear, but where you can live in faith
How do we actually do that?
Well, the first thing is it's not about trying harder
you know, it's not not about I'm gonna try harder to be more generous and
Give a little and give a little my time give a little my energy give a little bit of my money
No, it's it's actually acknowledging
It's surrendering to Jesus. It's like I can't do this
And I need you
That's also asking Jesus. I've been holding this this idol in my heart that I think delivers what only you can give
Will you forgive me for this and will instead will you show me?
You know your love for me
Will you show me that you care for me that you provide for me that you will give me what I need
and
Then as that that reality breaks over our lives as a spirit of God, you know makes that known to us
And we can ask them a Lord what how do you want me to be generous this week?
What do you want me to do?
You know, how can I show love?
Towards people around me. Maybe how can I show love towards people here in this church community?
How can I show love towards people in my family and in outside, you know the wider you long community?
And then when God reveals to you what to do, you know, take the step of faith you jump into the pool and
And you do it and you trust, you know that he will work through it
But you also trust that you're not gonna suffer loss because of it
You know, but that you are gonna live life that's rich towards God
So I want to invite everyone to stand and I would love to pray over us
If
What invites you to?
Really think about right now. Am I seeking his kingdom first or is there other things I'm seeking after?
Am I seeking his kingdom first or there are other things I'm seeking after
And
If you
Just say Jesus I want to seek your kingdom, you know
But I'm but I'm struggling to trust you that you are truly good that you will truly deliver that you will truly provide. I
Just want to invite you to stretch out your hand, you know as an expression
Of just openness to God and just a desire and a surrender
To him like I want to seek you. I want to live for you
I don't I want these idols to rule in my heart. I want you Jesus to rule my heart and let me pray over you
Jesus I I thank you so much that you love us so incredibly much
Lord, you know all of our journeys, you know every single heart in this room
You know the things that we hold dear
That we think will you know provide for us deliver things for us give us security
But it's pray that everything is a lie that you expose that right now
That you help us instead to turn our hearts to you now place our faith and our trust in you I
Asked Holy Spirit that you will come right now and you reveal your love to us
The love of the father who doesn't abandon his children who doesn't give bad gifts. He gives good gifts
That's a father that and will add these things unto you when you live that radical life of generosity
And radical life of faith of following him of doing the things Jesus calls us to do
Or will you pour out just this faith and discourage in our hearts
We forgive us for you know for greed where we failed you but will you help us by your spirit to live differently
Will you strengthen us by your grace will you help us to be people of faith not people of fear
We know that is your spirits work. It's not we can't
Do this out of our own strength Lord's will you come right now? We help us to be seekers of your kingdom
As a community I pray all this in your name Jesus. Amen
Let's worship