Thank you, Pastor Chapman. And good morning, everybody. It is such an honor and I'm so
blessed to be able to preach today, this morning. And first of all, I want to ask you a question.
I don't know how many of you can understand about buying fresh fruit. All these housewife
mothers, do you know? Yes? Wow, wonderful. I have to learn from you. I'm a person who
doesn't really understand very well. And many times when I buy fruit, I just look at the
outside appearance, if it is smooth or is shiny. And then especially when I buy avocados,
because I like to eat that very much. And unfortunately, after I bring them home, and
most of the time, the inside of the avocado is black and rotten. One of the common mistakes
when choosing fruit is to pick the outside, the appearance alone. Many people judge by
a fruit quality, mainly in its color, size, and the outward appearance. However, the good
looking fruit is not always the best. And being able to properly to select a high quality
fruit require a certain level of knowledge and skill, like this lady. I've learned from
you. And otherwise, it will lead us to poor selection. In the last two months, we have
been looking at the book of Galatians. In this sermon series, we look at Paul's letter
as he is astonished that Galatian believers are turning away from the truth of the gospel.
They actually cannot discern the good and the bad. They are being deceived and tricked
by a counterfeit gospel. So Paul defends and unpacks the true gospel to the churches so
that God's visions can be lived out by these new Christians.
Today we come to the final section of the Galatian letter, chapter 6, verses 12 to 17.
In this last section, towards the end of Paul's letter, he's given a final warning and benediction.
Now let's look at what he tried to deliver in verses 12. "Those who want to impress people
by means of the flesh are trying to compel you to be circumcised. The only reason they
do this is to avoid being persecuted for the cross of Christ." Verses 13. "Not even those
who are circumcised keep the law, yet they want you to be circumcised that they may boast
about your circumcision in the flesh." In verse 12, there are some people who are claiming
to be following Jesus, and they're trying to convince the Gentile Christians to have
a cut in their flesh, that is circumcision. And they also, this false teacher, want these
Gentiles to follow the law of Moses. And the reason behind that is that they do not want
a life to be difficult, and they want to avoid being persecuted.
You see, these false teachers, they were looking at these uncircumcised Gentiles as deficient
and unworthy, unless they circumcised. They definitely have brought a division to the
church instead of unity. And of course, discipleship of these false teachers is just a show, is
a hypocritical faith. I don't know if sometimes we may do that too in the church. We may see
other believers who look or act differently than us. We have a tendency to judge, to judge
them based on the external factors, when in reality, Jesus is enough, and there's no favoritism
with God. You see, this new movement of Christians,
claiming that Jesus is the long-awaited Christ, the Messiah, is troubling these Jewish leaders.
And now the movement is spreading to the Gentiles. Non-Christian Jews want to stop it, to snuff
it out. They begin persecuting Christians, and in order to avoid this persecution, these
prideful false teachers, they are putting a show to appease non-Christian Jews by boasting
to them that, "Hey, look, these Gentile converts to Christ, they are coming under the Jewish
law." And the motive is winning more converts to their cause to make themselves look good,
feel important, and look righteousness. And unfortunately, they themselves cannot keep
the law of Moses, which consists of a lot of rituals, restrictions, and prohibitions.
And just kind of like the Pharisees, Jesus said, "They preach, but they do not practice."
But also, these false teachers, they cannot keep the law of Christ, which is full of grace
and the love of God. Paul here is trying to say, "Let's no boast in the flesh or in the
outward appearance." When we stand before God, nothing apart from Jesus matters. Jesus
is the one who turns our boasting upside down. Our rank, our status, our money, our achievements
don't do anything for us. So Paul does boast, and he boasts in the cross. In verses 14,
he said, "May I never boast except in the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through which
the world has been crucified to me, and not I to the world." Paul has repeatedly emphasized
the work of Christ upon the cross, and the grace of God is sufficient. Circumstances,
crucial diets, feasts, rituals, et cetera, et cetera, they don't have the power to transform
lives. And the ground of acceptance is Jesus, and depend on anything else is deadly. Honestly,
the cross is a real challenge for those who want to maintain their pride. It's a problem
for those who have a desire for others to praise them and to see them successful. I
know in that in some churches, many believers often know the amount of time and offerings
of other believers, and the donation information will always be printed out weekly to show
everybody. And as a result, some believers may show extra respect and care for those
who donate more, and while others who donate less are often neglected. A pastor friend
told me before in his church, he must reach a certain number of people in his group in
order to receive a year-end bonus, and depending on how well he reaches the target, the bonus
he received very likely is higher than his monthly pay. I can go on and on and tell you
all kinds of stories, but there's no great mystery about the motives behind all this
is to look good and show off. They actually do not understand the meaning of the true
gospel. Actually, the cross is pretty embarrassing. It wasn't the religious symbol as it is today.
Remember, the cross was the method of execution for serious crimes committed and for those
against the Roman Empire. But how is Paul boasting in something so shameful like the
cross of Jesus? As for Paul, and for all of us, the cross is not something to be ashamed
of, for as he wrote to the church at Rome, it is the power of God for salvation. Our
boasting, our identity, our trust should ultimately come from one place and one place only, and
that is the cross of our Jesus. Here Paul says that the world is dead to him, and that
he is dead to the world. What does it mean for the world to be crucified to him? If the
world is dead to you, then it does not have the power over you. The world is care, desires,
and values have no sway in your life. The world is dead to you. The world does not influence
you. It does not move you. And Paul is saying that all those things are dead to him, and
the world is crucified to him, and that this is what he's proud of. You see, the cross
is the very heart of our faith. For our endless sinful rebellion in our flesh, we are the
ones who deserve to spill our own blood. But God loves us so much, took on the human flesh
and blood to die for us. God's will is that the cross be always be magnified, and that
Jesus Christ, his crucifixion, is always be our praise and our boast. And Jesus get the
glory and the honor for every good thing in our lives, and every bad thing that God causes
to turn for good. Amen. So now if Gentiles don't need to put an effort to do the circumcision,
wow, they should be able to win God's favor, right? No. Let's read verses 15. "Neither
circumcision nor uncircumcision means anything. What counts is the new creation." Now that's
the contrast between circumcision and new creation. It doesn't matter if they're circumcised
or not. And it doesn't matter if take that step or not. For they cannot win God's love
and acceptance. So church, what counts? What is the most important then? What matters is
that as Christians, we have been transformed on the inside and the circumcision of the
heart. And that is by God's divine power that launches us to be a new creation. Just as
Christ was crucified and raised. So Paul's old self, your old self, and my old self was
crucified with Christ by faith. And we too have been raised to a new life. We now live
a new heart. We are new creatures indwelled by the Holy Spirit. And even as we continue
to battle and make headway against our remaining sin, the cross is the source of transformation
that Paul calls a new creation. But what is a new creation anyway? As Christians, we are
born again. The world is no longer our treasure or source of satisfaction. This new birth
is not physical, but spiritual. Being born again to Jesus, the power of the world has
been broken over us. We have been translated from darkness into the light. Jesus becomes
our Lord. His grace is the undeserved favor of God that gives us the new life. And it
also provides us a new desire and power to live in a way that we can please God. Our
Lord, he concerns with our motives, our attitudes, our desires, behind our actions, not just
our outward behavior. This new, lifelong, ongoing spiritual transformation journey
requires cooperation on our part with what the Holy Spirit means to do in us. It shifts
us from gratifying desires of the flesh to being led by the Spirit and bearing the fruit
of the Spirit. And this is our calling, church. This is our purpose, to live a genuine, Spirit-empowered,
obedience life in Jesus. We represent him everywhere and every time. And that we need
to show gentleness, grace, mercy, and love to others. And in this journey, it is not
a one-time experience. This is a lifelong journey, leads to a greater intimacy with
God and Christ-likeness. And there's a blessing of peace and mercy, as Galatians 6, 16 said,
all who follow this rule. What rule? This rule of being justified by faith in Christ
and not works of law. And all who own God's work and power in making them new creatures.
We are God's true people. And Paul calls them the Israel of God. And this is the church,
the true Israel. And the reality of being new creation in Jesus is personal and individual,
as well as corporate. Not only did Jesus very personally love you and die for you and give
himself for you and at the cross, but he love us. He love you and he love me. And this is
his church. And he make us a people together as family in him. And the new creation is
a wondrous thing, formed in the mind of God and created in his power and for his glory.
This is in line of our church, divine's vision for growing big people. Growing big people
means to become more like Jesus. Growing big people is not something just for only the
high status or mature Christians. It's God's heart for every single us. Every single us.
No matter you are mature or you're new to the Christ. This is for all of us. And this
is what we discover and see in the letter of Galatians. That is God's heart to mature
us and be a blessings to many others and to build them up and to speak life to them.
And finally, we come to the end of Galatians. And one of the last things Paul writes to
is in his own hand, he said, "I bear on my body the marks of Jesus." In verses 17. These
marks in Greek means stigmata. It means the signs of ownership, especially were branded
on slaves and cattle. Paul referred to the scars on his body, which were caused by the
persecution for Jesus. And because they demonstrate that he was a slave of Jesus and not people
pleaser. Like Jesus, Paul also had the scars. The scars which point not to his own work,
but to Jesus' work. The marks of Jesus that he carries in his own body. As in 2 Corinthians
chapter 11, verses 23 to 27, Paul has mentioned some of what he suffered for the sake of Christ
in prison, in shipwreck, in danger of many, many situations and kindness, near death beatings
and also being stoned by many others. He put a final period in place with his own life,
with what he has been willing to suffer in order to live for Jesus and preach the gospel.
And amazingly, he lived what he preached at a great cost. I personally have a story to
tell you about the cost. About 23 years ago, I was called by God and came back to Hong
Kong from America as missionary. That was 2001. Our family of four, my husband and I
and my two children at that time is six and two years old. We respond to God's call. We
sold everything. The only thing we have is four suitcases and flew back to Hong Kong
to commit ourselves to serve the law. As the funds we brought back to Hong Kong were reducing,
my husband gave up the ministry and found a job teaching at a kindergarten. I continue
to take care of the family and volunteer regularly at the local Christian drug rehab center and
also minister in different house churches in the mainland China.
Unfortunately, in 2003, my husband was dissatisfied with the life in Hong Kong and have an affair
with a lady. He refused to turn around. He took advantage when I spent two nights at
the Macau Women's Drug Rehab Center and without saying a word, he stole everything from me.
My passport, my credit cards and all my money. And he took our two children who were only
eight and four years old at that time. He left, they left Hong Kong and flew back to
the United States. When I returned home from Macau, I saw the empty house and I was devastated.
My whole world was collapsed and I shattered into pieces.
Feeling extremely sad, lost and confused, I continue to sought the law with fasting
and prayers. And finally, I decide to stay in Hong Kong to continue fulfilling the calling
of God. With much God's grace and strength, he sustains me. Though my ex-husband lied
and twist the fact when he returned to America, I agreed to his request for a divorce and
gave up the custody of our children. God spoke and gave me the promise that my two children
would return to Hong Kong in the future. And he asked me to stick to his call without fear
or doubt. And afterwards, I enrolled and studied in a theological seminary. And I also
continued the ministry in China and opened my residence to help people in need.
Yes, God has promised. But when? I'm sure many of you will have the same experience
that waiting for God is not an easy task. I missed my children so much I cried every
day until all tears dried. God has promised, but it didn't mean it would happen right
away. Then suddenly, one day, God's promise and mercy came true in the summer of 2006.
My ex-husband gave up the children. And at that time, the children aged seven and eleven,
who had been separated from their mother for three years, returned to my arms. It felt
like I had been waiting for a lifetime. And now they are grown-up adults staying in Australia.
Church, yes, there's a price to pay when you follow Jesus. The cross and the cost.
In these 23 years of ministry, I can tell you, battles are never-ending. However, the
Christ in me always helped me to embrace the process and overcome. I have fought the good
fight, yet the race is not finished. And there's always glory in suffering. We will find spiritual
growth, hope, and deeper experience of God's presence, even in the midst of difficulties
and pains in our life. These false teachers, under pressure, they make marks on other people's
flesh and boast in a headcount of circumcision. Marks have been made in Paul's flesh as he
has defended the truth of the gospel. Embraced by faith alone, we are a new creation, and
it is enough to keep us right with God. Our precious brothers and sisters, what really
counts in your life? We're going to have personal prayer at your
seats. I invite you to pray and talk to Jesus, and he is here to listen. What are you looking
for in this world? The temporary happiness that quickly vanishes as soon as it is experienced,
leaving us empty and looking for more to keep us alive. What is the world given to you?
Is it the confusion, the anxiety, the suffering, grief, or even hatred that keep us hooked?
It is the cross that free us from all the worries of this world, and it is supposed
to be a new life where this world no longer has its hooks in us.
Church, does your life look like Jesus? Are you willing to live a life which is guided
and obeyed the Holy Spirit to bear fruit? God is here to transform you and help you
through the process. He sustains your life, and you can trust him. He is the one true
God. This is a very precious moment you have for
Jesus, and he is waiting here to listen to you and talk to you. And when you finish your
prayer, and when you are ready, please come to the front and receive your bread and cup
and to have communion with our precious God Almighty.
[MUSIC PLAYING]