- Amen, hey church, it's such a privilege to be with you
as it is every week and just to be a part
of what God is doing amongst us.
And I just wanna echo Carla's words from earlier.
You know, it's been a really difficult week in Hong Kong.
It's impacted all of us in different ways.
And we're standing with you, we're praying for you.
We wanna walk together in this season and in this hour.
And I do hope that you know that amongst the brothers
and sisters of faith, you have a community
that's cheering you on, no one is alone, no one is isolated.
We're all part of one family together.
And that's the joy of being able to do this together.
To listen to God's word, to encourage each other
and to see what God's gonna do amongst us.
And I'm really excited about that today.
I wanna tell you a little bit as I start
about my experiences as a young Christian.
You know, for a number of years
when I first became a Christian,
I was really skeptical about the more charismatic
expressions of the Christian faith.
In particular, I was very skeptical about speaking in tongues.
I actually came to faith
when I was studying philosophy at university.
And I was somebody who prided themselves
on rational thinking.
I saw the world actually through the lens,
through the framework of rationality
that actually debate and understanding
and rational things were important and true.
And that in order to really understand things,
we needed to see the facts.
We needed to understand things
with our rational minds and brains.
So therefore, as a younger person,
I was pretty sceptical of emotional people,
particularly sceptical of emotional people at church.
I thought emotional people at church
were just kind of going through the motions
or just kind of being a bit strange.
And that actually the only way that we truly come
to understand the power of God is through our minds,
through how we think.
And that theology and rationality
was the most important thing.
This was actually a bit of a problem for me
when I graduated university,
came back to Hong Kong and joined the Vine.
'Cause the Vine, as you know, is a charismatic church.
But back in those days, I would say on Sundays,
our charismatic expression was even more than it is today.
It was quite regular back in those days
that during worship,
somebody might get slain in the spirit.
That's falling down on the ground
through the power of God's spirit.
A lot of people would pray out loud
or sing out loud in tongues.
I remember this one particular week,
and this is etched in my memory forever.
This one particular week, this older lady in our church,
she crowed like a rooster for five minutes during worship.
Everybody else was completely uncomfortable
with the reality that this lady, bless her,
was crowing like a rooster.
And so we had some pretty strange things taking place.
And I have to say, I was very uncomfortable with it all.
It didn't sit well with me.
I believe that God didn't bring chaos into the church,
that the church was a place of safety,
of comfort, of security,
that we came to church to feel like that.
And that in those moments in worship,
I wasn't comfortable for me.
And I felt like God wouldn't be a part of something
that was chaotic like it was.
Well, there was this one particular Sunday
where things were particularly frustrating and bad.
On this particular Sunday, actually,
I was standing right behind in the row,
right behind of that old lady who had crowed like the rooster
just a few weeks before.
And I'm standing right behind her and worship is starting.
And I can tell she's getting set to do something,
some sort of animal noise
I knew was gonna come out of this woman.
She started to shake back and forth.
She started to kind of do this.
And I was just preparing myself
for the eruption that was to come.
And I was kind of frustrated by it all,
if I'm honest with you.
So I just sort of decided I was gonna close my eyes
and just try to block everything else out
and just try to connect with God.
So as I closed my eyes,
I received what I can only describe to you as a vision.
It was a vision because even though my eyes were closed,
I could see with 100% clarity a picture.
And in this picture, it was like a movie.
And it was like I was suddenly in this movie set.
And the set was like this dusty street
with lots of little narrow alleyways
and lots of homes side by side,
small white houses with flat roofs.
And I could see these things just very clearly.
And I could almost walk amongst those streets.
And actually the houses reminded me
of the kind of houses that I was seeing
in the little pencil drawings
that were found in my Bible in those days.
I knew that this was Israel,
that I was seeing some street,
perhaps in the old city of Jerusalem.
And as I'm looking at this,
I noticed that on every doorframe of every building,
there is Hebrew words,
Hebrew script written over them.
Now, this was years before I went to Bible school.
And as I looked at the doorframes,
I could see the Hebrew and immediately I could read it
just as if it was English.
I knew exactly what it was saying.
The words over every house was this,
it's time to come home again.
It's time to come home again,
written over every single doorframe of every single home.
And I could read it just like I say,
just like it was English,
like it was my own language.
And as I'm reading the Hebrew,
knowing exactly what it means, not only that,
but also knowing how to pronounce the word,
if I was gonna say it.
This all happened like just immediately.
I also found in me the Spirit of God
just working towards me a place of peace and shalom,
like this place of being right where I needed to be
with God in that moment.
And I knew that the words over those homes
was for that old lady standing in front of me.
So I, without really perhaps even thinking about it,
I leaned forward, I put my hands on her shoulders
and I start to get this,
I start to sing those Hebrew words over her
in Hebrew, not in English, okay?
I start to sing Hebrew.
Now that's amazing for two things.
Number one, I don't speak Hebrew, let alone sing it.
But number two, if you know me,
if you know me, you know that I don't sing,
that I do not have a good singing voice.
So I'm there singing my heart out in Hebrew,
a language that up into that moment,
I did not know, didn't understand,
but knew exactly what I was singing over her
in the perfect pronunciation.
She starts weeping, like deep weeping,
like just weeping and weeping and weeping.
And I keep singing and singing those words.
It's time to come home again.
It's time to come home again in Hebrew over her.
Well, a couple of days later, she reached out to me
and she let me know what was going on.
She had visited Israel many, many times in her life,
but she had stopped going for a bunch of different reasons.
And she didn't feel like she wanted to go there anymore,
but she really deeply missed being amongst the Jewish people,
even though she herself was not Jewish.
And as I was singing over her in that church service,
she knew that God was saying those exact words to her.
She understood Hebrew.
She knew what I was singing over her
was it's time to come home again.
Here's an interesting thing.
There's me, sceptical,
totally driven by rationality in those days,
kind of feeling awkward
when the Holy Spirit would move upon people.
And God gives me a vision and I step out in faith
and everything in me changes.
From that moment onwards,
I've had a really interesting relationship
with the Holy Spirit.
Things have shifted and changed in me.
And while I haven't had visions like that very often
throughout my Christian life,
that moment was a changing moment.
It was like the breaking down of a barrier
that I had put in my mind
to what the Holy Spirit actually wanted to do.
And I realised that so often my customs, my traditions,
the things that I am comfortable with
can become a barrier to the thing
that the Holy Spirit might actually want to do.
As we enter into this final week
of our Dreaming Again series,
I wanna speak a word today
that I believe is important for all of us.
I think there's a need for all of us
to receive a fresh revelation from God.
The kind of fresh revelation
that actually shakes and disrupts and breaks down
some of those unhealthy barriers,
unhealthy customs and traditions
that we can sometimes hold onto
even above what God might wanna do amongst us.
Now, don't get me wrong.
Having some customs, having traditions is fine.
Okay, here at the Vine, we have a theology,
a framework of theology, a statement of beliefs.
You can find it on our website that we believe passionately.
But here's the reality that I've come to see
in my Christian life and experience.
And perhaps you've seen this too,
is that so often we can embed ourselves,
so often we can embed ourselves
in the kind of thinking about our church practices,
our customs and traditions that we feel comfortable with,
that those things actually begin to define
how we think about God.
And so actually it is our customs and traditions
and practices that become to shape our theology.
And when that happens, we're in danger, I think,
of putting our personal preferences over God's truth.
And when that takes place,
I think God so often must step in with a fresh revelation
because it will take, like it did for me on that day,
a profound move of the Holy Spirit to shake us out
of some of the entrenched thinking that we can find
through our personal preferences,
our comforts and our securities.
You see, it's interesting
because Jesus understood this deeply
when he began his own ministry here on earth.
He knew that he was bringing a message
of the kingdom of God,
a message that was gonna come and shake things up.
He also understood that that message
was not gonna be very easily received
by those that were entrenched
in Judaic thinking at the time.
In fact, right at the start of his ministry,
Mark records for us a teaching Jesus brings the crowds.
I wanna read this to you from Mark chapter two,
starting in verse 22.
He says this, "No one pours new wine into old wineskins.
If he does, the wine will burst the skins
and both the wine and the wineskins will be ruined.
No, he pours new wine into new wineskins."
I think so often the reality is this,
that when it comes to our idea of dreaming,
God gives us these dreams and they're amazing.
And it's like this new wine is being poured into us.
But here's the reality.
So often we take the new wine of God
and we try to fit it into the old wineskins
of our traditions and customs.
When actually what we need is a new wineskin
that is able to retain the new wine that God is giving us.
See, the reality is this,
sometimes to move forward in our dreams
that God has given us will require
a new fresh way of thinking,
a fresh way of believing that is only possible in us
through a profound movement of the Spirit of God.
That's what we need sometimes,
to shake us out of how we always have thought,
how we always have tried to put God into a little box
when God actually wants to break forward.
We put that little metal gate in front of the fire
so we protect ourselves
'cause we're happy with the God that we know
rather than the God that actually wants to show up.
The one who might actually want to shake us up.
The one that we actually need to come to set us on fire.
Again, I feel like for some of you watching this,
this is gonna be a word for you in season.
And here's the reason.
It's because God has given you new dreams.
He has, if you will, poured out his new wine,
but you've been frustrated
because you've been trying to fit that new wine
into the old wineskin
of what you're comfortable with in your life right now.
And while this might not be always easy to hear
when God brings his new wine,
it's 'cause he wants to put it in a new wineskin.
That means some things might need to change.
That means we might need to be open to fresh revelation,
fresh way of thinking, fresh way of understanding,
fresh way of actually practising our belief and our faith.
Perhaps even, dare I say, fresh theology,
fresh ways of truly understanding who God is amongst us.
I wanna challenge us with this idea
of what it is to embrace fresh revelation today
by taking us to a passage from the early church.
It's a passage actually where the early church
has this dramatic encounter with God
that procures and creates a new wineskin in the church.
That is the very reason why,
if you're watching this right now and you're a believer,
that you've become a Christian.
It's because of what God does in this particular story
I wanna take you to.
It's from Acts chapter 10,
and I'm gonna start reading in verse one.
I hope you're with me.
I hope you're awake.
I believe honestly that God's got some fresh revelation
for you today.
And I wanna pray actually just before I open the Word.
I wasn't planning to do this,
but I feel like this is important just to break off
any distraction that there might be out there.
Let me pray for this.
Father, as we open your Word, we do so with hunger.
We do so Lord willing to shake off our traditions,
to shake off even our religion,
if it means that we've missed you along the way.
And Father, we wanna ask for a fresh revelation, Lord,
of your power, of your spirit, of your love, of your Word.
And I pray you would do this amongst us
in such a beautiful way today.
Let me pray this in Jesus' name.
Everyone says.
- Amen. - Amen.
All right, I wanna read to you from Acts chapter 10,
starting in verse one.
At Caesarea, there was a man named Cornelius,
a centurion in what was known as the Italian Regiment.
He and all his family were devout and God-fearing.
He gave generously to those in need
and prayed to God regularly.
One day at about three in the afternoon, he had a vision.
He distinctly saw an angel of God
who came to him and said, "Cornelius."
Cornelius stared at him in fear.
"What is it, Lord?" he said.
The angel answered, "Your prayers
and the gifts of the poor
have come as a memorial offering before God.
Now send men to Joppa to bring back a man named Simon,
who is called Peter.
He is staying with Simon the Tanner,
whose house is by the sea."
When the angel who spoke to him had gone,
Cornelius called two of his servants
and a devout soldier who was one of his attendants.
He told them everything that had happened
and he sent them to Joppa.
Luke starts the story by introducing us
to this main character in the story, Cornelius.
He tells us three quick things.
He's a Gentile, he's a centurion.
In other words, he's a Roman soldier
that has a hundred soldiers under his command.
And most importantly, he says he's devout and God-fearing.
This was somewhat common in the times
that Gentiles might have become aligned
to the Jewish way of thinking,
and even perhaps aligned to the worship of the Jewish God.
A God-fearer was a Gentile
who took on the beliefs of the Jewish faith.
Not perhaps in every way in their life,
but perhaps in an openness, as we hear in this story,
to give money to the poor
or to pray to this God from time to time.
And here we have a picture of Cornelius
praying to the Jewish God,
and God shows up and gives him a new dream.
He actually says to him,
"Okay, I want you to go to Joppa.
I want you to get this apostle, Peter, who's a Jew.
I want you to invite this Jewish man to come into your home."
Now on paper, that doesn't seem like a big deal to you and I,
but in the first century, that's completely revolutionary.
We need to understand two quick things in context here.
The first is this, that actually it was illegal.
It wasn't right in Jewish thinking for a Jewish person
to go into the home and share a meal
with a Gentile in those days.
That was outlawed in the rabbinic law.
It's really important that you know
that there were two types of law.
There was rabbinic law and Torah law.
Torah law was the law that was found
in the first five books of the Bible,
the law that came from God's word himself.
But there was also rabbinical law.
Rabbinical law was the law that had grown up
through the rabbis over the years
as they sought to interpret God's word.
And rabbinical law, not Torah law,
had outruled the idea that a Jewish person
could go into a Gentile's home for a meal.
Now here's the reason why.
It's because in Jewish thinking,
there was things that were seen as both unclean and impure.
Unclean and impure.
An unclean thing was a Gentile,
the Gentiles by their very existence,
being foreign, being ethnically other from the Jewish people,
not under that Jewish covenant,
not part of the chosen generation.
They were seen as unclean in God's eyes.
And if a Jewish person associated
with someone who is unclean,
while the Jewish person could not become unclean themselves
'cause they're under the new covenant,
they could become impure,
tainted by the unclean person that they were with.
Think about this in COVID terms.
This is like a Jewish person becomes a close contact
with a Gentile, they have to go in quarantine
before they're allowed to be released
back into the Jewish community.
You following with me?
That was what was happening here.
So when God says to Cornelius,
"Invite this Jewish man to your house,"
he's thinking to himself, "Hang on a sec.
God is asking me to do something
that's against the rabbinical law.
And if I invite this Peter over and he comes,
he'll become impure."
Like this doesn't make any sense.
This is God bringing fresh revelation
to disrupt the rabbinical law,
the customs and traditions that had gotten in the way
of what he wanted to do.
Cornelius as a God-fearing devout man says,
"All right, Lord, if this is what you're doing,
if this is what you're gonna say, I will trust you.
I'll go out and I'll invite this Peter to come."
Let's see what happens next.
Verse nine, "About noon the following day,
as they were on their journey and approaching the city,
Peter went up onto the roof to pray.
He became hungry and wanted something to eat.
And while the meal was being prepared,
he fell into a trance, a vision, if you will, a dream.
He saw heaven open and something like a large sheet
containing was being let down to earth on its four corners.
It contained all kinds of four-footed animals,
as well as reptiles of the earth and birds of the air.
Then a voice told him this, 'Get up, Peter, kill and eat.'
'Surely not, Lord,' Peter replied.
I have never eaten anything," notice this,
"that is impure or unclean."
The voice spoke to him a second time,
"Do not call anything impure that God has made clean."
This happened three times.
And immediately the sheet was taken back to heaven.
Just like for Cornelius, now for Peter.
Peter receives a similar vision.
He's up praying and a vision comes.
And in that vision, the sheet's let down.
And it's really important, it says here
that he saw all kinds of four-footed animals together.
Now this is really important because Peter's hungry
and he sees all these animals in front of him in this dream.
And he sees, notice, four-footed animals all together.
Now in Jewish dietary laws,
there were animals that were deemed clean and unclean.
Clean to eat and unclean not to eat.
Unclean animals were things like pigs and horses.
Clean animals were things like cows and chickens.
You can eat those, but you can't eat what's unclean.
However, if the clean animals,
like the cows and the chickens,
come into close proximity with the unclean pigs and such,
then they became impure and also could not be eaten,
even though they were deemed clean to begin with.
Are you following with me?
All right, so what that means is this.
When Peter's seeing all these animals on this sheet,
even though some are theoretically clean,
because they're mingling with those that are unclean,
they've become impure and he can't eat any of them.
He's hungry, staring at all these things,
and he's realising he's not allowed
to eat any of them at all.
So when God says, "Get up, Peter, kill and eat,"
he is totally taken back.
This goes against everything he understands
about the law of God.
This goes against everything he would understand
that God would ever tell him to do.
He can't get his head around the idea
that God would want him to go and kill and eat something
that either is unclean or is impure,
which is why he says to God, "Surely not, Lord.
I have never eaten anything that is unclean or impure."
I love this.
He says, "Surely not, Lord."
In other words, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, no, Lord.
You can't be asking me to do that.
You can't, because that's not of you.
That's surely not of your character.
That's not the box that I've got you in.
That doesn't fit right.
I don't want that.
Surely not, Lord.
I think the reality is this.
All of us have a tendency to say, "Surely not, Lord."
When God so often moves in a fresh revelation,
when he brings a word to us,
it's so perhaps different from what we thought
our initial reaction surely is, "Surely not, Lord."
Particularly when those things
go against our personal preferences,
the things that we've made,
our customs and our traditions and the ways.
See, here's the reality.
There is a comfort, isn't there,
to our customs and traditions.
We like a no surprises kind of God,
one who is stable and understandable,
one who is relational, who is reasonable, predictable.
That's the kind of God that we like.
We like a religion that's nicely tied up
with a sweet little bow
that helps us to understand everything.
We like to have answers, don't we?
We don't like uncertainty.
We like certainty.
I've noticed that as I've gotten older in life,
I want stability and certainty more than ever before.
I know that I can find myself
rooted in my personal preferences
as I get older more and more.
And the reality is this,
that so often when we are entrenched
in those customs and traditions,
when we're seeking a God that we fully understand,
where we try to get out mystery,
where we try to get away doubt,
when we try to run away from the things
that might confuse us about God
and try to put God in a little box
that we can tie with a bow and fully understand,
when that happens, here's the reality,
so often we find ourselves acting more from a place of law
than a place of grace.
You need to follow with this, church,
'cause this is really important.
So often we find ourselves in a place of law
more than a place of grace
because law is comfortable.
Law creates boundaries.
Law gives us safety and security.
Grace is risky.
Grace shunts us out of the things that are comfortable
and puts us in a place of higher risk,
of unpredictability, of at times uncertainty.
And we need to realize that so often
we find ourselves like that.
And here's the reality,
so often those of us who are comfortable in man's laws
are really uncomfortable in God's grace.
I'm gonna say that again, church,
'cause I think that's super important right now.
So often those of us who are comfortable with man's laws
really struggle with God's grace.
We struggle because God's grace
turns some of those things outside of what we're expecting,
rips open our customs and our beliefs,
rips open the things that we have created
to help us to feel comfortable and safe and secure.
God's grace is risky by its very definition.
We're like the elder son
in the parable of the prodigal son
who can't understand that our father would reach out
and bless that person.
Oh God, I don't understand why you would bless,
haven't you seen their lifestyle?
Haven't you seen how they live?
Haven't you seen the mistakes they've made?
Haven't you seen the way they're treating their spouse?
Haven't you seen all of this stuff
that's going on in their lives?
How could you bless them
in the same way that you're blessed to be?
Surely not, Lord.
When we find ourselves entrenched this way,
we really struggle with the reality
that God's grace is here.
And I want you to know this,
so often Christians are so judgmental towards one another.
We are some of the worst when it comes
to judging one another,
to judging our faith based on our actions,
judging our churches based on their expressions,
judging theology based on denominations,
judging who we think should be in
and who we think should be out.
And this is something that God wants to disrupt in us
in this time, I believe.
He wants unity across the brokenness more than ever before.
And that will take some fresh revelation for us.
'Cause the sad truth is this,
that so many Christians who have been saved through grace
end up becoming judgmental through the law.
So often that takes place for us.
So often that happens.
And we need to be shaken where some of our customs
and traditions have put our personal preferences
over God's truth and His word.
And this is not just for the church.
This is for our city, for our society as well.
You know, we cry out,
surely not, Lord, in society often all the times.
And we put barriers up between those
that we think are worth it
and those that we don't think are worth it.
And we can see things like racism and in classism
and kind of tribalism at work and around us all the time.
And we can see even our city and our society say things like,
well, that person's not quite as valuable as that person.
And our laws and the way we treat one another
and the way that things happen
can actually put ethnic groups amongst each other,
can actually put ethnic minorities
against those that might be in a majority.
And that some get privileged and some don't.
And we're aware that this happens
even here in our beloved city of Hong Kong.
I think we're honest,
some of the stuff we've seen in the news this week
about how some of our Filipino sisters in this city
have been handled is disgraceful.
We should call out the reality
when these things take place.
I experienced this personally in my life
just a few weeks ago.
My wife and I, along with our helper, Lizelle,
wanted to get our booster for the vaccine.
We'd already been double-dosed
and we wanted to get our booster now.
And so I jumped on the website
to be able to sign the three of us up to get boosted.
And the cases were increasing here in Hong Kong.
And so we wanted to get it done sooner than later.
And here's what happened.
As I filled in the forms,
I realized that for my wife and I,
I was able to book a time
that was just two days after the day that I was booking.
But for my helper,
I wasn't able to book her a time for three weeks.
Why?
Simply because she held a different ID card
than what I held.
Simply because helpers
were not allowed to get vaccinated first.
I thought that was disgraceful.
And the reality is that so often in a crisis,
it reveals where our true values are.
So often crisis can show us what's actually inside of us.
And we need a fresh revelation, not just in the church,
but in our city and in society as well,
that shakes us out of some of these racist,
some of these tribalistic, classist impressions that we have.
And we need to be grounded again in the word of God.
New wine into new wineskins.
You still with me, everyone?
Still following with this?
Now, this is exactly what Peter needed.
And that was exactly what Peter received.
So much so that I wanna show you
what he says here in verse 23.
He says it this way.
He says, "Then Peter invited the three men
that had been sent by Cornelius
into his house to be his guests."
That sounds again like a very normal thing.
That is revolutionary.
Peter is taking three Gentiles
into his house to be his guests.
Why?
Because through the dream he had received,
he now has a fresh revelation about the heart of God.
He knows now that God is not seeing Gentiles
as unclean anymore.
He understands that if he's in relationship with Gentiles,
if he's sharing food and fellowship with them,
he's not gonna be seen as impure anymore
'cause we should not call unclean or impure
the things that God has called clean and pure.
And so he invites them into his house.
And in fact, later on,
when he shows up at Cornelius' house,
he explains why he has done that.
Let me read this to you from verse 28.
He says this.
"He said to them, 'You are well aware
that it is against our law for a Jew
to associate with a Gentile or visit him.
But God has shown me that I should not call
any man impure or unclean.'"
I love this.
He says, "You know that it is our law."
Notice he doesn't say God's law.
He says, "Our law, our rabbinical traditions,
our customs and our traditions
has created a barrier ethnically between the ethnic other.
And it is not right.
And God has broken in by the power of his spirit
to help me to understand that that isn't right.
And I now know that I shouldn't call anybody unclean
or impure that God sees value in, that God loves,
that God has created in his image."
This is Peter beginning to totally cross over
to the other side.
This is completely new thinking for him.
So much so that he can sit there in this room
and preach the gospel to these people.
And so much so that this happens.
Have a look in verse 44 and 46.
"While Peter was still speaking these words,
the Holy Spirit came on all who heard his message.
The circumcised believers who had come with Peter
were astonished that the gift of the Holy Spirit
had been poured out even on the Gentiles."
I love that.
"Even on the Gentiles, even on those unclean ones,
even on those ones that we had rejected,
even on the ethnically other,
the ones that we thought were disgusting in God's eyes,
God's spirit has poured out even on them.
For they heard them speaking in tongues and praising God."
This dramatically changes everything.
God does something in their midst
that he had never done before.
Peter sees the Holy Spirit come upon those
that up to that point he had seen as unclean.
This is Peter going from the elder brother to the father,
realizing now that he is the one
that should throw a party for everyone
because God's grace has broken over man's laws.
That God's grace is always greater
than our customs and traditions.
That God's law has come
and he opens his heart to a fresh way of thinking.
A fresh way of thinking, my friends,
that completely transforms the church.
In fact, this creates a new wine skin for the church.
And Peter is able to connect vision to mission.
And from this point, they can take up Jesus' words
that says, "Take the gospel, not just to Jerusalem,
but to Judea and Samaria and the ends of the earth."
That this was Genesis 12,
the calling of Abraham come to its fruition.
The idea that, "Oh, look up into the skies
and all of these people, the Jewish people,
will be a blessing to every nation."
This is the moment where Peter and the early church
finally understood what was on God's heart
from right at the beginning of all time,
that the Gentiles, anyone, you and me,
are able to receive the power of the Holy Spirit
for salvation and life.
If you're watching this right now,
you're not Jewish and you believe in Jesus.
That's because of this moment right here.
This moment where the new wine of God's power pours out
and the church decides to build a new wine skin.
Now, it wasn't easy for them.
In fact, they would have a lot of arguments about this.
You can read later in Acts 14 and 15
about the Jerusalem council and how they wrestled
with this new theology,
with this new reality of the presence of God
poured out on people that they didn't think
the presence of God should pour out on.
It wasn't an easy transition for them,
but that transition certainly took place.
And I want you to see why that transition took place.
Notice this, track with this.
See, God gives a dream to two people
that causes a dramatic shift in their thinking
that breaks down the dividing walls between them
through an outpouring of the Holy Spirit
that changes all history.
Isn't that amazing, church?
A dream comes, the dream changes their thinking.
The change in their thinking breaks down the walls,
the dividing walls between them,
and that results in the spirit of God
being unleashed on earth like never before.
And the question we've got to ask ourselves
when we read a passage like this is simply this,
what dividing walls are there still existing in us today?
What dividing walls are present for us
that the Holy Spirit right here in Hong Kong
might by His power want to bring some new dreams,
some new wine for the old wineskin,
new wine that gets placed in a new church,
a new people, a new people that are open
to hearing God's new word who are saying,
"This is the way we now need to live."
That these dividing walls,
the other that we were once afraid of,
we're gonna break down those walls
because the spirit of God brings unity.
Where are our dividing walls in Hong Kong right now?
I wonder if there's a future where yellow and blue
could find unity through the spirit of God.
I wonder if there's a future where Hong Kong people
and mainland Chinese might find unity
through the spirit of God.
I wonder if there's a future here
where the ethnic minority in our cities
might be seen with the same value as everybody else.
I wonder if new wine is being poured into new wineskins.
How can we respond with this fresh revelation?
How can we receive it?
'Cause if you're listening to this right now
and you're anything like me, I'd be like,
"Well, this sounds really good.
I wanna have a Peter moment."
Or maybe I wanna have a moment like Andrew did
and got that vision and was able to speak in Hebrew.
Maybe some of you are younger here,
got a Spanish test coming up
and you're praying for that dream right now.
I'm with you.
Okay, how do we position ourselves
to receive this from God?
Well, I think we see three very quick practical things
in the passages that we've just been reading today.
The first one is this.
We have to position ourselves for revelation.
Position ourselves for that revelation.
Notice in both Cornelius and in Peter,
they were both going about their usual activity
and habit of praying.
And in that moment of prayer,
God is able to break in and bring his revelation.
Notice that not all customs and traditions are bad, right?
There are many good and healthy ones.
And our regular practice of praying,
our regular practice of coming before God
and relationship with him is exactly part of that.
Both Cornelius and Peter going about their normal,
everyday committed, habitual relationship
with God in prayer positions themselves
for receiving revelation.
Some of you are wanting revelation for God,
but you're not doing anything practically
to bring it about in your life.
Some of you need to re-engage
in a prayerful relationship with him.
God wants to bring his dreams,
but so often those dreams come when we close our eyes
and position ourselves to hear from him.
So first of all, position yourself for revelation.
Second of all is this, look for confirmation.
Look for confirmation.
It blows my mind that Cornelius, the Gentile,
and Peter, the faithful Jew,
receive the same dream from God.
God is trying to connect the two of them together
by giving them the same dream at the same time.
And both of those dreams disrupt the ways
in which they traditionally thought
to bring them into a new relationship
together with new thinking.
Look for confirmation
when God brings a fresh revelation to you.
Don't just jump out and start acting on it.
Look for the confirmation that God is gonna bring
that that fresh revelation is truly from him.
And so often that confirmation comes,
particularly if it's about repairing any dividing walls,
that confirmation will come
because God will be preparing that other person
to receive also that reconciliation,
that crossing over the divide to them.
And I wanna encourage you to be on the lookout
for that kind of confirmation.
God moves, not just by giving you a dream,
but by preparing the people around you for the shift.
And I believe this is what the Holy Spirit's doing
with the church in Hong Kong right now.
I think he's shifting us.
He's shaking us up.
He's bringing fresh revelation around us all
so that we can begin to truly be the new wineskin
that Hong Kong needs in this hour and this time.
Here's the third and final thing.
Look for the fruit of the Holy Spirit to be present.
We know that we can judge something by its fruit.
And both here, we have Cornelius and Peter
gathered in that room and the Holy Spirit pours out.
And Peter immediately knows,
well, that is the fruit that I need to know
that this is truly a work of God,
that this is truly a move of God,
that it's not just my new thinking,
it's not just my fresh understanding,
but God is truly in this
because I can see the fruit of his Spirit in it.
How do we know that the revelation we received
is fresh from God, that it is truly his,
that it is confirmed by those around us
while we look for the fruit?
Does it bring the fruit of the Spirit in our lives
and in the lives of those around us?
Does it bring more love and joy and peace and patience
and kindness and goodness and faithfulness
and gentleness and self-control?
Because if it does, then we know
that this is God's work amongst us.
We look for the fruit of the Spirit
and that helps us to understand
that the fresh revelation we have
is truly from the source of God himself.
Friends, we need new wine to be poured into new wineskins.
What that means is a number of things for us.
It means that we need to be ready and prepared to change.
It means that we need to be open
to the ways in which we might need to think differently,
to adapt to the times, to let go of some of the things
that we had previously held tightly onto
so that we can grab a hold
of the new thing God is bringing.
It means that we need to be willing
to take a good, hard, honest look
at some of our traditional customs and practices
that we've just always done
that are actually creating a dividing wall
between us and the other, whoever that might be.
It means that we need to ask ourselves
the difficult question of who is the Gentile to us?
Who is the one that we think if we spent time with them,
we would become unclean, we would become impure,
we would be in the wrong?
Who is the other that we are afraid of,
the one that we're not sure about,
the one that we try to avoid?
Who's become the Gentile?
Because perhaps God wants to bring
some fresh revelation to us about them.
One thing we learn from this text above everything else
is that there is no human being in God's eyes
who is unclean and impure,
that there is no one that we should reject,
shun, turn our backs on, walk away from,
that everyone, as it says in this passage,
everyone is treated equitably by God,
that God has created us in His image
and He loves every single one of us.
And I think this passage also does this for us.
It challenges us in this way,
that like Peter, we have to realise
that in order to learn some new habits,
we actually have to, first of all, unlearn some old ones.
And sometimes the unlearning of the old requires repentance,
requires us being honest that we had it wrong,
requires us being honest about the dividing walls
that our personal preferences had created
and around our lives.
It requires us getting on our knees
and saying the rabbinical law, Lord,
I had allowed to stand over the Torah law, Your word,
that my desires became more important to me
than Your true word.
Perhaps as we close this series,
as we think about what it is for us to truly dream again,
as we receive this new wine of God's dreams,
we have to say, Lord, I remove that metal gate
from in front of Your fire.
I don't wanna be protected from the things
that Your Spirit truly wants to do
in and through me right now.
Lord, I wanna be open to the fresh revelation.
Lord, forgive me where I've put some dividing walls down,
where I've made my personal preferences
more important to me than Your truth.
Forgive me, Lord, where I've come to look
at the ethnically other differently,
where I've put more value on myself than I have on them.
Lord, would You come and bring such fresh revelation
that I actually am now thinking
about the kingdom of God differently.
Bring Your Spirit, bring Your power
so we can dream the sort of dreams
and be the kind of church God wants for Hong Kong
in this time and this hour.
Church, it is time for us to dream again.
May His new wine be poured into our new wineskin.
Lord, bring Your fresh revelation for each one of us.
Would you pray with me?
Let's pray together.
Father, we just thank You so much for this truth today,
that Lord, You bring at times a new way of thinking,
a new way of believing that enables us to let go
of some of the things that have created barriers
between us and the fresh thing that You're doing on earth.
Lord, I wanna pray that where this might be a reality
for many of us watching this right now.
Lord, I wanna pray that You would challenge us deeply
to be open, positioned
for Your fresh revelation in this season.
Lord, would You enable us to unlearn some old habits?
Habits that may not be the best
for what it is that You're doing at this time.
Lord, would You give us the courage to embrace grace?
Lord, would Your grace enable us to let go
where we've put our traditions above You?
And Lord, I wanna pray, Father, that Your fire would fall,
that we would let go of the things, Lord.
That actually hold us back,
that the sparks that we've protected ourselves from
that are designed to set fire to our lives, Lord, would come.
Lord, that new wine, Your dreams.
Forgive us, Lord, while we stuff those new wines
and new dreams into the old wineskins
of the way that we've always done things as a church.
Lord, I pray for those that need it,
that Lord, You would completely revolutionise
their thinking about Your Spirit.
That You are good, God.
That You love us so much.
And Lord, if we've ever put You in a box,
or if You're in a box in our lives right now,
Lord, would You break out of the box, Lord?
Lord, we thank You that Peter and Cornelius
were able to allow You to break out of their boxes.
And in them coming together
and the power of the Spirit at work in that moment,
the whole church was changed forever.
Lord, I believe we need another moment like that
in Hong Kong right now.
I believe we need a pouring out of Your Holy Spirit, Lord,
that would shake us out of the boxes
that we put ourselves in,
so that we might be able to truly bring unity,
reconciliation and hope to this place in this time.
So Lord, come now, bring Your new wine
and may it find its fertile soil
in the new wineskins of our heart.
And we thank You for this, in Jesus' Name.
Everyone says, Amen.
[BLANK_AUDIO]