On the very first day of seminary, I met Laughing Jesus.
He was hanging awkwardly on the side
of a cluttered cork notice board,
surrounded by handwritten notices,
trying to sell textbooks and rusted bicycles.
I sat next to Laughing Jesus for about an hour and a half
before I even realized he was there.
I can be a little bit like that with Jesus.
Laughing Jesus was this pencil drawing of Jesus,
the kind of drawing I had never encountered before.
In fact, I wanna show you the exact drawing.
It was that one there.
Now, undoubtedly, this was Jesus.
I mean, it looked like Jesus, right?
I mean, he's got that unkempt beard.
He's got the kind of long, flowing hair.
He's a little bit more Middle Eastern looking
than I was used to, but I was at seminary,
so there you go.
It wasn't actually kinda how he looked
that kinda caught my eye.
It was what he was doing that caught my eye.
Jesus was laughing, and not just kinda like,
oh, that's kind of a nice antidote.
He's like laughing, laughing, right?
Like either Jesus has just told a great joke
to the disciples, and he's like,
(laughing)
you're like that to them,
or maybe someone's told Jesus a great joke,
and he's laughing alongside of them with that great joke.
And as I stared at this, as I was sitting there
in my first class at seminary on the very first day,
I felt an emotion rising up inside of me,
an emotion towards Jesus I had not felt before,
and after a while, I was able to name that emotion.
Laughing Jesus offended me.
He offended me.
Because as I looked at that picture,
I noticed that the artist had captured Jesus
in a misrepresented way.
Because the Jesus I knew was far too serious
to laugh like that.
The Jesus I knew was here on earth
doing a very sober mission,
where he had come to heal people who were blind,
to cast out demons.
He had come to listen and obey his father.
He had come to teach the things he needed to teach.
He had come to be obedient to death.
Jesus was not laughing about any of that.
No sirree.
As I looked at this more and more,
I was like, this is not the Jesus that I understand.
I thought about all the jokes
that would make me laugh like this,
and I realized none of them were holy.
Are you with me, church?
And I realized that this is a Jesus
that didn't fit the frameworks for Jesus that I had.
Not the pious, divine, sitting on the throne kind of Jesus
that I had met when I was a youth.
Not the powerful, sovereign, almighty Jesus
that I had followed in my 20s.
This was certainly not the more chilled out, calm, relaxed,
justice loving Jesus that I had followed in my 30s.
The reality was laughing Jesus
was simply a Jesus I didn't know.
Now I don't know about you,
but as Christians when we're encountered
by a version of Jesus that we don't know,
we tend to as Christians have a default towards skepticism.
Now on the one side, there's a healthiness to that.
Oftentimes yesterday's skepticism is today's wisdom.
But I think there's a worrying trend
that we have in the church.
That when we see something new of Jesus,
or we hear about something new of Jesus,
we kind of have that reaction
like I had on the first day of seminary.
There's skepticism, we draw back,
we're like, this isn't the kind of Jesus
that I was aware of, and I don't know
what to do with this Jesus.
And oftentimes our response is a little bit
like the people in Bethlehem.
I don't think there's room in the inn for that Jesus.
And as I was looking at this,
I realized one of the reasons why he offended me so much.
It was because the artist had captured a moment of Jesus
in his most human-ness.
Now I understood, 'cause I was at seminary,
that the incarnation meant that God was fully God
and fully human at the same time,
that Jesus in this incarnation brought all that together.
I understood theoretically and theologically about that.
But when I was encountered by a moment of his human-ness,
it annoyed me.
And it annoyed me because I could see
that the artist was trying to say,
this is also Jesus, the human Jesus,
the one who's like at a barbecue,
cracking jokes with his buddies.
And I realized that the reason why this offended me
was because that wasn't the Jesus I needed.
I didn't need a Jesus to be a buddy with me at the barbecue.
I needed Jesus to save my soul
from the brokenness and the sin that I was carrying.
I needed a Jesus, in other words, that wasn't like me.
I intentionally needed a Jesus that wasn't like me.
Are you with me?
Like I wanted a Jesus that was different from me
because I knew who I was.
And I knew that my human-ness meant X, Y, and Z.
I could see the frailties in me,
the insecurities I carried,
the sin that was so prevalent in me.
I didn't wanna worship a Jesus that was like me.
I wanted to worship a Jesus that was so different from me,
transcendent from my human-ness,
able to rise above those emotions,
rise above that sin and that brokenness,
and save me powerfully.
So I had constructed a version of Jesus that I needed.
And when I was encountered with a version of Jesus
that as much as Him as anything else,
because it's not the one that I needed,
it was easy for me to reject Him.
I wanted Jesus to be superhuman, not simply human.
I think one of the main reasons why we fail
to make room in our hearts for more of Jesus
is because the room that we have constructed in our hearts
fits only the Jesus that we want,
not necessarily the Jesus that is.
The Jesus of our own making,
the Jesus of our own construction,
the Jesus that fits comfortably to what I need Him to be,
the Jesus that can save what is going on in my life,
the Jesus that feels good to me.
And when Jesus kinda comes to us
and reveals a part of Himself
that we hadn't encountered before,
rather than open ourselves up more for that reality of Jesus,
we so often shut Him down, push Him out,
and tell Him that there's no room in the end.
The wrestle that we have to do
is that one of the greatest limitations and barriers
to discipleship for us Christians
is I think the limitations we place
on our thinking about Jesus.
And we stay shut away from fresh ways of thinking
and reflecting and embracing the King of Kings
and the Lord of Lords.
And so when Jesus shows up
and reveals something that's different
to the shape that we had created for Him to fit in,
and we suddenly realize that He doesn't fit anymore
the nice, neat shape that I had created for Him,
rather than change my shape, I change Him.
Come on, church.
I fit Him into the shape that I've made for Him.
Rather than expand my heart,
I shrink His divinity down to me.
If we wanna make more room for Jesus,
we must first dethrone the Jesus we make.
Come on, church.
We wanna make more room for Jesus,
we need to first dethrone the Jesus
that we have constructed,
the Jesus that fits nice to us,
the Jesus that serves us.
And we need to begin to think and experience
and encounter the Jesus who really is.
It is this challenge that Luke,
in presenting the birth narrative of Jesus,
finishes his Christmas story with.
He finishes with a story that challenges
how we come to think about the Messiah.
I wanna read this to you from Luke chapter two.
This is the final chapter, if you will,
to his Christmas narrative.
And I wanna pick it up in verse 22 of chapter two in Luke.
When the time of their purification,
according to the law of Moses, had been completed,
Joseph and Mary took him to Jerusalem
to present him before the Lord.
The time of purification, according to the law of Moses,
was about 40 days.
So we reckon here Jesus is about 40 to 45 days old
as Mary and Joseph bring him to the temple.
As it is written in the law of the Lord,
every firstborn male is to be consecrated to the Lord
and to offer a sacrifice in keeping with what is said
in the law of the Lord,
a pair of doves and two young pigeons.
Now, there was a man in Jerusalem called Simeon
who was righteous and devout.
He was waiting for the consolation of Israel
and the Holy Spirit was upon him.
It had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit
that he would not die before he had seen the Lord's Christ.
What a beautiful promise.
Moved by the Spirit, he went into the temple courts.
And when the parents brought in the child Jesus
to do for him, which was custom to the Lord required,
Simeon took him in his arms.
I wonder if the parents freaked out about that, by the way.
Like, you know, that's kind of weird.
It's like they're walking in with the baby
and Simeon sweeps the child off of their arms
into his hands, scary kind of moment.
And Simeon took him in his arms and praised God
by saying this, "Sovereign Lord, as you have promised,
"you can now dismiss your servant in peace.
"For my eyes have seen your salvation,
"which you have prepared in the sight of all the people,
"a light for revelation to the Gentiles
"and for the glory of your people, Israel."
The child's father and mother marveled
at what was said about him.
Yeah, as Luke draws this story to a close,
he starts by, he's a master storyteller, by the way.
He starts by telling you a picture
of this beautiful, pious, religious couple, Mary and Joseph.
He paints them as religious and devout,
as adhering to all of the Old Testament law
that was responsible and requiring for them
to do the things that they do.
So he tells you that they go to the temple
on about 40 days of Jesus' birth.
They've purified themselves,
as was according to the law of Moses.
They then come and do three things in the temple.
The first was a further purification of themselves
by bringing a sacrifice of either a lamb or the doves,
most likely pigeons for them,
as they were of the poorer class.
Then they would take Jesus and present him before the priest,
which is what was right to do for a firstborn son.
Then they would offer another sacrifice
as they dedicate their child to the service of the Lord.
So Luke is presenting to us a story
where this religious and devout couple
do what was required of them in the Old Testament law.
He wants you to see that they're adhering
to all of the scriptures,
all of the things that have been taught in Moses,
all of the things that the Old Testament had suggested.
Here's Mary and Joseph doing it right.
They are operating within the framework
that they understood at the time.
And Luke wants you to understand the irony of this.
It's ironic because the very child
that they are now dedicating to the service of the Lord
is going to be the one who will grow up
and actually break the box that had been created.
So here's Mary and Joseph living within this box
of here's how we should do things
according to the law of Moses.
And their child, the very one they're dedicating,
is gonna be the one that is gonna inaugurate a new wine
through a new wineskin.
One who's gonna bring the kingdom of God,
who's not gonna abolish that law,
but fulfill it and fulfill it in ways
that they never expected him to do.
He's gonna come and say,
"Look, what you're doing on the Sabbath right now is wrong.
"You're so caught up in the law, you've forgotten grace."
He's gonna say some pretty strong things
to the rulers and the teachers and the Pharisees of the law.
He's gonna do stuff where people will stand back and go,
"No Messiah would ever do this."
And he's gonna stand before the people and say,
"If you've got ears, you're gonna be able to hear.
"If you've got eyes, you're gonna be able to see me."
He's gonna disrupt all of the things
that Mary and Joseph are adhering to so perfectly
and Luke's like, "Watch what happens next."
And God always, in these moments
where there's something significant shaping history,
loves to break in and bring a change.
And God decides that this is the moment
where he's gonna proclaim something about his son
publicly before all of Israel.
And he does so by doing how he always did it
through the Old Testament,
by filling the spirit into a man
who is a prophet of his people before his people.
We are introduced to this man by the name of Simeon
in verses 25 and 26.
Notice how Luke describes him.
It says in verse 25,
"Now there was a man in Jerusalem called Simeon
"who was righteous and devout.
"He was waiting for the consolation of Israel
"and the Holy Spirit was upon him."
That's a pretty darn good resume, by the way.
"The Holy Spirit was upon him.
"It had been revealed to him by the Holy Spirit
"that he would not die before he had seen the Lord's Christ."
Can you imagine what this was like?
Sometime in Simeon's life,
and we don't know when it happened,
the Holy Spirit had told him somehow,
maybe through a dream, maybe in another way,
that he would, with his own eyes,
see the Messiah for himself.
You can imagine how exciting that must have been for Simeon.
I'm gonna finally see this longed for.
Remember, the Jewish people had been praying
for 400 years up to this point for this coming Messiah,
and the Lord said by his spirit to Simeon,
"You're not gonna die before you see this."
Now, he was probably quite young at the time.
He's like, "Good, I'm not prepared to die right now.
"That's a good thing."
And maybe every day he went into the temple courts,
every day scanning the children
that were being brought in for these ceremonies,
which happened every day,
and he's praying and going, "Lord, is it this one?
"Lord, is it that one?
"Lord, I hope it's not that one."
And whatever, right?
He's like looking at these kids,
and he's trying to work out which one is which,
and no Messiah, and so he goes home every day.
Can you imagine what it would have felt like
to have a promise of the Lord spoken into your spirit,
holding to that promise, going every day,
believing that that promise is gonna be fulfilled that day,
and then returning home,
realizing that the promise hasn't come through.
And Luke describes him as faithful, devout,
holding on despite the long wait,
and we don't know how long that wait is,
but we know now that he's very old
because the first thing he says
when the Holy Spirit's thought of,
he's like, "Oh, finally, I can now die."
(congregation laughing)
But really what he's saying is
the culmination of the promise has come.
This idea shakes a few things up for us, I think,
because Luke is describing him as faithful and obedient,
and yet the promise hasn't come through yet,
which I think teaches us a very important lesson,
that faithfulness and obedience to the Lord
does not mean an easy life.
It doesn't mean that suddenly
all the answers are gonna come.
It doesn't mean that immediately
the promise will be revealed.
It doesn't even mean that the promise
will come through in our timing, in our preference,
in the nice little neat box that we have created for it.
Sometimes being faithful and obedient means having to wait.
And if that encourages you, maybe challenges you,
well, good news, in January,
we're actually gonna do a whole series on Psalm 27.
I'm really excited about it.
We're gonna be talking about this season of waiting
that many of us wrestle with
and what we can learn and encounter in that season.
So I'm not gonna talk more about that now,
but I wanna say this,
that it's often in those longer seasons,
like it was for Simeon, who faithfully every day showed up
and faithfully went home and said,
"I guess it's gonna be tomorrow."
And he came back the next day and he went home.
And then on this day, everything changed.
So often God breaks in when things are the bleakest,
when they are the darkest, when they are the coldest,
where it feels like he's the furthest away.
Sometimes it's when we're in the valley
of the shadow of death,
that he shows up, breaks in, brings a word, makes a change.
And here's a moment for Simeon
where he didn't know it was gonna be this day
and the wait had been long and things had been hard,
but God breaks in.
And that is the message of Christmas.
And the whole birth of Jesus is God breaking in
to the bleak, dark, coldness of this world
with new lived hope.
I wanna invite you to reflect around that idea
of God breaking in.
And we're gonna do that through listening to another carol
from our worship team.
And they're gonna sing this over us as they do.
So the lyrics will be on the screen behind.
And I want you to read the lyrics and reflect on the lyrics
in relation to what I've been teaching with you so far.
And this beautiful idea that God can break in
to those moments that seem the bleakest.
Let's take a look.
(pages rustling)
(piano notes playing)
I love that.
Final line or the final stanza of the hymn.
Let me read it to you one more time.
What can I give him as poor as I am?
If I were a shepherd, I would bring a lamb.
If I were a wise man, I would do my part.
Yet what I can give him is I can give him my heart.
Beautiful message of Christmas there.
But I think also leaning into what Luke
is trying to say to us in the passage
we're looking at this morning.
We are to give Jesus our heart.
The challenge is what heart are you giving him?
Is it a heart that's big enough to receive all that he is
or a heart so small that you're expecting him
to reduce himself to you?
It is this that basically Simeon is filled with
as he speaks out over Israel.
Let me read to you one more time these words
that Simeon prophesies over Jesus
and the people in the temple.
He says, "Sovereign Lord, as you have promised,
"you can now dismiss your servant in peace.
"For my eyes have indeed seen your salvation,
"which you have prepared in the sight of all the people.
"A light for revelation to the Gentiles
"and a glory to your people Israel."
It's beautiful to me that Simeon filled with the spirit
comes and says something that actually
the Jewish people were not expecting.
If we step back from the moment
and just look at the history that leads us to it,
as I said earlier, that there has been
a 400 year waiting period for this moment.
400 years where the last prophecy
in Malachi in the Old Testament
to this moment where Simeon prophesies in the temple.
That's a long period of time.
And during that time, the Jewish people
had constructed for themselves this Messiah
that they were longing to come.
And they had thought about what is it
that they want this Messiah to be when he does arrive?
And the three primary focuses for the Jewish people
in the first century as they prayed
and longed for the Messiah were this.
Number one, that when the Messiah comes,
the Romans will be pushed away.
The oppression that we're under under the Romans
would finish and the Romans would rule us no more.
Number two, when the Messiah comes,
sin will be suddenly dealt with.
It'll be like an apocalyptic moment
where the world will be changed in an instant
and sin will be no more.
And when the Messiah comes, we, the Jewish people,
would have our rightful place again,
ruling here in the world with our right land
and our right context.
So this idea of Romans be gone, sin be gone,
and for us to have a place of power
and leadership for ourselves, once again,
this was what was wrapped up in the desire for the Messiah.
Now think also, this is the first moment
that the Messiah is proclaimed publicly in Israel.
Remember, the angels had come and proclaimed the Messiah
over the shepherds, and the shepherds had gone
to see Jesus in the stable.
The star had shone in the sky,
which enabled the Magi to journey towards Jesus,
bringing their gifts,
and able to do that before him in the stable.
But 40 days later, this is the first time
that God decides to make a public announcement
about the Messiah and who the Messiah is,
and he's doing that announcement in the very center
of what the Jewish culture and religious sort of hub was
of the day, right there in the temple.
And notice what God, by his Spirit,
inspires Simeon to say first.
The first thing that comes out of his mouth is this,
this Messiah is a light of revelation to the Gentiles.
You can almost imagine,
you could have heard a pin drop in that room.
This is the temple.
This is the seat of Jewish power.
This is where they've been longing and praying
and hoping for, and there's Simeon,
and the first thing he says is,
you wanna know who the Messiah is?
You wanna know what this Jesus is?
He's gonna be a light of revelation to the Gentiles.
Isn't that great?
And you can imagine the people standing around him saying,
whoa, hang on, hang on a sec.
The Gentiles, the ones who rule over us,
the ones who are oppressing us,
this one is going to be a light of revelation to them.
That doesn't sound like grace.
It's funny, isn't it?
Grace is only ever amazing when it's grace for us.
When we find out that grace is for our enemy,
for our oppressor, for the one who has enslaved us,
you're telling me that the Messiah,
this is the first thing, notice God here.
This is the first thing that's announced
to the Jewish power and authority
and the priests and the people
that Jesus is gonna be the Messiah that you did not expect.
You thought the Messiah was gonna push away the Gentiles.
You thought this was all about your re-enthronement.
No, no, no, the Messiah, yes,
there's gonna be glory to Israel,
which is what he says second,
but the first thing he says is,
here's what you need to know about Jesus,
'cause if you don't know this about Jesus, Jewish people,
you're gonna miss him completely.
He's coming to show grace and mercy
and love and revelation and bring change
to the ones that you currently hate.
I mean, talk about God breaking open some boxes
that his people had put Jesus in.
Oh, it needs to look like this.
God says, the first thing you need to know,
it isn't, it's gonna look nothing
like you thought it was gonna look.
And if you don't realize it now,
you're gonna completely miss out.
It's interesting 'cause Jesus then in his ministry,
as he begins to inaugurate the kingdom of God
and as he begins to show that through the miracles he does,
as he begins to do that through the teaching that he does,
often in parables, he would end those teachings saying,
if you have ears to hear, let him hear.
If you can see with eyes, let you see.
In other words, I am here, I'm the Messiah.
I'm the fullness of what you've ever had,
but it looks different to the thing
that you have created me for.
And unless you are enabled to expand what you thought
and embrace the new, you're gonna completely miss out.
This is why Jesus, when he's standing over Jerusalem
at the end of his ministry and the triumphal entry,
looking over the temple as well up on the hill,
he says in the final five days of his life,
he's looking at that temple and he says this.
He says, if only you knew who it was
that was coming to you now,
the Prince of Peace coming to you,
but he says, it is hidden from you.
You put me in a box and you're refusing to accept me
if I don't fit into your box.
But guess what?
It's not about me fitting into your box,
it's about your box getting smashed.
This is the prophetic word to Israel
right at the inauguration of Jesus' dedication
in the temple.
Your box that you have placed me in,
if you do not smash that box, you will miss out.
In other words, it was almost like God was saying,
you are not prepared, Israel,
for the receiving of the Messiah.
And I'm bringing a prophetic word through Simeon
to you right now, that if you can hear it,
if you can open your heart to it,
you will see Jesus bigger.
You will see your Messiah far bigger and far grander
than you could ever see him.
He is more glorious, more powerful, more saving,
more loving, more graceful, more merciful
than you had ever thought he was.
He is gonna be an even greater glory to Israel
if you would just let him out of your box.
It's like he's kind of wanting to take a hammer.
I'm gonna do this for you.
I'm gonna move this out of the way.
It's like he wants to take a hammer to this box
and do this, you ready?
No, I'm not gonna do that.
It's my wife's.
(congregation laughing)
This is my wife's jewelry box, okay?
She's currently on holiday in New Zealand.
She would be very upset if I smashed her jewelry box.
But that's, it's like you need glasses in the front row.
But that's essentially what God is doing
through Simeon to Israel in this moment.
And I wanna say a couple of things to us today
in connection to that.
Number one, I don't think it's just Israel
that puts Jesus in a box.
I think we all have the tendency to do it.
Number two, in the same way that I think Simeon
was this prophetic declaration to Israel,
you are not yet prepared for the Messiah that is coming.
And if you don't get ready, you're gonna miss.
I wanna say this boldly to some of you in this room,
and this will resonate with some of you.
You are not yet prepared for the Jesus of 2026 in your life.
And you need to break him out of the box
you've placed him in.
Otherwise, you will miss out on all the things
that he might have for you in 2026.
You see, we place Jesus in boxes all the time in our life.
I think we have the box of limitations
where we limit the power of Jesus down.
And we say, I don't think Jesus
could touch that part of my life.
I don't think he could heal me of that.
I don't think he could address that situation in my life.
It's been a long time, nothing's ever happened.
I just don't think he can do it.
Boxes of limitations.
We have boxes of experience.
Well, Jesus has never done that for me.
Oh, he might have done that for you.
That's good, that's nice.
That's your testimony, but that's not my experience.
And we limit the power of Jesus in our lives
and we place him in a box because of our experience of him.
I think we have boxes of culture.
Oh, this is how I do things.
This is how my people do things.
This is the way of our culture.
And Jesus doesn't fit to that culture.
And I think we need to shift Jesus
and make him look a little bit more like us
rather than make myself look more like him.
And Jesus comes and gives us the culture
of the kingdom of God,
one that can be seen and flourishing
in all cultures in this world,
but one that needs to be a new culture for each one.
Or perhaps we have boxes of theology.
Ooh, yeah.
Oh, this is how I know Jesus is.
I mean, I've read the scriptures.
This is it.
I know it.
It's like this.
It's a tight little thing like this.
And sometimes our theological boxes
can actually contain him down
rather than keep him mysterious and marvelous and amazing.
Simeon speaks out a bold word to his people.
He's gonna be the light of revelation to the Gentiles.
You need to open your box, he's saying.
Smash it, change it.
Jesus is different.
This is why Paul, when he writes to the church in Ephesus,
chapter three, says, "Jesus," this one,
"is able to do immeasurably more
"than you could ever ask or imagine."
Don't limit him down.
He can do immeasurably more.
"So that his glory would be seen in Christ Jesus
"and in the church," he says.
And there's Jesus himself ministering to the people,
constantly challenging the boxes
that they place the Messiah in,
constantly challenging the old traditions and laws
that have hemmed him in,
and constantly standing before the people and saying,
"I'm with you now.
"Come and see and taste.
"All of you who are weary and burdened, come to me,
"and I will give you rest.
"I am bigger and more grander and more powerful
"than you have created the box for me to be."
Smash your box.
And I can't think of a more important word
as we finish 2025 and as we move into 2026.
That God would stand over you today,
maybe with the same prophetic utterance,
and say, "You've placed me too much in a box.
"I am far bigger than how you currently see me.
"Are you willing to open your eyes?
"For those who have eyes, let them see,
"and those who have ears, let them hear."
Can I pray for you?
Let's pray.
Father, we are humbled by this beautiful part
of the Christmas story,
where the very first utterance publicly over Israel
is to say this Savior is the Savior for the ones
that you do not want to have a Savior.
This Messiah is big enough to offer love and mercy
and forgiveness to even those who you consider your enemies.
The grace is so much bigger than you thought.
And Father, I wanna pray for each of us
as we finish off 2025 and prepare ourselves for 2026.
As this week on Wednesday and Thursday,
we celebrate the arrival of Jesus.
Lord, we wanna go into that process
aware of the boxes that we've placed you in,
where we've limited you because of our experience
or our culture or our theology,
because we try to sort you out
and create a nice, neat little box for you to fit in.
And Lord, I do believe that there are people in this room
who are not yet prepared for the incredible things
that you want to do in their lives in the year ahead.
And you're saying, "Would you smash the box?
"Would you open your heart more?
"Would you not be so skeptical?
"Would you believe that I am grander and bigger
"than you've ever thought, that I am immeasurably more
"than you could ever ask or imagine?
"And I am that for you.
"And this is not about you changing me
"to fit your comfortable life.
"It's about me challenging you to change you
"to walk into the best life."
So Holy Spirit, I wanna pray for anyone in this room
where this message is resonating with them.
As we're in this transition time
between one year to the next,
Father, as a church community, we want to move, Lord,
into the year with no more boxes, no more limitations,
nothing limited by experience or culture or theology,
but an openness in spirit and heart for more of you.
Would you be a light of revelation to us,
the Gentiles in this room?
(gentle music)
Would you reveal yourself in grander and bigger ways
than we could ever have imagined?
And may our worship of you expand
beyond what my heart currently says about you.
Would you show me things about you
that would set my heart on fire, Lord?
I am not satisfied with the Jesus I currently know,
as grateful as I am for it.
Would you be more, Lord?
Would you open me to fresh wind, new wine?
Would you make in me a new wineskin?
And would it be for your glory?
We pray this in Jesus' name.
Everyone says, would you stand with me?
And we're gonna respond together as a community in worship.
(gentle music)