Hello, everyone. I am Mr. Lui.
Welcome to my lecture today.
Today's topic is "Science and Creativity".
I believe you all have the impression that
science and religion seem to have a lot of conflicts.
I believe that many times it is because we don't understand both sides,
and that's why we have these misunderstandings.
I will try to share my understanding with you today.
The content of my lecture today is partly based on
Professor Kuo-king's time-lapse,
and the books and videos of Professor Brian Cox of Manchester University.
I will also use the Bible to explain some of the topics related to creation today.
I would like to emphasize that the Bible is not a book of explanation,
but its description of creation is in line with what we see now.
I will explain in detail later.
In China, in the Western Zhou Dynasty,
there was a saying that "the sky is round and the earth is flat".
At that time, people thought that the earth was square and flat,
while the sky was round.
So the sun and moon rotated in this way.
This kind of understanding affects other Chinese cultures.
For example, the copper coin in the middle is square and the outside is round.
This is the concept of "the sky is round and the earth is flat".
The sky is round and the earth is flat.
The earth is flat and the earth is flat.
This is the understanding of the universe of China 1000 years ago.
In the 4th century BC,
Aristotle predicted that the earth should be round, not square.
In China, about 100 years after the founding of the Chinese Communist Party,
the "Cyclical Theory of Heaven" proposed by Zhang Heng
believed that the sky was like a shell,
and the earth was like a net,
but the earth was flat and floating in the water.
So the shell is rotating outside.
But in the Old Testament, 700 years before the founding of the Chinese Communist Party,
Aristotle had already said that the earth is round.
He said that the gods are sitting on the big circle of the earth.
The residents on the earth are like caterpillars.
The gods are like a net, and the net is like a net.
The sky is flat and the earth is flat.
The net is like a net, and the earth is flat.
The earth is like a net, and the net is like a net.
So in the Old Testament,
it was already said that the earth is round.
God pushed the universe out like a growing wormhole.
The earth we live on now is the solar system,
and the solar system is a part of the entire galaxy.
How big is the entire galaxy?
There are 100,000 light years from one side to the other.
I want to explain that light years are not a unit of time.
Light years are units of distance.
A light year is the speed of light traveling a distance of one year.
How fast does the light travel?
Every second can revolve around the earth and turn 7.5 times.
This is the speed of light.
So the universe is very big, so we have to use light years.
But light years are not big enough.
Sometimes we use light years.
Light years is the distance of light traveling 100 million years.
The distance of the galaxy is one thousandth of a light year.
The earth is one of the points.
You can't see it here.
But the arrangement of the universe
was described in the book of 1,500 BC
as "God created the earth, and the origin is in the void."
There is nothing to be said.
So the part of creation in the Bible
is not a book to explain physics,
but its description is accurate.
How big is the universe?
The universe is 930-940 light years.
A light year is the distance.
I just said that the galaxy is only one thousandth of a light year.
So the universe is very big.
How do we know that the universe is expanding?
This is a phenomenon called "red light."
Everyone can feel it.
Imagine a ambulance coming towards you.
You hear a very oppressive sound.
When the ambulance leaves you,
the sound starts to relax.
When the sound is getting farther and farther,
the sound is getting longer.
So in science,
the sound is moving towards the red side.
So we can see the light that is moving
and the light that is not moving.
The universe can affect many people's thoughts.
For example, in the 500 BC,
Heraclitus, a philosopher,
turned the universe into a sealed space that would not move.
Heraclitus at that time was the same.
When the universe is not big or small,
and it is forever like not moving,
people will generate some reincarnation thoughts.
All things are reincarnated and have a cycle effect.
But if the universe is expanding,
it means that there is a possibility that it has a beginning.
So it is not a unchanging universe.
In Professor Fok-Kun's time-scale,
there are many charts that help us understand the universe,
time and space.
One of them is a knife-shaped ice cream can.
What does he want to say?
He wants to say that if we imagine this board is a water,
there is no water wave at the beginning.
If there is a stone in the middle,
the water waves will spread outwards.
If the speed of this spreading outwards is the speed of light,
the speed of light is the fastest speed in the universe as we know.
It can't be faster than the speed of light.
Then in one second, the speed of light will spread outwards.
Two seconds is even faster.
Three seconds is even faster.
So this is the direction of time.
And this is the space that the speed of light can go.
So if the speed of light is the fastest,
the edge of the ice cream can is the limit.
Nothing can go faster than the edge of the ice cream can.
And all substances cannot spread as fast as light.
So the substance can only exist in the space inside.
This is what it means.
When the universe is exploding,
the force that spreads outward and the force that absorbs inward
must have a relative balance.
Because if the expansion is too strong,
the space in the universe is too large,
it is difficult for the substance to absorb together and form a star.
We call this the open universe.
The open universe is difficult to make life or stars exist.
But if the force of absorption is greater than the force of expansion,
the universe will quickly stick together and shrink back to a point.
So it becomes a closed universe.
So scientists have calculated that
to make the universe continue,
the data that spreads outward must have a small error.
How small is this error?
According to the calculation of Professor Paul Davis,
a colleague of Professor Fok-Kam at Cambridge University,
this error cannot be greater than 1/10^60.
What does this mean?
It means 0.591011 is so small.
It is so small that it may not make much sense to us.
In fact, what helps us understand is that
the universe I just mentioned is 940 billion light-years large.
The difference between the universe from one side to the other
cannot be greater than the area of ​​a fingernail.
This is the accuracy.
If this accuracy is not reached,
the universe will not continue.
So Paul Davis said that
many scientists believe that
the universe is fine-tuned for life.
It can be fine-tuned to allow life to exist.
Although Paul Davis is not a Christian,
many scientists have seen a lot of accurate data in the universe.
When the accuracy is not good,
they believe that the universe is fine-tuned.
Many books now use this "reverse speaker" to describe the expansion of the universe.
What does this speaker mean?
The lower part is the explosion point.
When it starts to explode, it is like blowing a balloon.
When it is blown, the balloon suddenly expands very quickly.
In English, it is called "inflation".
Then the speed of the explosion will slow down.
When it slows down to a certain extent,
we will find that the explosion is accelerating again.
So it is like a speaker.
The flat surface represents the size of the universe.
Scientists did not know that the universe was expanding.
The first time scientists proposed this calculation was in 1922.
It was only in 1929 that it was proven.
It's been about 100 years for our history.
So don't think that science is very advanced.
In fact, we are still very primitive.
As I said,
the early 700s BC already knew that the universe was expanding.
The God "shut out the heavens"
and the God "spread them out"
So to understand the explosion,
we need to understand it with some more specific concepts.
First, I will talk about the relationship between solid and liquid,
the matter and the particles.
Suppose we have an ice cube.
If we heat the ice cube,
the ice will break into water.
When we heat it again,
the water particles will jump out and become air.
the water particles will break into acid.
The particles will jump out of the atoms and atoms.
Generally speaking,
we call anything that can flow as a fluid.
For example, liquid, gas, particles can flow.
These three are called fluids.
What if we heat the particles again?
We break down the structure of the particles,
such as electrons, neutrons, and neutrons.
It becomes acid, 10 atomic particles.
What happens when we heat it again?
It becomes energy, not matter.
But the explosion is the other way around.
At first, all energy is at one point,
the temperature is extremely high.
When the explosion occurs,
the space expands and expands.
The temperature drops,
and the particles start to form from energy.
Gradually, they become different kinds.
When the temperature drops,
we can have gas, liquid, solid, etc.
So the big explosion starts from here.
The simplest material in the universe is called gas.
The sun is mainly gas.
Most of the universe is gas.
Gas is the simplest.
The basic structure of a gas is that
there is a core in the middle.
There are some positive and negative atoms in the core.
The neutral atoms are neither positive nor negative.
The negative atoms are in the electron.
They are rotating in the outer orbit.
The simplest structure of the universe is a negative atom.
The core in the middle has only one positive pole.
There is an electron in the orbit.
The negative pole becomes a neutral negative atom.
The negative atom does not glow.
But when the electron absorbs energy in the orbit,
and jumps up to a higher orbit,
and falls down,
it will emit blue light from the fifth orbit to the second orbit.
The fourth orbit to the second orbit will emit green light.
The third orbit to the second orbit will emit red light.
These three colors are called tri-color.
These are the most basic colors.
The sun emits tri-color.
The LED emits these three colors.
What is the importance of the tri-color?
It is easy to remember.
The logo of a TV is a tri-color.
The tri-color can be combined into five colors.
The sun emits these three colors,
and emits white light.
The amazing thing is that the eyes of the gods
receive these three colors.
So we see the colors because
the eyes of the gods have these sensors
that reflect these three colors.
There is a chart in the "Fork of Gold"
that shows the different stages of the universe after the explosion.
The first stage is a very short time,
called "Law of Physics Unknown".
We don't know what physics is.
I want you to pay attention to the upper part,
which is about temperature.
The temperature is getting lower and lower.
The lower part is the time.
The first part is the shortest part.
Physics is unknown.
It starts from zero to 0.42.0+1 seconds.
In such a short time,
physics is unknown.
So all the explosion theories
don't count this part at the beginning.
So they tell you directly that
there is no need for gods.
Because the explosion is not included in the model.
They start from here.
As the explosion progresses,
the temperature on the top is getting lower and lower.
Because the space is getting bigger and bigger.
Time increases.
But the temperature is still 100 billion degrees in 1 second.
If we feel 35 degrees is very hot,
51 degrees is very hot.
Here it is 100 billion degrees in 1 second.
After the explosion,
it will be 10 billion degrees in 3 minutes.
So when the temperature is getting lower,
this graph shows that
from the atom to the atom,
then some substances appear.
The stars appear.
The star system is formed in about 10 billion years.
Finally, the sun appears.
I just explained that
the theory of quantum mechanics does not need gods.
Because it does not start from zero.
The first part of physics cannot be explained.
So who started it?
Science cannot explain.
Science cannot explain whether there are gods.
Now, in the theory of the explosion in 2022,
I can explain with this graph.
I want to emphasize that it is 2022.
Why?
Because in the past two years,
there have been many new discoveries.
The model is not accurate.
I will explain later.
But the basic explanation is
when the explosion started,
it was very hot at first.
After the explosion, the space increased,
and some substances began to form.
The light had appeared at that time.
But the light could not come out.
Because at that time,
the light and the electrons of other electrons
had interaction.
At this time, it was like a very thick soup.
The light could not come out.
It was like a very large fog.
When the car lights were shot out,
the fog covered the light.
So at this time,
although the light had appeared,
there was light at first,
but the light could not come out.
Around 380,000 years ago,
the light suddenly appeared.
Why?
Because the temperature had dropped.
The light particles and electrons
formed the simplest light atoms.
So suddenly the light appeared.
Now we see the farthest light in the universe
is coming out at this time.
After the light appeared,
many light atoms began to form.
The light atoms, like fog,
covered the light.
So we have a period of dark ages.
According to the old model,
after 300 million years,
the stars appeared in 400 million years.
Because at this time,
the stars began to accumulate together.
The stars have a nuclear fusion process,
producing some ultraviolet light.
Ultraviolet light can make
the electrons in the nuclear fusion atoms
jump and start to emit light.
Many stars have become a spiral structure.
It is called a star system.
It is estimated that it appeared after 100 million years.
The earth appeared after the explosion of 90 billion years.
The universe is now 137 years old.
So the earth is about 47 years old.
This is 2022.
I will use a simple chart to explain.
At first, it is estimated that
there were stars in 400 million years.
This is the period of dark ages.
Although the light exists, it cannot come out.
There were stars in 100 million years.
I want everyone to remember these two numbers.
There were stars in 400 million years and stars in 100 million years.
Two years ago, the Space Agency sent
a new James Webb space telescope to the moon.
It broke all our understanding of the beginning of the universe.
On April 7, 2023,
it was discovered that the earliest star system
was found in 300 million years.
We thought that the star system existed in 100 million years.
Now, it has been found in 300 million to 500 million years.
So it broke the model of our ancient science.
In March of this year, it was found that
some stars have died in 700 million years.
What does it mean by dead?
It means that the whole star system cannot produce new stars.
But remember that in 700 million years,
the universe was still very early.
Now we are talking about 137 billion years.
So 700 million years is still very early.
But some stars have died.
So they cannot produce new stars.
Earlier this year, a British scientist
discovered a very strange phenomenon.
As I said, the universe is 940 billion light years large.
Our galaxy is only one thousandth of a billion light years.
This British scientist noticed that
there are two huge structures in the universe.
These structures are made up of large stars.
One of them is called the Big Circle.
Its diameter is 130 billion light years.
Each point is a huge star.
The other is a larger arc.
Its diameter is 130 billion light years.
This creator is still making some strange structures.
It looks like a smiley face.
Very huge structure.
So it is very difficult for us scientists
to understand how these structures are formed.
As I mentioned, everyone noticed that
the model of science is not absolutely true.
Science is just a tool of knowledge
for understanding the nature and physical world.
Science is not absolutely true.
Science must be constantly corrected.
Science is an approximation to the truth
in a physical world.
It cannot be true outside the physical world.
For example, science cannot be based on
a poem or a poem.
A painting is not beautiful.
Parents' love for children is not science.
It is not a physical field.
Science has a very big limit.
It is not absolutely true.
So we must understand that
science has its own function.
Science is not an absolute authority.
The Bible is not a book of science.
The Bible, especially the Book of Genesis,
is a literary text.
It does not explain the universe in a physical way.
It is just a brief description of God's creation.
The main theme of Genesis is to declare
that God created the universe.
God created the universe with his sovereignty.
At first, God created the universe in a state of vacuum
and gradually became full of life and various miracles.
So the first three days are the basic preparation
for the fourth and fifth days.
The first day is the day of the sun.
The second day is the day of the vacuum.
The vacuum is water and sky.
The third day is the day of the plants.
The fourth day is the day of the stars.
The fourth day is the day of the sun.
The fifth day is the day of the vacuum.
The fifth day is the day of the plants.
The fifth day is the day of the birds.
The sixth day is the day of the animals.
This is the structure of the Bible.
The most important thing is to declare that the universe is God's creation.
Although it seems to be very light,
the most important theme in the first four sentences
is God's creation.
Although it is a few sentences in Hebrew,
the theory of the big explosion we just talked about
is not accurate now.
But we can understand the basic concept.
But the time, maybe we scientists
have to re-change the model
because of the new discovery in the past two years.
Although they have to change the model again,
but we can notice that the basic words
and the framework of the universe
we have observed are consistent.
If we look back at the beginning of God's creation,
we can see that Professor Fok-Kam's picture
shows a moment of vacuum.
Although God created light,
the light cannot come out.
There is a dark period.
After the dark period, the light comes out of the dark.
So the Bible mentions that light is good,
and the light and dark are separated.
Light and dark are later to be separated.
Of course, we can't say that these sentences
are the creation of the whole universe.
Because it is a literary description,
not a theoretical description.
But I want to say that
the Bible says that God created the universe.
This is the point.
But in the Bible,
the creation of the universe is mainly about the earth
from the second day to the sixth day.
The first day is about the universe,
and the second to the sixth day is about the earth.
It is more detailed.
And in the Bible,
there is a detailed description of
the understanding of the earth
by modern scientists.
They believe that the earth was a very hot fluid at first.
A very hot fluid.
I just mentioned the fluid,
including the solid, liquid and gas.
It was very hot at first.
At first, they thought that
the earth we were born on had no atmosphere.
Even if there was, there was no oxygen.
Because what did the gas look like?
It was like the gas that came out of the volcano.
It was a poisonous gas,
like sulfur.
It was not a transparent gas.
So they estimated that
the earliest living creatures on this earth
came from the ocean
and absorbed sulfur.
The earliest living creatures
absorbed these toxins
and produced oxygen.
Oxygen is transparent.
When it absorbs toxins from the atmosphere
and produces oxygen,
the atmosphere becomes transparent.
When there is oxygen, other creatures can slowly form.
For example, fish, reptiles, abalone, and finally humans.
This is the current understanding of modern scientists.
If we pay attention to the Bible,
it is very strange.
The four sentences I said on the first day
are about the formation of the universe.
From the second day to the sixth day,
it is about humans.
Here it talks about the water of the pig.
There are different types of fluids.
The water is divided into up and down.
Some fluids are heavier, some are lighter.
The use of sulfur is heavy,
the use of water is light,
the use of steam is light.
The fluid is divided into up and down.
If you have ever been on a plane,
you will notice that
when you fly to a few thousand feet,
the outside temperature may be -60 °C or -70 °C.
When you fly to a higher level,
the temperature is low,
the steam will turn into water and fall to the ground.
The ground will form a geological shell.
The geological shell of our planet is very thin.
It is about 15 to 20 km on average.
So our planet is like an orange.
There is a hard skin.
There are many fluids and fluids in the middle.
There is a lot of hot sulfur.
A lot of melted iron is spinning here.
So the sequence here is that
there is water at the beginning,
the water falls to the ground,
the ground is cooled and formed a geological shell.
Then the water is collected in the geological shell
and becomes the sea.
When there is a sea, there is no rain.
According to the Bible,
first there is a green plant,
a plant of iron seeds,
a green creature.
Why green creature?
Because of the effect of the sun.
First, it absorbs the smoke from the atmosphere.
Then it excretes oxygen.
So with these carbon dioxide,
the green plant that absorbs the sun's effect and produces oxygen,
like the seaweeds,
we have a large atmosphere.
Then, the third one,
we see two rivers,
the first is the Yangtze River,
where we see the sun and the moon.
Then, the creatures appear,
which is water,
and come out of the water.
It is the same as what scientists believe now.
Then there is a bird.
Then there is a big fish.
In Chinese, it is also called big fish.
In English, it is a monstrous creature.
It is very huge,
maybe similar to
dinosaurs.
Then, at the end,
there are insects,
beasts,
and other creatures.
Finally,
according to the image of God,
we have to follow our own image,
and finally become human.
The last one is
Moses.
At least 1500 years ago,
that is,
3,500 years ago,
God moved him to write the Bible.
He did not have
modern scientific knowledge.
He did not even know
the disease,
the bacteria.
But God let him write
this order,
which is the same as
what we scientists understand now.
This is the miracle of the Bible.
I want to explain one more sentence.
God said,
we have to follow our image,
and finally become human.
Why is this sentence important?
Because I believe that
there are misunderstandings
in the scientific world.
Some people say
that if you count the history of
the Israelites to the time of Adam,
it may be around 7,000 years.
If I find a human
with a human skeleton
of 20,000 years,
how do you explain it?
The DNA is very close.
The Bible says that
the definition of human
is not from the DNA,
but from the image of God.
God may have done something
similar to humans
10,000 years ago.
DNA is a very close creature.
But those creatures at that time
did not have God's image,
no God's spirit,
and could not communicate with God.
So God did not
have a human skeleton.
So the human in the Bible
is not defined by DNA,
but by the image of God.
Here, we are the three-dimensional
God, the image of God.
This is the definition
of the human in the Bible.
So if we find a human skeleton
with a human DNA,
it is also a human,
not a human.
So we can say that
the human is a human.
The human is a human.
Not a human.
As I said,
the most amazing thing in the Bible
is that Moses did not study
at a modern university.
He did not have the knowledge
of modern science.
But he wrote the book
"The Book of Genesis"
more than 3,000 years ago.
Although it is not a materialistic book,
it has a lot of precise
definition of the universe.
As I said,
in the 1500 BC,
God created the earth
in the sky
with the power of man.
The sky is the structure.
In God's eyes,
a thousand years are as one day,
a day is as a thousand years.
This is the relative theory
we know now.
These concepts have existed
since ancient times.
As I mentioned,
God knew that the earth
was a structure created
by the expansion of the universe.
God used his power to create the earth.
This is a wise world.
I will explain the wisdom
later.
So we notice that
the universe expansion
we can observe now,
the order in which the earth
and the organisms are formed,
the order in which the organisms
are formed,
the description in the Bible
is the same.
These scientific interpretations
are described in the Bible.
As I mentioned,
wisdom,
we know that DNA
is not just a material,
DNA is a program of life.
There is a programmer,
there must be a person
behind the programmer.
Because the creator is the source of wisdom.
So we can't say
there is only material.
There is no other.
Because we can see
there is a creator behind this material.
There is a creator behind this material.
Human knowledge of science
is very short and very active.
We only know that a battery
will produce a battery wall
in 1820.
God has already predicted
that in the early days of creation.
As I mentioned,
the rocks in the middle of the earth
are still flowing.
There are a lot of iron
in the middle of the earth
flowing like lava.
This lava
is like an electricity
and produces a battery wall.
This battery wall is very important
because when the sun storm
hits us,
it is a shield, a protective shield.
So our earth still has a large atmosphere.
And the atmosphere of Mars
is already very thin.
Because the atmosphere
of the earth
has already blown away
the atmosphere of Mars.
Because we have this
protective shield,
we can survive.
We see the polar lights,
the polar lights,
when the solar panels
hit us,
they dissipate
the energy in the air.
So we see the light.
But this is a protective shield.
Without the protective shield,
all living things cannot survive.
So when the sun storm
hits us,
it is very kind to us
to arrange this
battery wall for us.
This chart represents
the earth surrounded by the sun.
We have four seasons here.
Last week
was summer.
If you think about
the summer,
we are facing the sun
at noon.
Do you know
how many times
the earth rotates itself?
Many people answer
one circle.
One circle is 360 degrees.
But if we really
rotate 360 degrees,
there will be a problem.
Why?
If we rotate
one circle a day,
the sun will be here
in the future.
After half a year,
when noon comes,
we will be here
on the day of winter solstice.
We will not face the sun.
The sun will be at night.
It turns out that
God is very wonderful.
God makes the arrangement
of the earth surrounded by the sun.
He rotates 0.9856 degrees
with us every day.
One circle is 360 degrees.
It turns out that
the earth rotates
360.9856 degrees.
Why?
We have 365 days
or 365 days
in a year.
In addition to the second,
we have half a year
to winter solstice.
Every day,
we have more than
one day of winter solstice.
If we add 0.9856 degrees,
it will be 180 degrees.
Originally,
when we were here
and went to winter solstice,
God made us
more than one degree.
When we are in winter solstice,
noon is also
under the sun.
Isn't it wonderful?
So you notice
that when the creator of the world
is extremely wonderful,
he even arranged
the earth to rotate a little more
for us.
We see that science
cannot prove
that God exists.
Science is only applied in the natural world
and the material world.
God is a spirit.
So science is not an absolute truth.
Science is only limited to
the approximation to the truth
in the physical world.
Science is not a authority.
God made people
in the absolute world
through a revelation.
God made people
in the non-absolute world
through a revelation.
After people were made,
they produced
many different knowledge.
Science is only one of the knowledge
that can be applied
in the material world.
It cannot explain
art,
love of parents to children,
art, poetry, songs, and dance.
Science cannot do that.
Science is limited.
If we look at the future prediction,
people in the superstition
will look at the whole.
But if we look at how science is applied,
economic prediction,
weather prediction, and science prediction
are not accurate.
So we always blame
the astronomical observatory for bad predictions.
We will say they are not doing enough.
But in fact, they have limitations.
Although they have all the super computers,
but because science is limited,
science is only slowly
approaching the truth.
It is not the truth itself.
If you look at the Bible,
you will notice that
the Bible is very different.
The words of God in the Bible
whether you like it or not,
it must happen.
So the words of God in the Bible
I will explain later.
Why does God
have to be disdainful?
The Bible has already said,
"My will is not your will,
your way is not my way,
how high is the sky above the earth,
how high is my way above your way,
how high is my will above your will."
This is what God
announced to us.
God is much higher than us.
I use these two photos
to explain what is disdainful.
This photo
is taken with my dog
when we were playing.
My dog is a smart dog.
I really went to class with him
and got his certificate.
But no matter how good he is,
I do research, I watch TV,
or I listen to music,
I will not explain to my dog.
Because his
cognitive ability is limited.
Every time
I teach him
some knowledge from a higher level of wisdom
to a lower level of wisdom,
I call it a "discourse".
I can teach him to do things
he can't do normally.
For example, I can teach him
not to pick up food from the table
and eat it when it falls to the ground.
Just like in the Olympic Games,
the chess competition,
the chess players
can train the horse to dance.
The horse doesn't know how to dance.
From a higher level of wisdom
to a lower level of wisdom
to teach and pass on some knowledge
is called "discourse".
The same reason,
God gives people
the highest level of creativity,
gives us the smartest rationality.
I use this yellow circle
to represent people's rationality.
If God's wisdom is infinite,
then we can't
be as smart as God.
God's wisdom is far
higher than our mind.
God's wisdom is far higher than our mind.
If God's wisdom is infinite,
then it is impossible
to try to describe
an infinite God
with human's wisdom
and rationality.
So,
when Thomas Jefferson
said a very important
principle,
God creates human's rationality,
human's rationality
cannot create God,
can only create God and images.
I want to say it again.
God creates human's rationality,
this small rationality,
human's rationality
cannot create an infinite God,
can only create God and images.
I will give you
a few examples to explain
what Thomas Jefferson said.
The most famous
"Fortnite Theorem"
is the "Theorem of Music".
Music is a 18th century
Scottish philosopher.
Many modern
philosophers and philosophers
use similar
theories to try
to prove that God is
bad.
What did he say?
If God is good,
he will not allow
evil and sin in the world.
If God is all-powerful,
he has the ability to
stop evil and sin.
But in fact,
the world is full of evil and sin.
So, he used
the "Fortnite Theorem"
in the very small circle
to deduce that if God is good,
he is not all-powerful
because he has no ability
to stop evil and sin.
So, they used the
limited wisdom of people
to deduce a God.
Their God said
God cannot be all-powerful
and good at the same time.
This is what Thomas Jefferson
said very clearly.
People use their limited wisdom
to try to describe an infinite God.
God can only produce a false god.
This false god cannot be all-powerful
and not all-powerful.
God cannot be all-powerful
and not all-powerful at the same time.
This is the most exquisite observation
of Thomas Jefferson.
Not only this,
there are also
such stories in the Old Testament.
When Moses went to Mount Sinai
to receive the Ten Commandments,
the Israelites
were making gold bulls
at the bottom.
This gold bull was not an idol.
This gold bull was a gift
from the Israelites.
They wanted a God
who could produce
and understand
God.
A God
who can produce,
control
and understand
God
cannot be a true God.
It can only be a false God.
This is the explanation
of Thomas Jefferson's observation.
There are so many human rationalities.
They are all made up rationalities.
To try to explain the infinite wisdom of God,
we can only make a false God.
So you can see
that whether you don't believe
God's wisdom,
believe God,
but believe God in your own way,
the Israelites
also produced a false God.
Their conclusion is also a false God.
Now many people
are also making a false God.
They are trying to
infer God's wisdom
from the rationalities of the people.
You may have heard of this question.
If God is omnipotent,
can he make a big stone
that he can't lift?
Whether it is a big stone
that cannot be lifted,
or a car,
what he wants to say is
if God is omnipotent,
can he not be omniscient?
If we turn this into
a sentence,
if A is God,
B is omnipotent,
he asks
if A is equal to B,
can A not be equal to B?
This is a theory
based on human limitations.
Where is this question?
If A is equal to B,
can A not equal to B?
This is a question of the question itself.
Because this question itself is not logical.
A question that is not logical
is not a logical answer.
So when people think they are very smart,
and try to infer an infinite God
with human rationality,
they can only come up with
such a mistake.
We often get stuck here.
In fact, if people think clearly,
all the miracles of Jesus Christ
cannot be understood
by human rationality.
So we actually need
God's inspiration
to understand
God's inspiration.
God's inspiration,
I call this part "exceeding our rationality".
It is God's inspiration.
So God's words,
God's deeds,
are what we need to accept.
Even if we accept
God's inspiration,
we only know
infinite God a little more.
We will never fully understand
this God.
Because if we really understand this God,
we will only be
a false God in this larger area.
So people in this area
often be a false God.
People who are willing to
accept God's inspiration
and exceed their rationality
to accept and believe in God
are only a little more intelligent.
We will never fully understand God.
So we need to know
where our limitations are.
How to pursue truth?
There are ways to be faithful to others,
ways to be faithful to God.
In the past,
there were Heraclitus of Helium,
Buddha, Confucius, and Lao Tzu.
These are all great people.
They pursued truth all their lives,
and tried to find the truth
through many years of life experience.
But why did they find the truth?
Because they were not the truth.
This is also pointed out
by Thomas Lembke.
These people
have pursued the truth all their lives
because they were not the truth.
We can see in the Bible
that Jesus Christ
was baptized
at the age of 30
according to the Old Testament.
He was baptized at the age of 30.
At first,
he claimed that
he was the way, the truth, and the life.
He claimed that
he was the only way, the justice
between him and the Father and the eternal life.
He was the truth itself.
He was the source of life.
Life was like the Lord of our lives.
In John 1,
the first chapter,
"The beginning of the world is the way,"
this "way" is about Jesus Christ.
Because Satan,
after Jesus Christ ascended to heaven,
about 5 to 60 years later,
he subdued his knowledge
of Jesus Christ
and wrote down
John's Gospel.
At that time,
his other disciples
had all died.
Only John's Gospel
and the Book of Mormon
were left.
It is mentioned here
that the first creation
had this "way" and this "truth."
This "truth" is Jesus Christ.
This "way" and this "truth"
are in the same place with God.
This "way" is God.
What does it mean?
We usually think that the truth
is the philosophical thought
found by some intellectuals.
It is wrong.
Here it tells us
that God is the true essence of truth.
God is the truth of life.
God is the absolute truth.
And the absolute truth
is the truth
because God is the true essence of truth.
The opinions he expresses
and the words he speaks
are the truth.
He has the light,
and it becomes reality.
This is God's ability.
He is the truth.
What he says will happen.
So, everything is done by God.
God also announces
that the whole universe
is done by God.
Here, especially Jesus Christ,
the Holy Trinity,
everything is done by God.
Everything is done by God.
His life is in Him.
He is the source of life.
Life is the light of man.
But the light shines in darkness,
and man does not shine in light.
If we look at this chart,
God is in the absolute world,
in the eternal world,
free and eternal,
justice, holiness,
love and the true essence.
When he led Jesus Christ
to create the universe,
the world of creation,
Jesus Christ claimed
that he was the Alpha,
the Creator,
so the whole human history
is in the hands of Jesus Christ.
From the eternal world of God
to the world of his own creation,
Jesus Christ
is the one who created
the universe.
He is the only way to return to eternity.
So in the Bible,
we should not be surprised
by some very clear proclamation.
For example,
in the book of Timothy,
there is only one God
in the middle of God and man,
there is only one God,
and that is Jesus Christ,
who was born for man.
There is no salvation other than him,
because in the world of man
there is only one God,
and that is Jesus Christ.
So we can see that
science is just a part
of the pre-made wisdom,
and the pre-made science
cannot prove the wonder of God.
So you can see that
even if we go back to the theory of the big explosion,
all scientists cannot go back
to the point of the explosion,
because for a while,
physics cannot be applied.
So all his theories
of the big explosion
started after the explosion.
So science cannot prove
the existence of God.
But God himself
gives us general and special
instructions
to let us know that he exists.
The general instructions are
his creation and to give people
a conscience,
to create for us to have different knowledge,
so that we can develop religion and science,
but most importantly,
God gives special instructions,
special instructions,
God gives the Bible,
God's words,
and Jesus Christ's coming to tell us
what God is like.
So God's existence
is not proven by science,
so there is no need for
any scientific evidence.
Science cannot prove
the existence of God or not.
God's existence is
God's own manifestation.
The Bible says so.
The Bible says that God's righteousness
is manifested in the voice,
God's anger is manifested in heaven,
God's things are manifested by God himself.
It is not that people look for God,
people cannot find God,
but God finds people.
But people usually need to see
the results of God,
understand rationally,
then believe,
like a goldfish,
and then believe in God.
But the Bible has a very strange principle,
that is, by faith,
not by eye,
I will explain later.
Let's look at the results.
The Bible says that
Jews need to see the results,
and the Hebrews need to seek wisdom,
that is, to understand rationally.
People are like this now,
so people need to see with their eyes,
understand rationally.
So some people always say,
"Why don't you call your Jesus
to come down and see me?
I believe when I see him."
So people are often trapped
in the eyes of the eye,
and understand rationally.
The Bible says that
the way out is by faith,
not by these two things.
Can God make people believe?
When we look at the book of Acts,
God separated the Red Sea
from the West,
and the Israelites passed through
the desert on the other side
of the Red Sea.
They saw the Red Sea
separated and they did not believe.
They had no water,
no food,
and Moses had killed them.
They had nothing to eat.
God gave them some food
called "Mala" in heaven every day.
They ate it every day,
and saw Mala and miracles every day.
They did not believe.
They went to the West Mountain,
and they built a false god
called "Bai-Kim-Nau"
in their hearts.
Finally, they went to the land of Canaan,
the land of the angels.
They sent 12 scouts
to this new place.
None of them believed.
The result was very, very miserable.
The miserable result was
that the Israelites
had been in the desert for 40 years.
This generation of disbelievers
could not enter the land of Canaan
and the land of the angels.
This is the miserable result.
Can the miracle make us believe?
In fact, everything God does
is a miracle.
Your and my life
Your and my heartbeats
do not depend on
your and my efforts.
You can ask God to jump faster
or slower,
but you cannot ask God to jump or not jump.
It is the grace of God
that keeps our lives going.
Your and my existence
is not our choice.
But today,
when we live and see
the miracles every day,
people do not believe.
So it is useless to see the miracles.
Is reason important?
We need to understand that reason is important.
But we need to understand that reason
also has its functions and limitations.
The reason God gives people
is beyond other creatures.
So reason is important.
But we need to pay attention to
that reason is not rational.
Many people do not believe in God,
but believe in the devil.
Many people believe in eternal life
and eternal life.
But they tell you that
death is like a light.
What evidence do you have to prove that?
No evidence.
It is not rational.
Many people believe in themselves
when they are not sick or cold.
But when they have symptoms,
they hope to have a miracle.
Right?
So atheism is also irrational.
God's existence does not matter
whether I believe in him or not.
It does not matter if I say he exists or not.
Reason has limitations.
I just explained that
people's reason is limited.
A limited reason
cannot understand
this infinite God.
We need to rely on enlightenment.
So our common mistake is
people's limited reason and
selective wisdom
limit God's enlightenment.
This human reason
becomes a difficulty
to understand God.
I just gave three examples.
The theory of music.
Can God be human?
This is a theory that
the stone cannot lift.
God's enlightenment
is limited.
Some people say whether to believe or not
does not matter.
Look at the Bible.
God's existence or not
does not matter to people's subjective opinion.
God does not exist
because I believe in him.
God does not exist because I do not believe in him.
So whether you and I
believe God exists or not
does not matter to people's subjective opinion.
We are trapped
in the theory of a person.
We just pretend to be a God.
There is also a choice problem in the theory of God.
I once gave a lecture
to a brother.
He told me
that he believed
in many of Jesus'
miracles.
The only thing he did not believe in was the resurrection of Jesus.
I looked at this picture.
All of Jesus'
miracles
are accepted
in the theory of supernatural.
If people have a choice
whether to believe or not,
I cannot see the whole
enlightenment of God.
Even in the Bible,
some people ask me to
give a blessing, I will listen.
Some people ask me to change
my sinful behavior,
I do not want to listen.
People have a choice.
Wisdom is not unimportant.
God gives us
the highest rationality.
So we
have to use up
God's wisdom.
After using to the limit,
we have to open our minds
with confidence
in this supernatural
realm to accept God's
inspiration.
God's infinite wisdom
limits our understanding of God.
God may want to
show us the whole
light.
If we wear colored glasses,
we can only see a part of it.
This is our rationality that limits us.
So we have to open ourselves
to see everything.
Do not rationalize it like a partition
between God and us.
I just talked about faith.
The faith we talked about
is the ability of people
to believe and not to believe.
The faith we talked about
is not a student telling his mother
that he is very hard-working in studying
and has confidence in his exam.
Our faith has three
points.
Our faith
is limited to our faith in God
and
God's words,
which is God's inspiration.
This is limited to this part.
Our faith is in rationality.
We have to understand
that we have to believe in
the part that is beyond rationality.
After we understand
God's words,
we have to
obey
and turn God's words
into the power of life change
to change our lives.
Because faith is infinite.
So the faith and repentance
are two sides of a coin.
Sometimes God calls us to repent
and we see heaven.
God says faith is eternal.
Faith and repentance
are two sides of a coin.
It is the same meaning
that eternal life and seeing heaven.
The third point of faith
is that our faith
is based on God's faith.
I believe in God's words.
I have to understand
and obey God's words.
The most important thing is that I believe
not by my ability,
not by how much I can believe
and how much you can believe.
It doesn't matter if we believe or not.
God is also faithful.
So we put our faith
in God's faith
because God's faith is unchanging.
So the Bible tells us
that when God
gives His word,
He is holding it
to give His word.
Because you and I are not reliable.
Only God is reliable.
In the whole gospel,
only God is faithful.
He can speak
and do things.
He is unchanging.
His faith is unchanging.
So our faith
is based on God's faith,
not our ability to believe.
We don't believe at all.
We feel it will change.
But God's faith is unchanging.
I just said that
the general revelation is related to the universe.
I won't talk about it here.
The special revelation is that
God is holding the Bible
and Jesus Christ
to be born.
This is a belief based on evidence.
There are different people
in the religious community
who have done different statistics
on the meaning of the Bible
and have already accepted a part of it.
One of the things
that I have calculated
is that there are
about 2,500 languages in the Bible.
Some count
more than 1,800 languages.
I use this calculation
to say that there are
about 2,500 languages,
and more than 2,000 of them
have already been born.
So our faith
is not based on estimates.
We are based on God's words
and God's faith.
Because God
tells us that
whether we agree or disagree
in education,
whatever God says will happen.
So in the book of Genesis,
God says, "I have told you
from the beginning of the world,
from ancient times to the end of the world,
that my plan
must be established,
that I must achieve
what I have set out to do.
It doesn't matter whether you believe it or not.
God will do what He says."
This is the foundation of our faith,
the faith of God.
God does not rely on people
to find Him.
God Himself
shows Himself.
How does He show Himself?
He chose Israel
as His teaching tool.
He chose a nation,
told it's words to this nation,
and then led this nation
to be glorified by the whole world.
His goal is to show
people,
to let people know that He is the only God,
and no other gods.
He emphasizes that
He chose Israel
because it is His sovereignty.
So you don't need to ask
why He chose Israel.
God says, "Because it is My sovereignty,
it is My choice."
God chose people
for the purpose of
telling us
about the creation of God,
blessing and help
in front of us.
If we listen to God,
we will be blessed
by the revelation of
the good and righteous justice of God.
If we don't listen to God,
we will be deceived.
There are three important messages
in the Bible.
First, I talked about God's creation,
then the fall of man,
the punishment,
and the salvation.
I will not go into too much detail
about the Bible,
about sin and salvation.
Today I mainly want to talk about
how the Bible proves
that God's existence is not based on science,
but the Bible itself,
God's own judgment.
I mentioned the source of sin,
so I won't spend too much time on it.
The most important thing I want to say is
that God solves the problem of human sin.
You and I are both sinners.
But it doesn't matter if you are comfortable or not.
God told us that we are sinners.
Because you and I know how to lie since childhood,
we don't need anyone to teach us.
We even lie to the point
that we have no concept of sin.
We don't feel ashamed.
The sin of man is not just the sin of action.
Jesus Christ explains that
when you hate someone,
you commit a murder.
You are guilty of the first crime,
which is to kill someone.
You are guilty of the second crime,
The first crime starts from the heart.
I hate someone,
maybe I don't dare to kill him
because I don't want to go to jail
or I can't beat him.
I hate someone for a lifetime,
I hate someone for a lifetime.
I have a guilty conscience against others,
I have committed a crime.
Jesus Christ said that
the heart is the starting point,
the heart of God.
So each of us is a sinner
but God is just and loving.
God said that
no sin will be judged,
but God did not kill anyone.
So God arranged
a redemption for us.
He said that
even if you kill someone,
you have committed a sin,
and you have to be punished by God.
But God gave us a grace
that we can be clean
by following Jesus' old ways.
How to do it?
We can't be atonement for ourselves.
God sent his only son,
Jesus Christ,
a man without sin,
a man who has the same flesh
as you and me,
who has been tested and has not committed a crime,
to become a redemption,
a sacrifice,
a salvation,
a high-quality
without sin,
a high-quality without inferiority.
He used this atonement
to atone for others.
He ate the blood of Jesus,
shed the blood,
and covered the sins of others.
As long as people believe
in the God Jesus Christ
as their Savior,
they can be called righteous.
This is the reason why
the Bible says "to be clean by faith".
The reason is that
you and I are not good people,
we are bad people, we are sinners.
But when we go to the cross,
Jesus died for us.
We admit Jesus,
we admit that we are sinners,
we admit that Jesus is our Savior,
and we accept his salvation.
This means that we add our sins
to Jesus Christ,
and die on the cross for us.
At the same time,
Jesus is the only one
who is a man of the Holy Spirit.
He added his sins
to us like a garment,
and covered us
with his blood.
He covered our shame
and made us
sinners as innocent people.
This is the reason why
we should be clean by faith.
So the most important thing
is that the Bible says
that this Savior,
who created you and me,
not only created you and me,
but also made you
and me into human beings.
So God loves the world,
and even bestowed
his only begotten Son to us.
Let us believe in him,
not to die, but to be eternal.
This is God's love for us.
The salvation of God
is completely the same
from the beginning of the world
to the end of the world.
When Noah committed a crime,
God had already said
that the offspring of a woman
in the future
is Jesus Christ.
Because Jesus Christ is a holy man,
he has no male father.
The offspring of a woman
in the future
is his foster father,
not his biological father.
He is a holy man,
so the woman is Jesus Christ.
When God wanted to
drive Adam and Eve
away from Eden,
God killed an animal
for Adam and Eve,
a bloodthirsty swine,
to make a leather
for Adam and Eve.
This leather is to cover
Adam and Eve's shame
from the crime,
to foretell the future.
In the Bible,
"The man will repent of his sin,
and our sin will be added to
Jesus Christ, not our own sin."
Jesus Christ is like a wedding gown
to cover our shame.
This is the meaning.
There are more than 300 languages
in the Bible
that are related to Jesus.
For example,
in the 600s and 700s
before the communion,
it was said that he was
born of a woman,
born in Bethlehem.
In the book of Isaiah 53,
there are many detailed descriptions
of Jesus Christ.
He will be despised,
he will suffer a lot,
he will be oppressed
and we will be safe.
Because of his oppression,
we will be saved.
He was a criminal,
he was oppressed,
he was buried,
he became a prisoner,
and so on.
In the Bible,
in the book of Matthew,
this Savior came
and asked us to repent.
He has two reasons.
He wants to
collect the
useless fire
and burn it.
It means that
he came to save us
and then to judge us.
Jesus Christ came twice.
The first time was the cross
to save humanity.
The second time was the judgment.
He gave us a chance to repent.
So when people want to
have a miracle,
to see,
to have a wisdom,
to understand God's solution
to human sin,
there is no mercy.
There is only a cross.
This cross represents God's salvation,
God's love for humanity,
forgiveness and grace.
It represents the death of the world
and the resurrection of the world.
The resurrection is the
certainty of eternal life.
So Jesus Christ is resurrected.
This represents love.
The Bible also mentions
that it is rare for people
to die for others.
Some people die for others,
some for others.
But Jesus Christ died for us
when we were sinners.
God's love
is manifested to us again.
Today we are sinning against God.
God loves us.
He speaks to us in tongues
and asks us to repent.
This is God's love.
So the cross represents
God's salvation,
God's wisdom,
God's mercy,
Jesus Christ himself
suffered all the evil of human sin
and suffered alone
to save us.
What is faith?
I just explained
the object of faith,
the characteristics and the basis of faith.
In the Bible,
there are two more things to mention.
First, the grasp of the judgment,
the proof of the truth
of the truth of the cross.
If we look at this chart,
we are here
in the year of our life.
We are here now.
People's eyes
can only see
what is in front of their eyes.
We don't know what will happen
tomorrow.
But the eyes of faith
can transcend time and space.
Because our faith
is based on God's words
and God's truth.
What is the unseen thing?
From the beginning of the world,
the Bible tells us
how God created
and how he led
the Israelites
to spread the word of God
to the whole world.
All the prophecies
that have already happened
have not been seen by us.
But we believe
they are God's words.
There are still many
unfulfilled prophecies
that are
something we are looking forward to.
For example, Jesus will come back to judge.
We know that
he will come back
based on God's truth.
So this faith
is beyond time and space.
I want to emphasize
that this faith is not
what you and I believe.
Our faith is based on God's words.
God's words and God's words.
The foundation is God's truth.
What God says
has nothing to do with our belief.
What he says will definitely happen.
So what has already happened,
although I am not there,
I believe.
So based on the eyes of faith,
it is beyond time and space.
Because of this reason,
Hebert Rice said
a very important thing.
We understand that
the universe is created by God's words.
This is the point.
The point of the Big Bang.
It really has a Big Bang.
Scientists can't explain it
because of physics.
But because of faith,
we know that God created it.
This is what
can be seen by the eye
is created from what can't be seen.
The universe that can be seen
is created from the God
that can't be seen.
The matter that can be seen
is created from the energy
that can't be seen.
Because of faith,
we see very broadly.
Beyond time and space,
we have to understand a lot.
I don't need to be there.
I know because God told me.
And what God said will definitely happen.
We have to believe.
So our faith is much bigger
than people's rationality.
All God's work
is in the part of super rationality.
All God's work is in this part.
If we just keep ourselves in this part,
we will never see God's greatness.
Abraham
we call him the father of faith.
The God and his
herds
can't be seen in the whole life.
The God told him
"The herds of the people
are blessed because of you."
This "herds" refers to Jesus Christ,
the Savior.
He appeared in the
2,000 years of the cross.
He can't be seen in the flesh.
What did Jesus say?
He said in the Gospel of John,
"Abraham rejoiced
and looked up at the days
when he saw joy."
How did he see?
His faith is the spiritual vision.
We believe God's words.
So when God speaks, I believe.
So Abraham
looked up
and saw the Savior.
Although he couldn't see him
in the flesh,
he saw him with faith.
His national land
was built.
When the nation
was in the Jerusalem,
he was no longer in the world.
He had faith.
He believed God.
This is the reason why he had faith.
The Bible says
faith is beyond time.
The faith we talk about
is not what you and I think.
It is God's word.
It is God's word and the faith based on God.
One thing is very important.
It is the resurrection of Christ.
We have never seen it.
Neither have you and I.
The resurrection of Christ.
The Bible says
the resurrection of Christ.
Who was Paul?
Paul was the leader
who led people
to persecute the Christians.
Until the resurrection of Christ,
Paul was the only one
who was resurrected.
Paul said in the Bible
I have been faithful and have given you
the most important thing.
The most important thing is
that Christ is as recorded in the Bible.
It is not what people say.
It is as recorded in the Bible.
It was said in the Bible.
He died for our sins.
He was buried.
It is as recorded in the Bible.
He was resurrected in three days.
We read it in the Old and New Testament.
Jesus Christ predicted three times
that he would be killed and resurrected in three days.
Then he emphasized
that the resurrected Christ
would be Jesus Christ.
The 12 disciples
would appear.
The 500 brothers would appear.
The son of Jesus would appear.
The disciples would appear.
The son of Jesus
would appear.
He was the least of the few.
He was the one who was disowned.
Many people
went to the temple to see
the 12 disciples.
Except John,
who wrote the book of Ephesians
and John's letter to John.
All the other disciples
were Christians.
One of the disciples
was called Thomas.
Thomas was also
a Christian.
Christianity has a very important meaning.
It is the Kingdom of Israel.
It was in 586 BC
which is equivalent to
the Spring and Autumn Period in China.
It is described in detail.
The Israelites were thrown
from heaven to earth.
They were driven to various countries
and humiliated.
They were separated in 2600
and in 1900.
They were separated in 2600 and in 1900.
It is mentioned in the Old Testament
that those who were exiled would return to their homeland.
There was no country in the world
that was able to
return to their homeland
after 2600 years.
There was no country in the world
that could return to their homeland
after 2600 years.
So, before 1948,
many people could still
laugh at the Bible.
After 1948,
we could not
laugh at the Bible.
Jesus Christ
resurrected.
Many believers
witnessed
the resurrection of Jesus Christ.
One of them was Thomas.
Jesus Christ resurrected
for the first time in the Gospels.
Thomas was not present at that time.
When the other Gospels told him,
he said, "Unless I personally
touch the nails of Jesus,
I will be saved."
When Jesus Christ was resurrected for the second time,
he asked Thomas to touch his wounds.
Thomas knelt down
and told Jesus,
"My Lord, my God."
Why?
Because Thomas no longer used his limited
human wisdom to block
God's revelation.
He understood that Jesus Christ was God.
Jesus Christ then told him,
"You see me and believe,
but those who do not see and believe
have the good news."
"What kind of people are these?"
Jesus Christ said,
"Jesus Christ told us
that we were not there
when Jesus Christ was resurrected.
Jesus Christ told
those who did not see
and believed
that Thomas was there.
You believe me,
and you have the good news."
That's all for today.
Thank you.
Take care.
[END]
[BLANK_AUDIO]