All right guys
Happy New Year and why don't you say to your neighbor just a little bit, you know one phrase. Happy New Year. Happy
Okay, so today's the last Sunday of
2025 and as you can
Feel that time is flying
so fast and we're gonna welcome a new year 2026 and
every
Moment of the end of the year turning to a new year
We going to do something new right we think about something new
Today's our young woman in the whole you got to read
She can't end up to the fish or to make a new year the you know, what am I?
Don't go to woman. She didn't end you see Cindy
and then let me go back to
There's something wrong with the PowerPoint and there we go. Okay, there we go
It's how many of you have gym membership?
How many of you know?
Okay, I see two people and then how many you think about new year you're gonna go on diet
Okay
Quick thought, you know, maybe oh I need to go on diet or something
I mean maybe more healthy and we think about new plans and new goals and
You know how the story goes and by March
2026 we're gonna give up right and then the diet is broken the planners sitting on the shelf and the problem is sometimes
we
Something more of our hearts and our hearts need to change
Jason found me and also study
She enjoyed our gym vacay. Why it's until Buchang go to Apple. Yes. I told you woman that in song
We're not I think that you have been said the issue. Yes, I'm seeing John's here. That was Cindy. It's about who's the kid you?
You thought of Sandra fan Jason Kaji woman to不用了也是计划也失败了
Ji-hwa-bae-ye-bae fan. So Jia-sang when he was a woman who's not a woman each other. So the she may have done that I'd beenso
Like to turn to a psalm in the Bible, which is the longest
Psalm in the Bible Psalm 119 and this song is not inviting to all of us to be
to to do some self improvement the psalm is inviting us for a
Transformation and it's not trying to encourage us to try harder
Harder and harder it actually invites us to go deeper to listen
To kind of have a spiritual diary that we can be shaped and we shaped by the voice of God
So that's what Psalm 19 is all about. So as we welcome
2026 God is not calling us to for another, you know new
You know trying hard habit, but he's calling us to have our life anchor in his word
She can't even I used to kill him. Who's he? Oh, she wants you want me to work? He's on our ship. We don't want me shooting guns in
He's not trying to encourage us to try harder and harder it actually invites us to go deeper to listen
To kind of have a spiritual diary that we can be shaped and we shaped by the voice of God
2026 God is not calling us to for another, you know new
She's not trying to encourage us to try harder and harder it actually invites us to have our life anchor in his word
And you have to understand Psalm 19 is the longest chapter in the Bible and there was total of
176 verses in this psalm
If I call you to memorize this, you know, there's no way right? There's no way but you know
It's the longest chapter, but it's not accidental as you can see
Even though not all of us know Hebrew
You've stopped from the right. No from reading from the right to left. That's Hebrew
You see 119. Do you see that 119 in the picture?
119 on the right or already right and you see verse one two, three, four five easier
You see that right?
Okay, I know you're smart. Okay, and then the first letter you can see is kind of like a cross and that is olive
That's the first alphabet of the 22 alphabets of biblical Hebrew and then you go to the next
Picture on the left you see six seven and eight, right?
You see that don't you?
Right. It's also the same letter, right?
so the first eight verses start with the same letter olive and then you see nine to
Two sixteen don't you right and you see another letter starting the next section and
Every line of the next eight lines from nine from verses nine to sixteen start with bake
Which is the second?
alphabet of the psalm so there's a 22 letters in biblical alphabets and
each letter
Has eight verses in Psalm 119 and each verse is a group and begins with the same letter
So as I show you one to eight is olive and then all the way
To the last section of this psalm this long psalm you go to the last alphabet, which is a 22nd letter, which is tough
So the 119th psalm is the longest psalm in the Bible and it has 176 verses
So we can't recite it but it's not a coincidence that it's a psalm of the Hebrew alphabet
There are 22 Hebrew alphabets and each letter corresponds to eight verses and each starts with the same letter
For example, the first to the eighth verses start with olive
The ninth to the sixteenth verses start with bake and the last letter starts with tongue
You know you you you
see what I
Would oh, that's what I'm doing. Okay
Bay and I'll try host of all right. Yeah, I thought you didn't you don't know. Okay. Yeah
Well, that means the psalm is beautifully craft
we call it a cross the psalm and the poet is trying to work really really hard and
In a way that will show you that the Word of God is not
Casual it is intentional and it requires effort and you know beauty and artistic
Artistry to preserve it and the form of the psalm itself is a piece of masterpiece
It's an it's an art form. So it's not randomly put together. It's not occasionally put together, but faithfully
Beautifully put together. It's like English from A to Z
(translation)
Even though you don't know biblical Hebrew before but now, you know, the first letter is called what?
The first letter of Hebrew alphabet olive. Yeah, olive and then the second one
Bay, bay. Yeah, exactly. That's why we got alphabet, right? It goes
Back to many many years ago the development of alphabetical language
Then Hebrew is one of the first ones and anyways
so this psalm is a beautifully put together and it reminds us the first point is that
Let the Word of God lead you into deeper prayer
and
the psalm
Begins with open my eyes that I may see you so
verses
33 it says oh, I'm sorry. I skipped
Open my eyes that I may behold the wonderful things of the law
Right psalm 119 is a beautiful law beautiful psalm together and it's not a prayer for a beginner
it's a prayer for someone who is reading scripture, you know soaking in the Word of God and
and
And want to really really really go into scripture
(translation)
and verses 33 and 34 as you can see on the screen teach me he prays
Oh Lord teach me to follow your decrees and I will keep them to the end and give me
Understanding I will keep your law and obey it with all my heart
So every time you can sense that the poet
Opens the Bible
Turn to the pages of the scripture and he asked God to speak first and he is there to listen and the first response
God's Word produces is not just give us knowledge. It's give us dependency. We want to depend on God and pray to him
(translation)
As we turn to the Word of God as we listen to the Word of God
What we're doing right now our posture has always been to obey and to listen you can think of a young child
You know, we've got some young children here
And I still remember when my boy was so young so young so small and he was scared at night
and the room and the house was dark and the shadows to him was like monsters and
He was in fear and sometimes in the middle of the night
he will come over and
Down the hallway left his room and come to my room and then he was scared and I talked to him
I spoke to him come here. You're safe. You know, daddy is here and
You know, he would not
He would just listen to my voice and he would not do some analysis some
Intellectual exercise to analyze my words. He hears my words and love my words and he will run to me
(translation)
This is what God wants us to do when we hear his Word. It's not just about information but an invitation
It's a voice of invitation
so I want to encourage you this the end of this this year to do something in new year is to
read the Bible and to read the Word of God and
It's not so much of you know doing homework and I need to finish the assignment
But you know you need to have the right posture before God and say to God when we read the Word of God
Father dear Heavenly Father speak to me and I am listening
(translation)
And the second point here is to let the Word of God will shape your heart
So
The second point here is that you know, we need to let the Word of God to change us
help
to to to transform our heart
verses 11 and 72
It says I have hidden or store up your word in my heart that I might not sin against you
and 72 the law the law of God from your mouth is more precious to me than thousands of
pieces of silver and gold
(translation)
So, you know the posture here is to store up, you know to to hide it
Inside the heart and the Hebrew word here implies something very very precious like gold or in your investment
You put it in your heart. So the psalm is not just poetry is to change our
Priority let the priority be first the will of God and you can imagine
again a child
Growing up in a loving home, right and the father constantly tells him, you know
You are love and you know kissing him and you know
Care for him and years later the child goes up and goes to college for example
and even though he's away from home and no one is checking on him, but
he has
stored the word of the father the voice of father inside of him and he knows he's
truly beloved and
Those words from the father will guide his decisions as his choices
(translation)
You know this kind of habit will transform us, you know, I do daily devotion as well
So you should right you should be doing daily devotion and it won't take a long time
You know, I want to tell you my habit every single day is that I subscribe to
devotional channel and I watch two one minute video and
It's it talks about a verse in the Bible and explain to me
You know
What is what the context is and what the meanings are and that's all it takes and then you try to store that
Information that verse in your heart the rest of the day and the Word of God will gradually transform you and that's what scripture
healing in our heart will do
2026 a new year as we welcome it. Please do not let the Word of God stay in your Bible app
Okay
You have Bible app, right?
Don't let it just collect us in your phone
Use it and let the Word of God guide our conscience and our decision and our reactions
(translation)
And then the third point here is to let the Word of God guide your daily steps
I have chosen verses first 105
It says your Word God is a lamb
Unto my feet and is the light to my path and you notice the the metaphor here
It is not a spotlight. You know, the Word of God is not like a spotlight. It is a lamb
(translation)
So imagine, you know waking up at the middle of the night
Maybe you go to I don't know that's what I do. I get old I go to pee
All right in the middle and you know, the room is dark and the house is dark and you don't turn on every light
But you know you had kind of have your lamb or use your phone
As a lamb and it doesn't show you the entire house
You know, the lamb does not have the power to show you everything but it's show you just enough to take the next step safely
Imagine we wake up in the middle of the night
Go to the bathroom or drink water and it's pitch black in the house
We don't turn on all the lights in the house but only the flashlight of the phone
It can't light up the whole house but it can make us safe to go to the next step
So this should be how the Word of God works in my in our lives
The Word of God does not reveal everything about your future about your life or your situation
But the Word of God will protect you every step of the way just enough for you to take the next step safely
You know when I prepare this simple sermon I remember
many many years ago probably
Actually 30 years ago when I first commit myself to to church ministry and I had
30 years ago. I had no idea what my future would look like. I had absolutely no idea, you know
You know, I did not know where I would go and I did not know where I will serve and what are the challenges
I would face and what kind of sacrifice it would require me to go forward
So here I am, you know, I'm still you know, you know rocking
Still working hard and you know, you know God never needed
To show me everything right? I don't I don't I don't ask God to show me every single thing and
Everything about my future. I never asked God to do that and God would not do that
But through his Word he gave me, you know enough guidance to take one step at a time one step at a time
so
At the end of the year I look back
you know, I find that God has been faithful and
He had been guiding me all along
So you can tell what I'm done. I'm doing it. I'm not that little either工作
So you shouldn't from bush you have a you can't go to women
Did I have a heart I eat booty Buddha daddy more maybe you know we talk on what's happening?
You know, I can't eat you say in dog and as we welcome the new year 2026
You know don't just you know come before God and want to try harder
You know don't just promise to to to be committed. You know, you have to think about this
You know one song a day one passage a day of one verse a day
One gospel a day and that is enough, you know read as you pray and pray as you read
Let the Word of God, you know form your year and guide the the new year for you
So you are you know, you know, you know, I'm just a show. She's a kind young show. We all wait. You can you call you make?
Can you can she can make any John for you? So being to be in dog? Oh, yeah, I said the horse without me again
So as we pray together
Remember the Word of God will lead us what lead us into prayer and we shape our heart and guide our every single step
That's that's that's cause it boy
So you are you know, man, you see I thought you know
Dear Lord as we step into
2026 we confess that our hearts are easily distracted
We trace many different things in the world, but we all often neglect your word
Today, we do not want to make you know empty promises want to come before you to make a little commitment
Store your word into our hearts
Shape our thoughts and our desires and our choices
Do I don't want to talk to our new year? We're trying to get a single you can see
Changchun who really the Hawaii今天我们不想在许下空洞的承诺而是要做出圣洁的伪身
求你将你的话写在我们的心理塑造我们的思想可望于每天的选择
Open our eyes to see the wonders the beauty of your work as psalm 119 shows us
Teach us your law according to
Your wisdom and give us understanding may your word become more precious more precious to us than gold and silver
And truly be a lamb
to our feet
like to our path
So you don't just see him the Svartian with woman can't yet so I'm a kind of you are you don't achieve now
Tell the d33 jiao dao women you the beauty told us a p.m. 34 gets a woman who sing when you the heart
So I'm a shin chong be king in gongbao way
Who's a candy? She's our Jaisalmer being真实成为我们脚前的灯路上的光
rule ship in the 105 jaisalmer go
Father make this year this new year different not because our circumstances would change
But because our hearts have changed and we offer the new year
2026 to you as an act of worship
Can't fool to nirvana niancheng way. We young lady. Yeah, who's a human one?
Jing I've been or she even when the sing I've been alone woman, but I don't know you niancheng any don't look in by
In Jesus name we pray phone to yes, or the mean dog. Oh, hey man
Like I bless all of you and remember to read the work out. All right with the world about even one verse a day. All right
Like a bus you can do something
Napa say he can eat yet
Thank you.
(upbeat music)