(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
Lego?
Play-Doh?
Games?
(speaking in foreign language)
(laughing)
Jesus's birthday.
(speaking in foreign language)
A big section of our family Sunday school
Jesus's ministry.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, here we go.
Happy birthday, Jesus.
(speaking in foreign language)
Friends are forever, friendships.
Miracles.
(speaking in foreign language)
Stories and parables.
Huge mind shit.
(speaking in foreign language)
Upside down, right side up.
Birthday.
(speaking in foreign language)
(clapping)
One, two, three.
(speaking in foreign language)
Friends.
Disciples.
(speaking in foreign language)
12 disciples.
, pause.
(speaking in foreign language)
Birthday.
James.
(speaking in foreign language)
John.
Matthew.
Mark.
Simon.
Thomas.
Peter.
Andrew.
Judas.
Thaddeus.
Philip.
(speaking in foreign language)
Bartholomew.
Lazarus.
Lazarus, Mary, Martha.
(speaking in foreign language)
Miracles.
(sighing)
(speaking in foreign language)
Right, water turns to wine.
Ready?
(sighing)
(speaking in foreign language)
Jesus calmed the storm.
Ready?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay.
(sighing)
(coughing)
(speaking in foreign language)
Lazarus, get up.
Lazarus, (speaking in foreign language)
Wow.
(speaking in foreign language)
Stories or parables.
Parables.
(speaking in foreign language)
Sort of like Pictionary.
(paper rustling)
(speaking in foreign language)
The story of the lost lamb.
One out of a hundred.
(speaking in foreign language)
Of the story of the parable.
Okay?
All right.
(speaking in foreign language)
Ready?
Okay.
First one, ready?
(speaking in foreign language)
Discuss, okay?
Go.
(speaking in foreign language)
Mind shift.
Like a thinking bubble.
(speaking in foreign language)
It's total opposite.
I'll tell you.
(speaking in foreign language)
A substitute, a lamb.
The ultimate lamb, that's Jesus.
(speaking in foreign language)
I can't do it alone.
I need help.
(speaking in foreign language)
I need help from God.
I need Jesus.
(speaking in foreign language)
Because he's perfect.
He can substitute me for my sin and things I've done wrong.
Whoa.
(speaking in foreign language)
What do you mean?
Friendship, stories.
(speaking in foreign language)
When our attitude and our hearts change.
God knows.
So I could send Jesus.
(speaking in foreign language)
We are touched by love.
And that's hard sometimes.
(speaking in foreign language)
Mind shift.
Extension time, extension time.
(speaking in foreign language)
Family Sunday school.
Okay, here we go.
Extension time.
(speaking in foreign language)
Friendship.
Miracles.
(speaking in foreign language)
Stories.
Mind shift.
(speaking in foreign language)
But through it all.
We don't, adults don't,
but to go through the journey together.
Okay?
(speaking in foreign language)
Easter.
All right, good.
Okay, after you go,
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, coming up next, Chinese time.
American-born Chinese.
(speaking in foreign language)
So, (speaking in foreign language)
it's okay.
(speaking in foreign language)
Counting words.
What is the difference?
(speaking in foreign language)
If you're ever confused with (speaking in foreign language)
All those, I'm here for you.
I hope, I hope.
Okay, here we go.
Why is (speaking in foreign language)
as in pen, pencil, marker, (speaking in foreign language)
You can't say (speaking in foreign language)
but you can't.
That doesn't make sense.
(speaking in foreign language)
And then, (speaking in foreign language)
Google accounting word is about,
you'll see, the shape of (speaking in foreign language)
Right?
(speaking in foreign language)
This is how I remember.
It's like a (speaking in foreign language)
(speaking in foreign language)
is like a branch, like a stick.
Right?
Stick.
(speaking in foreign language)
Branch, a stick of wood.
Lipstick.
Oh, big clue.
Stick.
(speaking in foreign language)
Chapstick.
That's when you use (speaking in foreign language)
Okay?
Yeah.
That's my clue for you.
Another thing.
(speaking in foreign language)
Sheets of paper.
50 sheets.
(speaking in foreign language)
100.
150.
(speaking in foreign language)
How many sheets?
So sheets.
Like this.
Right?
(speaking in foreign language)
Rectangular.
It comes in sheets.
Those are called (speaking in foreign language)
Okay?
(speaking in foreign language)
One sheet of paper.
That's when you use (speaking in foreign language)
I know.
Not my fault, this is Chinese.
At least.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay.
Ready?
(speaking in foreign language)
Just a shape, right?
Stick or thin rectangle.
(speaking in foreign language)
Also, (speaking in foreign language)
The size, right?
(speaking in foreign language)
Like drops.
Drops.
(speaking in foreign language)
Little bits, little pieces.
Like, (speaking in foreign language)
Skittles.
(speaking in foreign language)
Rock.
Pebbles.
(speaking in foreign language)
Right?
Little pebble.
Little rock.
Stone.
Maybe a little bigger.
(speaking in foreign language)
Stone, right?
Okay?
Boulder.
Big rock.
Huge rock.
Boulder.
(speaking in foreign language)
Whoa.
Okay, difference.
(speaking in foreign language)
Right?
Got it?
(speaking in foreign language)
But you probably say, (speaking in foreign language)
'cause you add the (speaking in foreign language)
it makes it smaller too.
I know.
This is why.
Cantonese is not easy.
Okay, last one.
Are you ready?
Last one for today.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay.
No.
(speaking in foreign language)
Is it like a stick?
No.
(speaking in foreign language)
Is it like a sheet?
Rectangular sheet?
(speaking in foreign language)
Here we go.
Listen up.
(speaking in foreign language)
What does that mean?
There's like a handle.
(speaking in foreign language)
There's a handle.
Okay?
Just like (speaking in foreign language)
(speaking in foreign language)
Sword.
As a handle.
(speaking in foreign language)
Pull out the sword.
Just like (speaking in foreign language)
There's a handle.
That's all I got, guys.
Hope that helps your Chinese, folks.
(speaking in foreign language)
But it's okay.
See you next time.
Bye.
(upbeat music)