[SPEAKING CHINESE]
You can see two pictures here.
On the left is a lonely man.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
On the right is a very happy gathering family.
And if you have a choice, which one would you pick?
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Of course, the right one.
We all desire to be part of the community.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we don't want to be isolated.
And wherever you go, you want that community,
the family to welcome you.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But in reality, sometimes it's different.
And sometimes we come to the United States,
we experience different kinds of isolation.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And all kinds of differences make us foreigner,
whether it's religion, skin color, or culture,
or language.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And sometimes in the church, we feel the same way, too.
We are isolated from each other.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then we want to talk to you about a passage that
talks about isolation and separation.
And it's not just happened to all of us today,
but it happened back then.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we talk about the church in Ephesus.
They have different groups with hostility against each other.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then this passage we're talking about,
it talks about Christ is the only one
who can break down the walls.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that in Christ, Jesus formed a new family
and new community.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we want to see how Christ would break down
all the walls here.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the passage is found in Ephesians chapter 2, 11.
There are three different divisions here.
The first part is 11 to 12.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
OK, 2, 11, it says, "Therefore, remember that formerly you
are Gentiles by birth and called uncircumcised by those
who call themselves the circumcision, which
is done in the body by human hands.
Remember that at that time you were
separated from Christ, excluded from citizenship in Israel
and foreigners to the covenants of the promise without hope,
without God in the world."
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then the second part is 13 and following.
Verses 13 and following, "Now in Christ Jesus,
you who were once were far away have been brought near
by the blood of Christ.
And he himself is our peace, who has made the two groups one
and has destroyed the barrier, the dividing wall of hostility
by setting aside in his flesh the law with his commands
and regulations.
His purpose was to create in himself one new humanity out
of the two, thus making peace, and in one body
to reconcile both of them to God through the cross by which he
put to death the hostility.
He came and preached peace to all of you
who were far away, peace to those who were near.
For through him, we both have access to the Father
by one spirit."
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
The third division of the passage
is found in verses 19 and following.
"Consequently, so you are no longer foreigners and strangers,
but fellow citizens with God's people
and also members of his household,
built on foundation of the apostles and prophets.
With Christ Jesus himself as the chief cornerstone,
in him the whole building is joined together,
rises to become a holy temple in the Lord.
In him, you too are being built together
to become a dwelling in which God lives by the Spirit."
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the background of this passage
talks about the hostility between Jews and Gentiles
in Ephesus.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
You can find the map of the city of Ephesus.
It's located at the western side of Turkey.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Ephesus was a metropolitan city in the ancient world.
And on the right, you can see a humongous theater,
and you can tell how big the city was.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Well, not only it has great wealth,
but it also has the famous Artemis Temple.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you can see the reconstruct diagram on the right.
It has 120 marble pillars to support the temple.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And it was a religious center of worshiping idols.
And once in every year, the crowd
would come from all nations to worship in festivals.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then there were prostitutes in the temple,
and all the visitors would come and have
sex with the temple prostitutes.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And from these kind of activities,
they thought they could guarantee fertility
by doing all these things.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So this was the center of a pilgrimage,
a religious idol pilgrimage.
And that's why Ephesus was a center of economy, finance,
and religion.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And compared to this, even Chicago Pride Parade
would not match this.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So as Chicago and New York and all the major cities,
Ephesus was a very diverse culturally.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So Jews and Gentiles, they lived side by side,
and they don't like each other.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then for three years, Paul was
pastoring the church in Ephesus and trying
to break down the walls with the truth of God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then the Ephesus Church will become
a model of unity in Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then we want to talk about what
are the sources of hostility between the two groups.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Paul begins by commanding the people to remember,
and he wants them to recall their past.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Then from the perspective of the Jews,
the Gentiles or the foreigners were being called uncircumcised.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So one of the sources of hostility
is the uncircumcision of the Gentiles.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And from the Old Testament, you can see how important
circumcision was, because it was our sign of God's covenant
to his people, beginning with Abraham.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you can see the Bible tells us
that circumcision is actually a symbol
to the spiritual reality inside.
But the Jews often turn it into a source of pride.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
They insult the Gentiles by all sorts of different racial
insults and slurs.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And there were so many Roman bathrooms, which was perfect.
And then when they see the Gentiles,
they would despise them.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So this kind of hostility is deeper,
is more intense than whatever racial divide
that we have today.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So there are so many regulations among the Jews,
and they are not willing to help Gentile women.
Even in their childbirth, they are not willing to help them.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And Paul was saying, you guys were being circumcised,
but it was done by human hands.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And Paul was a circumcised Jew as well.
And that's why Paul, speaking from a circumcised Jew,
he said circumcision is merely done by a human hand.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then he was speaking to the Gentiles
and talking to them about the fact
that they were outside of Israel,
outside of the covenant.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So you go back to the Old Testament.
God made a covenant with the Jews, with his people,
and starting from Abraham.
And although there were a few foreigners being included
into the nation of Israel, but however, primarily, it
was for the race, the Jews.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the Gentiles were the foreigners, outsiders
of the covenant.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then all the promises belong to the Jews,
and even the Messiah is prophesied and is for the Jews.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So that's why he says the Gentiles,
you have no part of this whole thing.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the Gentiles, without Christ, they have no hope.
They have no covenant.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you remember, we talked about Ephesus
was a very rich city and full of wealth and temples
and religion.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then all the citizens in Ephesus, the Gentiles,
they were having nightlife and all the excitements
in the worldly life.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then many people would admire them
and want to be like them.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And Paul is talking to the Gentiles in Ephesus
that even though you have all of these things,
but you are without hope in God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So Paul is reminding them they are totally without God,
without Christ, and without hope.
And their life may look very wealthy,
but their life is empty.
And they are without the grace of God
and don't part in God's program.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And one of the applications we can find in this passage
is that Paul's description for the Gentiles
remind us of our own past.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we were foreigners.
And we were without Christ, without God, without hope.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then to many people, maybe we
are having wealth and all these things in life,
but in the sight of God, we are without hope.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we can see that knowing God today, knowing Christ today,
is entirely His grace.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then we can see the human nature in this passage,
because we humans, we like to create divisions.
We like to focus on our differences
among different people.
But God's design is not like this.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we often use our differences to reject one another.
And that is actually pride, believing our group is
superior to other groups.
And the Jews thought circumcision
made them holier so that they despised the Gentiles.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we have to ask today whether we are building
this sort of invisible walls.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And many differences among us in languages, in culture,
in occupation.
Our church as well, we have English-speaking,
Cantonese-speaking, Mandarin-speaking people,
people from China, people from America, people from Hong Kong.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Now I heard a story from a pastor that I know in Canada.
He said his church is filled with two groups.
And one group is the immigrants, investor immigrants.
The other group is professional immigrants.
And they don't like each other, and they
look down on each other.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
The professional immigrants will look down on the investors,
thinking that they only have money,
and they don't have knowledge, and they don't have
the prestige of the society.
On the other hand, the investors will look down
on the professionals and think that they are simply
working class people.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the church should not be like this.
Paul is trying to contrast the past and the present.
You were separated from God, but now you are different.
Now you're in Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And Paul was saying, you guys were far away from God,
but now you are being brought near by the thought of Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And in the past, you were separated from God,
and now you are connected to God.
And that is one of the foundational change
that we have in Christian life.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that is the core value of Christianity.
You were separated from God, but now you are near to God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the core value, core essence of Christianity
is not about behavioral value change,
but it's about our life being changed in Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And it's not because I was bad before,
and now I want to improve myself, be better.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And it is the restoration of relationship with God.
And there's one professor who was a philosopher,
and he used to teach in Chinese University in Hong Kong.
He said Christianity is not about becoming a better person.
It is about being reconciled to God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the restoration of relationship with God
is not about our effort.
It's about the grace of God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And in Ephesus, when they worshiped the pagan god,
that involved a lot of sacrifice and killing a lot of animals.
And some of the cults even practiced infant sacrifice.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you can tell some of the pagans in the Ephesus church,
they have that kind of background.
And when they heard about blood sacrifice,
they immediately understand.
But Paul is trying to say to them, all this blood
that you have shed before had no value
and had no power to save you.
Only the blood of Jesus Christ can truly save you.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then what did Jesus do?
And he destroyed the dividing wall
between Jews and Gentiles.
And we can tell from this passage
what exactly Jesus has done.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And when Paul talks about Jesus breaking down the wall,
he's actually referring to a physical wall that
separates the court of the Jews and the court of the Gentiles
in the temple of Jerusalem.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that wall is actually the dividing separation
between the Jews and Gentiles.
And Gentiles cannot climb over the wall to go into the court.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we have found one of these stone inscriptions
that is being set up on the wall.
It's a warning sign to all the Gentiles.
And the content says, if you're Gentiles,
if you climb over this wall, you will bring yourself death
penalty.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So Paul is saying, Jesus came to break down this wall.
Exactly, this wall is trying to break down so
that Jews and Gentiles are one.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And when he talks about the regulations and the commandments,
he talks about the commandments received by the Jews from God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And because Jesus came, the Jews and even the Gentiles,
we do not depend on the sacrifice from the animal,
because Jesus is the perfect sacrifice.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Now, the source of the law of Moses
is actually from the grace of God.
And God has given the law so that the people
would behave in such a way that would match their identity.
However, the irony is that sometimes the Jews and people
would focus on, because we are keeping the law,
that's why we are better than other people.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And just like the Pharisees, they
were trying to accuse Jesus of not keeping the law,
and not keeping the law just like them.
That's why they accused Jesus and tried to kill him.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that's why the law, Paul says,
the Jews and the Gentiles divide different groups of people.
And Jesus came to remove the barrier,
because Jesus is the perfect keeper of the law.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And Christ fulfilled the law in every single level,
removing the law as a barrier between different people.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that in Christ, in Jesus, we are created as one new humanity.
Jews and Gentiles are all one, united in Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the Bible is telling us the cross of Jesus
is the foundation of true peace.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the true unity between different kinds of people
begins and founded on the peace of Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So if there was no peace of cross,
there was no harmony between different kinds of people.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So Paul is trying to emphasize the fact
that Jews or Gentiles, whether you
belong to the first group or the second group,
you have to come to Christ, come to God through Jesus Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And if we want to resolve conflicts
between different people, we must come to the cross
and meet Jesus at the foot of the cross,
because we are all sinners and we need the grace of God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And if you want to make peace with yourself,
you have to find the true peace in Jesus first.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And sometimes we cannot make peace with ourselves
because we cannot forgive ourselves,
but we find true forgiveness only in Jesus Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then this passage tells us the three persons of the Trinity,
the same God, all participate in the reconciliation of mankind
relationship with God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And Paul says, through the Spirit, we come to the Father.
And the Son redeems us and the Spirit makes us one.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So we talk about Father's love and the redemption of Christ,
and we also emphasize the Spirit's work in our lives.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So Christianity is not just doctrine, not just knowledge,
but it involves power, life-changing power
in the Spirit.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the doctrines that we believe in
is founded in the historic event of Jesus Christ.
And without what Jesus has done, our doctrine will be empty.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But if we just have doctrine and theology without the Spirit,
it becomes dead faith, dead orthodoxy.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But if we just pursue the Spirit without the truth,
it will become unhealthy emotionalism in our faith.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we need both truth and the Spirit.
And one of the main ways is to rely on the Spirit
through our prayer.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we can pray anytime.
And the irony is that sometimes we don't pray.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And sometimes we find it easy to attend worship,
to give an offering, but praying sometimes
becomes difficult for all of us.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
We can talk to our friend and have
chat with our friend for hours.
But sometimes the moment comes we have to pray.
Sometimes our minds will wander.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And different things will occupy our mind.
And we cannot be silent.
We cannot be attentive before God and pray.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And after a few minutes, we give up praying.
So we need the Spirit to help us to pray.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the third point here--
So you were separated from Christ,
but Jesus came to break down all this wall.
And you are now near to Christ.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the different identity changes here.
From you were foreigners, and now you
are fellow citizens in the kingdom.
You were strangers to God.
Now you are members of the family, the household of God.
You were scattered stone and separated, isolated.
But now you have been built together to become a temple.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then before, we did not have the heavenly identity.
Now we do have the heavenly identity in the kingdom.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
In the past, we wandered without hope.
But now we are part of the family,
part of the God's household.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we are all part of the members
being built together to build the dwelling of God,
the temple of God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the church is actually God's temple in construction.
And the church refers not to the physical building here,
but the people of God themselves.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Of course, our church is a visible church,
a manifestation of the people of God.
But there is also a capital C church,
which is so much bigger and involves all the saints
and all the Christians from history
and from different parts of the world.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the capital C church is the invisible church, which is real
and involves all the Christians from all the times.
And it goes beyond geographical boundaries.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So it says the church has a cornerstone in Christ.
And I find this diagram.
It shows you the cornerstone, where it is.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the foundation is the apostles and the prophets.
It's on the wall here.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So the cornerstone, you see, is Jesus Christ.
And the wall connected to the cornerstone
is the prophet and the apostles.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that's why all the Christians from the entire world,
we are part of this house.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the importance of the cornerstone, because it
dictates the plan and the structure
of the entire building.
And that is Jesus Christ himself.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And church is not built by a man.
It's not just a social organization.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And if the church is simply a social organization,
it would not survive for so many years.
But you can tell from church history,
the church survives all the generations.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the church is founded on Jesus Christ, the cornerstone,
and Christ himself dictates and commands the church.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you can see, even our church, sometimes we decline.
And our church can fall apart.
But we have to have that perspective of the capital C
Church, and Christ is commanding his church,
and all of the world, and all through history.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And every member of the church, every Christian,
is one of the living stones being built together
to form the temple for God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So in this diagram, we are part of the different stones
and bricks to build this whole household.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you can see the church will continue
to grow no matter what.
If you include the Old Testament,
it has even longer history.
And the church will continue to grow.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And the church will continue to grow in the size
that's beyond our imagination.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And for now, church history seems
to be mixed with the world history.
But it seems like it's just one of the organizations
in the world.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But you have to remember the church is in construction.
And you can tell, if an unfinished building,
you can see a lot of different things here,
different unconstructed part, and needs to be renovated.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But this building will continue to grow
and continue to be constructed by Christ.
And someday, this church will be complete.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And then all these tools and unfinished part will be gone.
And the wall will be gone.
But the church remains.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And it seems that the church is growing
with all kinds of organizations in the world, all the bodies
in the world.
But someday, when God completes His church,
everything will be unnecessary and will be removed.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And you can see we are the church.
The Spirit of God lives among us.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
You think about it in the Old Testament,
when the people of God want to see God and worship God,
they have to travel a long distance
to come to the temple to worship God together.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But now Christ has come.
All the people of God lives in Christ Himself.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So each and every one of us, the Spirit lives among us.
So when we love each other and we care for each other,
the light of God will be demonstrated.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And if we think about it, we need
to ask the question whether we are still
having the mentality of foreigners or outsiders.
We don't find the sense of belonging here.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
But you have to remember, even though you don't find acceptance
in the community, you have to remember
that you are fully accepted in Christ Jesus.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And when Christ sees you, it's not because of your skin color,
it's not because of your background,
but sees you just like He sees you in Christ, in Jesus.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
So your identity now you find in Christ
is that you are part of the family of God
and part of the people of God and near to God.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And that's why we need to pray and we
need to dwell in the presence of God, to draw near to Him.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Let's all pray together.
Heavenly Father, we want to praise you and give you thanks.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
You sent Jesus, your son, to be the messenger of peace.
So that we can restore our relationship with you.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we are no longer outsiders and we
can come become your family and call you Abba Father.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
Our Savior, Jesus Christ, He broke down all the barriers
with His blood.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And we are all different in front of you.
And I just pray that you will help us to be united in you.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And help us not forget that we are all sinners
and we are not better than other people.
We are all saved by grace.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
And please make us peacemakers as well.
So that we can bring the message of reconciliation
to other people.
[SPEAKING CHINESE]
In Jesus' name we pray.
Amen.
Bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]