[music]
Hello everyone! I'm Miss Rebecca.
Welcome back to Family Sunday School.
This week is the fifth episode.
Do you remember what we talked about in the fourth episode?
Yes, we get to know a lot of different animals
and make a lot of different sounds.
But what's the most important thing?
The dog!
What is Peter doing?
Yes, he is rejecting Jesus.
Did you notice that I'm wearing different glasses?
Do you remember?
In the last episode, I asked my parents to read other Bible verses.
I asked them to see if they could relate to the story I told.
Why do we need to see so many different verses?
So that we can see them from different angles.
For example, I'm wearing these glasses.
I'm a little blurred when I'm looking at things.
Why?
Because of the eyebrows, the nose, and the nose.
But if I wear glasses or wear clothes,
will it be more clear?
I'm wearing these glasses, but they are a little dirty.
I can't see very clearly.
I change my clothes, but I can see different things.
This pair of glasses is so clear.
When we turn our glasses, we can see different things.
Sometimes it's a little blurry, sometimes it's clearer.
Or something is magnified.
Because there are many different glasses for different purposes.
For example, when parents or elders are reading,
they are a little blurry.
They can't read when they are close to reading.
But with glasses, they can read.
So, we magnify.
Right?
So, today, let's see if you really read other Bible verses.
Did you find anything?
Any new discoveries?
Tell me.
No?
It's okay.
I read it too.
But, Miss Rebecca has a lot of different Bible verses.
Right?
When Miss Rebecca didn't talk about it in the last episode,
she didn't mention one thing.
She didn't mention the cock-a-doodle-doo.
Peter looked at Jesus.
Jesus looked at Peter.
Oh, he really did it.
Miss Rebecca didn't mention it.
How?
In that book?
This book also mentions it.
What does it say?
Peter cried and ran away.
He wept and fled the courtyard.
He cried and ran away.
So, when he left the courtyard,
he didn't know what happened.
So, this is one thing.
He left.
Right?
Who did it?
John!
Right.
There's one more thing.
Miss Rebecca found it in other Bible verses.
Do you remember?
There were three times when people asked Peter,
"Do you know Jesus?"
"No, I don't know him."
"I don't know what you're talking about."
Right?
There were two ladies.
One lady asked,
"You seem to be with him."
"No, not me."
"No, you really seem to be with him."
The second lady said,
"No, I don't know what you're talking about."
Then, a little further away,
there was a man.
He said, "No, I heard your accent."
"Accent" means "accent."
Sometimes, when we come from different places,
we have different accents.
Even though we're speaking English,
when we use English with different accents,
we'll know where we're from.
Right?
So, he heard her say,
"No, you're from Galilee."
Because in Galilee,
the way they speak and their accents are a little different.
They can hear.
Right?
Ms. Birkin didn't mention that.
So, there are many hints
to let them know that
Peter is with Jesus,
but Peter is a pharaoh.
What will we talk about in this episode?
Jesus went in.
He went into his house
with the elders.
These elders are the highest leaders of the Jews.
Do you know that?
When they went in,
they had to judge him.
Judge him.
Trial him.
See what crimes he committed.
Those who arrested him
thought he committed all kinds of crimes.
But is it true?
Today, we'll see
what happens when Jesus is judged.
But before we start,
what do we do?
Of course, we play a game.
Okay.
Let's play a game.
Get ready.
I have a musical instrument.
I will play this musical instrument.
This is called a xylophone.
In Chinese, it's called a wood instrument.
In the past, it was made of wood.
It made different sounds.
This one is made of iron.
When I play,
you have to throw the ball.
You can find a ball or a toy.
You can find a leaf.
I play and you throw.
You don't have to follow the order.
Throw to the person you want to throw.
Throw again.
The object is to not hit the ball.
I play the wood instrument.
After the music,
whoever holds the ball is out.
Okay?
We'll do four rounds.
I'll do four rounds.
I don't know how many people are there.
Let's start.
Here we go.
[xylophone playing]
Done!
Whoever holds the hot potato
is out of the round.
Okay, next round.
Ready?
You can switch places.
You can take it away.
You can do whatever you want.
Okay, second round.
Here we go.
[xylophone playing]
Done!
Okay.
Who got it?
What do you do if you get the hot potato?
Yes, you're out.
Sorry.
You can continue next time.
Okay?
It's not a game.
Sometimes we win, sometimes we lose.
[speaking in Chinese]
Okay.
Round number three.
[xylophone playing]
All done!
[speaking in Chinese]
Okay.
Ready?
Let's go.
[xylophone playing]
All done!
Okay.
[speaking in Chinese]
Last one standing.
Winner.
[speaking in Chinese]
Okay.
All right.
Have fun!
[speaking in Chinese]
Bible story time!
Bible story time.
[speaking in Chinese]
Hello Chinese time!
Let me tell you, break it down, break it down.
[speaking in Chinese]
Okay, ready?
At home extension time.
[speaking in Chinese]
Act it out.
Okay?
[speaking in Chinese]
That tells you, they got it.
[music playing]