Good morning.
Okay, the mic is working.
Today we will be
in the book of James.
So if you would all open with me your Bibles to the book of James.
It is closer to the back following
Hebrews. So I'll give you a moment.
If you do not have your Bibles with you or on you
we have it on the screen here.
So we will be reading from its first chapter
verses 1 to 18 and then we'll open
in a word of prayer.
James chapter 1 verses 1 to 18.
James, a servant of God and of the
Lord Jesus Christ. To the 12 tribes in the dispersion
greetings.
Count it all joy my brothers when you meet trials of various kinds
for you know that the testing of your faith produces steadfastness
and let steadfastness have its full effect that you may be perfect and complete
lacking in nothing.
If any of you lacks wisdom let him ask God who gives generously
to all without reproach and it will be given him. But let him
ask in faith with no doubting for the one who doubts is like a wave
of the sea that is driven and tossed by the wind. For that person
must not suppose that he will receive anything from the Lord. He is a double
minded man unstable in all his ways.
Let the lowly brother boast in his exaltation
and the rich in his humiliation because like a flower
in the flower of the grass he will pass away. For the
sun rises with scorching heat and withers the grass. Its flower
falls and its beauty perishes. So also will the rich man fade
away in the midst of his pursuits. Blessed
is the man who remains steadfast under trial
for when he has stood the test he will receive the crown of life
which God has promised to those who love him. Let no one say when he is tempted
I am being tempted by God for God cannot be tempted with evil
and he himself tempts no one. But each person is tempted when he is
lured and enticed by his own desire. Then desire when it has conceived
gives birth to sin and sin when it is fully grown brings
forth death. Do not
be deceived my beloved brothers. Every good gift and every perfect
gift is from above coming down from the father of lights with whom there is
no variation or shadow due to change. Of his own will
he brought us forth by the word of truth that we should be a kind of
first fruits of his creatures.
Let's pray.
Father all praise all glory all
honor be to you. For righteousness and justice
are the foundation of your throne. The heavens
declare your righteousness God and your people have seen
your glory.
In the coming moments we ask that you would speak that your word would
be illuminated for us. Guard the
ears of your people oh God that their feet would not be stumbled.
Would you give them hearts that are renewed so that
their hearts would yield to you and your spirit.
Call us to be still oh God so that we may again
find our refuge in you. All this we pray in
Jesus' name amen. Okay.
Let me go back to the beginning.
That's too far.
So I think you'll find
that one of the most pressing questions that appear before
us in our daily lives is the question what now?
After all our lives are constantly changing
because time is linear it moves in a linear fashion
we are continually picking up new responsibilities.
A few of us here are in school.
Some of us most of us are in the workforce
and there are a few of us here that are new
parents. Those of us who are not going to be new parents we have
friends who are being new parents. All new life stages
all new circumstances everything is
kind of inescapable. And with every change
in our life we're faced with the question what
now? What should my life look like? What is expected
of me and what do I do now?
And this question of what now becomes even more pressing when the
changes in our lives are not just confusing or new
but bad. Financial
strain, relational strife,
deep, deep loss.
All of it is a heavy, heavy weight on our shoulders.
And to further complicate things you'll find that there is
more to this question of what now?
It's a Sunday morning. You guys are here. You chose to be
here. And so the question for you is
as people of God how are you expected
to live? If you look again with
me to James chapter 1 verse 1 you'll find that the
audiences of this letter are the 12 tribes of
the dispersion. James a servant of God of the Lord Jesus
Christ to the 12 tribes of the dispersion. These are the
Jewish Christians living outside of Palestine. Those living in a foreign
and famished land. They are displaced.
They're poverty stricken. They are starving from persecution
and social exile.
In circumstances like that it's
almost natural for hardship to bleed into character.
It's almost expected. Under this sort of
pressure the cracks, our cracks begin to show.
They widen to reveal already present
flaws in our character. And if we're being honest with ourselves
we can all recognize some inadequacies
in ourselves that are covered up and usually hidden behind our strengths.
Like we see in verse 14.
Let me go to verse 14 real quick.
Verse 14.
What threatens to drag us away can so often come from
the desires within us that seek to produce sin and subsequently
death. It says, "But each person is tempted when he is lured and enticed
by his own desire. Then desire when it has conceived gives birth to sin
and sin when it has fully grown gives birth to death."
Life is hard. Life is hard
and it makes us hard. And yet, and yet we find
that James heaps instruction upon instruction
upon these Jewish Christians.
He gives instructions that call for those of the
dispersion to behave contrary to their circumstances.
To go against the natural flow of action.
Look at verse 2. What does it say?
It says, "Count it all joy, my brothers, when you meet trials of various kinds.
Consider it joy when you face trials." James makes
this point. Let this be an occasion for joy.
Joy.
This is a strange and unexpected response to suffering.
It almost feels inappropriate
in some ways. But don't misunderstand.
Don't look at this and think to yourself,
I gotta pretend that things are okay.
This is not a forced joy, but an eschatological
joy. A joy that comes from looking beyond.
And seeing something joyous. It's a response of joy.
If you look at verse 2, James calls for his brothers and sisters
to consider it joy when they face trials. And the reason
the reason to consider such things joy, such hardships
as joy is because the testing of their faith produces
steadfastness. Note that this
testing they speak of is not to determine
whether or not there is faith in you. It's instead
here to refine faith that is already present. And in this
refining of faith, steadfastness is produced.
You'll find that only through this refining
process would this facet of steadfastness
this endurance and perseverance exist within
believers. But
with all this talk about steadfastness
you'll find that this is not the goal. Not just for the
sake of being a steadfast person. Steadfastness itself
is not the goal. Instead, if you look with me
to verse 4, you'll see that the goal
and desired outcome of suffering trial is something else.
Right? And let steadfastness have its full
effect that you may be perfect and complete, lacking
in nothing. The goal is not a specific virtue.
It's not a particular fruit. The goal
of steadfastness is your perfection.
Your completeness. Perfection
is central to James' writing. It's this picture of wholeness
a finished and flawless
work. We see this idea of perfection
in verse 5 through the contrasting of two men.
Let's take a look. The first person
the first person spoken of by James embodies
wholeness. They are lacking in nothing because they ask in
faith and they receive wisdom from God. The first person is
wise. But the second? The second person is
like a wave of the sea, blown and tossed
by the wind. They are double-minded
and unstable, doubtful of the security of God's promises for them.
And they're torn apart with inner conflict. They wander
on and off every road they can see. In everything
they do, they are fractured and inconsistent. They're not
whole and they are not wise.
In all of this is the implication that God desires
for his followers to live true to their titles.
Followers. What do followers do? They follow. God desires for
his followers to follow him. And more than that, it's implied
it's implied that God desires for those who follow him
to be refined, to be perfected, and to be completed.
To be wise and be affected by
wisdom. Not in part, but in whole.
For the collective voice of scripture calls for you to not just be
followers, but imitators of Christ.
That your whole being and every aspect
of you would be refined and conformed into the likeness
of the rock that is higher. And that from this
completeness, your actions would be good and pleasing
to God. See,
this that we talk about, this being wise,
being perfected, this result of suffering under trial.
It is a continuing of the work of God. The call to count
all joy in poverty and humiliation is a command that is
founded on the finished work of Jesus. You,
having been saved, you are called away from being fractured
and inconsistent. You are called toward being whole
with every aspect of your being.
The reality we see in James is that
faith has an effect on
life. And that the culmination
of Christian life is a whole
and perfect conformity to the likeness of Christ.
Why?
Verse 9, "Why should the lowly brother boast
as lowly? Because his position
in Christ is not lowly, but exalted. He is not poor,
but rich. Why then should the rich
boast in his humiliation? Because his richness
comes from his inheritance from heaven, not
the collection of dust on this earth.
Why should those undergoing trials and temptations
consider it joy? Because in the
trying of your faith, you and those around you become witnesses
to the work of God that is being done in you.
You see with your eyes that faith is present in you. And now
you're given this opportunity to exercise the faith
that is in you by placing weight on it, by trusting
it. Do you see?
Do you see here? The command here
to count it pure joy is not another burden
for you to carry on top of the pains of life.
It's an instruction given to you so that you can live.
Blessed is the man who remains
steadfast under trial for he has, when he has withstood the test,
he will receive the crown of life which God has promised to those
who love him.
And so,
looking at all this,
do you want to be wise?
Do you want your life to look like?
My brothers and sisters, in
sickness, loneliness, bereavement, and disappointment,
don't keep your eyes fixed on the circumstances of life.
Don't keep your eyes fixed on the desires
of the flesh. Instead, look
towards the object of your faith, the good and perfect gift
of God to you, his son Jesus. And see
that the promises of God are fulfilled to you in Jesus, in Christ.
Know that the work of Jesus will not be undone, and that
the Spirit is in this very moment making you more and more
like Christ, and consider it all
joy. The task laid before
you is this. Joyfully lean into
the work of God that is being done in you,
and continue in that way.
Become holy like Christ.
That was a little short, but let me
close us in a word of prayer. Would you bow your heads with me?
Father, we give you thanks
because you have been with
us every single second of the day. There is not a moment
that we are away from you or apart from you. You have
seen us and known us, and before we were, you were.
So, Lord, ask that you would continue to
keep your hand on your people, on these brothers and sisters of mine,
that you would reveal to them how deeply you love them,
that they would start there, not looking at their own selves or the things
around them, but God, let them look at you first and foremost.
Would you make them rely on you, depend
on you for everything in their life, that they might be a reflection of the way
that you provide for them? Remove from them
all these obstacles that hinder them, Lord, and keep
them firmly in your hand. Give them a
stronger spirit, a motivation to grow,
and help them be good representatives of who you are.
We pray this in Jesus' name. Amen.
Thank you very much.