(speaking in foreign language)
In Christ's name we pray.
- Well, I wanna say Merry Christmas to all of you.
And I think like many of you,
Christmas can be a crazy time.
It can be a very busy time.
And this Christmas season,
I'm thinking of fathers, mothers,
hardworking people in the restaurants
who are running, operating in our society,
making sure our loved ones are being taken care of.
And today I know many of you who are part of our church,
you did your best to make this church a better place.
Especially today, those who are in the backstage,
those who prepare the table,
those who prepare the good food that we're gonna enjoy,
and the people and the personnel on stage,
the musicians and all the helpers.
I know this is a crazy, busy time,
but it's also a time for us to slow down,
to think about what this season is all about,
what Christmas is all about.
I also think of many of you,
or even many of us who are joining us online
and cannot be on site.
I'm thinking of you because I know you're going through
some crisis in your life,
some troubles, some difficulties.
And you are one of those taking care of the sick,
the dying in your family.
And know that God is with you.
This is a challenging time.
Maybe you are dealing with broken relationships.
Maybe you're dealing with a lot of uncertainty.
And many of us, this holiday season is not easy.
It's a tough season.
But this is the time we should turn to God.
We should turn our eyes to heaven
because Christmas is a special time
when we celebrate the birth of Jesus Christ,
someone who is special.
In Jesus Christ, we have everlasting joy,
not happiness.
We have everlasting peace, not temporary peace.
In Jesus Christ, we have hope, hope that is everlasting.
I know you probably listen to a lot of songs
about Christmas on radio or on Spotify.
If you pay attention to some of these Christmas songs,
Christmas hymns, some of them are hundreds of years old,
very, very old.
And you listen to the lyrics.
All of these Christmas songs
speak about the most basic human desire,
the desire deep down in our heart.
We yearn for peace in our time of chaos.
We yearn for joy in our time of sadness.
We yearn for someone to be with us, and we feel lonely.
We yearn for hope when we see there's no end in the tunnel.
It is no wonder that in this Christmas season,
the rate of suicide and depression increase.
It's no wonder.
This is a very depressing time for many of us.
But yes, even though we are in a difficult time,
even though we see a lot of oppressions, injustice,
darkness in our world,
we are reminded on this Christmas Sunday
that a newborn King was given to all of us.
(speaking in foreign language)
So in this Christmas,
we wanna turn our attention to this child.
The kid, the infant was born for all of us.
(speaking in foreign language)
We're gonna ask the children's choir to come up here
and they will help us to celebrate Christmas
by singing two very old Christmas hymns.
(speaking in foreign language)
Well, let's give them a big hand again.
(audience applauding)
The first Christmas was recorded in the Bible,
in the book of Matthew, Matthew chapter one.
This is how Jesus the Messiah was born.
His mother Mary was engaged to be married to Joseph.
But before the marriage took place,
while she was still a virgin,
she became pregnant through the power of the Holy Spirit.
And Joseph, to whom she was engaged, was a righteous man
and did not want to disgrace her publicly.
So he decided to break the engagement quietly.
As Joseph considered this,
an angel of the Lord appeared to him in a dream.
"Joseph, son of David," the angel said,
"do not be afraid to take Mary as your wife
because the child within her
was conceived by the Holy Spirit.
And she will have a son, and you are to name him Jesus,
for he will save his people from their sins."
(speaking in foreign language)
Now, as you read this portion of the story of Christmas,
this is a profound mystery,
perhaps the most profound mystery of all.
God himself incarnate came to our world,
fully divine, but fully human.
There's something beyond our rationality can explain.
This is the most profound truth in the Bible.
And when Joseph received the news,
God is saying to Joseph,
"My plan is different from your plan.
My will is higher than your will."
Yes, for Joseph, if you can imagine,
he was trying to build his own simple family, right?
Have a good life, have a small family in Israel
to farm or to be a carpenter,
just want to live a normal life.
But God said to him, and to Mary, to this holy family,
he said, "I want to send the Savior through your family."
Now, this is also profound,
because at times you see in this story,
God will act in a way that is different from your plan.
You may have your own plan,
and you may have thought your plan
is the most perfect plan of all,
but God shows up.
Christmas is telling us that God is close to us
and God can do his work.
Something that is higher than your will,
something that is different than your plan.
But again and again, God's way is different.
Though it's different, it is the best.
So Joseph obeyed God and took Mary,
who was conceived by the power of God,
and son was born.
And because of their obedience,
God's saving plan for all of us sinners is fulfilled.
(speaking in foreign language)
the Lord. (speaking in foreign language)
Now if you read this scripture again in 121,
in the book of Matthew, it says,
she will have a son and you are to name him Jesus.
Right?
Name him Jesus.
His name will be Jesus.
(speaking in foreign language)
Now what does it mean?
What does the name Jesus mean?
Now in Hebrew, Jesus will sound like this.
Yeah, sure.
In Greek, it's Yesu.
In Mandarin, it's Yesu, right?
In Cantonese, it's Yesu, right?
(speaking in foreign language)
(audience laughing)
The name Jesus, what does it mean?
It means saving, to rescue, to redeem.
That's why we call him savior.
Because the name Jesus, Yesu,
it means to save us from something.
And the story says, Jesus is gonna save us from sin,
from death, from the power of darkness.
Now as I said before, I know many of us
are facing different challenges
and seeing a lot of different forms
of injustice and oppression.
In the time of Jesus, many people thought that way too,
because they were under the shadow of the Roman Empire.
And the Roman Empire was an oppressive regime.
And today, many of us,
certainly we see some situations similar
to what they had before.
We see a situation that is oppressive
in many other countries, or even in our society.
Because we see all the brokenness in our world.
We see sin and darkness.
Some of the people think if we have the right policy,
if we have the right precedent,
if we have the right political power,
all of these issues will be resolved.
But the Bible cuts through all of these answers
and telling us the root problem is sinfulness.
Is that we are sinful, all of us, living in darkness.
And we need a savior.
And only Jesus himself can save us
from that kind of darkness.
Because until the power of sin is broken,
all changes are superficial.
Only when God came to our world in our heart
and start to transform us,
then our relationships can be reconciled.
Our world can be changed.
And that's why we celebrate Christmas.
And perhaps the story of first Christmas
remains the most profound mystery.
Because on the first Christmas,
this baby, the newborn king, was born,
fully human and fully divine.
And he is the bridge between us and God himself.
Christmas shows us God is near.
Now the year of 2022 is coming to a close.
Perhaps this year is tough and challenging for you.
It's very critical for you.
And my prayer is that we will all turn to God,
knowing that only in Jesus, our newborn king,
we can have true peace, true joy, and true hope.
So as we continue to worship, we will light the candle.
And as we light the candle,
as we pass the light from one to the next neighbor,
and then on and on, as we light up the room,
I want you to say a prayer.
Say a prayer, first of all, for yourself.
Maybe you are facing some difficulties.
Maybe you are facing some issues
that is beyond your ability to solve.
Say a prayer for yourself.
Let God be your God.
Then also say a second prayer
for someone you know who is needy in this season.
Maybe a family member, maybe a friend or relative,
maybe a neighbor.
Say a prayer for them.
May God be with them.
(speaking in foreign language)
So as we continue to worship, we will light the candle
and we'll pass the light from one to the other.
I know you have some candles on your table
and you can get that prepared.
Make sure you get the tray ready.
This is our tradition at UV in our church.
On Christmas Sunday, we will light the candle
and pass the light.
And we will light up the room together.
And this symbolizes the newborn king who has come,
who has come to save us.
He dispels all kinds of darkness
because light always conquers darkness.
(speaking in foreign language)
♪ O holy night ♪
♪ The stars are brightly shining ♪
♪ It is the night of our dear savior's birth ♪
♪ Long lay the world in sin and error pining ♪
♪ Till he appeared and the soul felt its worth ♪
♪ A thrill of hope ♪
♪ The weary world rejoices ♪
♪ For yonder breaks a new and glorious morn ♪
♪ Fall on your knees ♪
♪ Oh hear the angel voices ♪
♪ Amen ♪
♪ Divine ♪
♪ O night when Christ was born ♪
♪ O night divine ♪
♪ O night, O night divine ♪
♪ Truly he talks to one another ♪
♪ His law is love and his gospel is peace ♪
♪ For the slave is our God and in his name ♪
♪ All our precious shall sing ♪
♪ Sweet hymns of joy ♪
♪ In grateful chorus raise we ♪
♪ Let all we believe us praise his holy name ♪
♪ Christ is the Lord ♪
♪ Our praise he sings forever ♪
♪ His power and glory evermore proclaim ♪
♪ Glory evermore proclaim ♪
♪ Evermore proclaim ♪
(gentle music)
♪ Praise his holy name ♪
♪ Christ is the Lord ♪
♪ Our praise his name forever ♪
♪ His power and glory evermore proclaim ♪
♪ Glory evermore proclaim ♪
- 1 John chapter four, for God is love.
God show us how much he love us
by sending his one and only son into the world
so that we might have eternal life through him.
This is real love, not that we love God,
but that he loved us and sent his son as a sacrifice
to take away our sins.
(speaking in foreign language)
This is love.
There's no wonder why Christmas is a time
to give gifts to each other,
to exchange gifts with our friends.
I know we will have a game of white oven later,
but let's hold onto this
because I believe it will be worthwhile
for us to ask ourselves the question.
Now, if you have the opportunity to ask God
for a gift in this season, what would that be?
If you pray to God, you have the opportunity
to grant you one wish, one prayer, what would that be?
What would that be considered a gift for you in this season?
Perhaps you are thinking of a lot of different things,
perhaps a better career, a better future,
a better relationship, a better house, a better car,
or whatever that is better than what you have.
And I believe that God can certainly grant
these good things to all of us.
But here the Bible says,
"God has already granted us the greatest gift."
And this greatest gift is what we are celebrating today.
It's the one and only Son, Jesus Christ,
His salvation, His one and only Son
who will grant us eternal life, life indeed.
But this scripture tells us why does God do this?
Why did God give us His one and only Son?
Because of His love.
The greatest gift is given to us because of His love,
because it is who God is and giving us the best,
the best gift of all.
(speaking in foreign language)