[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Brothers and sisters, good morning.
To begin today, I would like to tell you a very simple story.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
There was a high school boy.
His name is Jimmy.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
He came from a poor family and was very quiet.
Every day, he would walk alone with a large stack of books,
and almost no classmates would talk to him.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In other people's eyes, he was a little bit strange,
almost like a transparent person with a very low presence.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
One day after school, he was carrying a whole stack
of books on his way home, as usual.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Several classmates walked over and suddenly bumped into him
on purpose.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Books and stationery were all scattered
on the ground, everywhere.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
People around him just smiled, and then they
separate ways and walk away.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
At this moment, there was a classmate
standing right beside him.
He could just pretend that he actually
did not see everything happen.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
But he felt a small sense of gratitude.
He thought, should I go over and help?
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
So he went over and scattered them.
Helped Jimmy to pick up his books one by one.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
And asked him, are you OK?
Where do you live?
Do you want to come along with me?
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
It's just a very simple action.
Just walk with him for a while and chat with him for a bit.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Gradually, they'd become friends.
And he invited the boy to play basketball with him
and participate in activities together.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
For this student, that day was just a very small episode
in the day.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
But years later, he suddenly realized
that that day had changed Jimmy's life.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
At the graduation ceremony, Jimmy stood on the stage
and gave a speech.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
He said the reason why he brought all the books home
from school that day was because--
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
It was because he had already prepared to end his life
that weekend.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Books no longer needed to be left at school anymore.
However, that afternoon, when the classmates walked over--
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
He knelt down to help him pick up the books one by one
and walk him home.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
That was the first time he truly felt--
It turns out that there are people in this world who
see me and care about me.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
It's through this gradual acceptance and care that--
This weighed him from taking his own life
and led him down to a completely different path.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Brothers and sisters, what may seem like this
is a very small action to us--
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
A greeting, a smile, a moment of companionship,
this can all be the turning point in one's person's life,
the transition from death to life.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Today, we're going to take a look at Gospel of John.
Let's take a look how God uses seemingly very small things
in our daily life to touch people's heart
and even change their whole life.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In John number two, Jesus did something
that seemed insignificant, yet it revealed the glory of God.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
When I was really young, I heard about this interpretation
of a scripture in church.
Jesus is a God who can change matter,
able to transform water, H2O, into alcohol, C2H5O,
adding many more carbon and hydrogen atoms.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Jesus is truly amazing, a God who can change matter.
However, today, if we consider Jesus' situation
in the Gospel of John and the author's description of Jesus
performing his first miracle--
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
--we will discover that this God is not only
a God who changes matter, but even more so,
a God who changes people's hearts.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Let's look at the first miracle Jesus
performed in Gospel of John.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
On the third day, there was a wedding at Cana in Calili.
The mother of Jesus was there.
Jesus also was invited to the wedding with his disciples.
When the wine ran out, the mother of Jesus said to him,
they have no wine.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
And Jesus said to her, woman, what
does this have to do with me?
My hours has not yet come.
His mother said to the servants, do whatever he tells you.
Now, there were six stone water jars
there for the Jewish rites of purification,
each holding 20 or 30 gallons.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Jesus said to the servant, fill the jars with water.
And they filled them up to the brim.
And he said to them, now, draw some out and take it
to the master of the feast.
So they took it.
When the master of the feast tasted the water,
now it become wine and did not know where it came from,
though the servants who had drawn the water knew it.
And the master of the feast called the bridegroom.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
And said to him, everyone serves the good wine first.
And when people have drunk freely, then the poor wine.
But you have kept the good wine till now.
This, the first of his signs, Jesus did at Cana in Galilee
and manifested his glory.
And his disciples believed in him.
After this, he went down to Capernaum
with his mother and his brothers and his disciples.
And they stayed there for several days.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Why did Jesus' mother said to him, they have no more wine?
And why did Jesus react so strong?
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In Jewish culture at the time, a wedding feast without wine
was a profound humiliation, seen as failure
on the part of the groom's family, a breach of etiquette,
and a social disaster that will be remembered for a lifetime.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Mary, Jesus' mom, was likely a relative or very close friend.
Her being mentioned first and seemingly moving in and out
of the inner court suggests that she
was more concerned with the host's reputation and glory
than others, keenly noticing the underlying difficulties.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
This reflects her initial belief in Jesus' ability to act.
Secondly, her expectation that Jesus could help
restore the host family glory.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Jesus responded, woman, what does this have to do with me?
My time has not come yet.
Mary's expectation was that Jesus' intervention
indirectly influenced Jesus to reveal God's glory.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In the Gospel of John, time is a crucial word.
When mentioned, it's usually associated with glory.
Because Jesus knew that when he performed a miracle,
he would reveal God's glory.
Therefore, Jesus' reaction was quite urgent.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
But what Jesus did next transformed
the most uncleaned water, the most despised water,
into something that would bring glory to his master
and to Jesus himself.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Versus six.
According to the Jewish ritual of purification,
there were six stone jaws placed there.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Some Chinese English translation
rendered this as a stone jaw used for Jewish purification
rituals.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In fact, Jews placed great importance
on cleanliness rituals because they
understand that cleanliness regulations God
gave in Exodus and Leviticus were intended
to show the world that Jewish people belong
to Jehovah and to God.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Therefore, all the derived purification rituals
are meant to show one's relationship with God.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Even today, if you have the opportunity
to visit Western Wall in Jerusalem,
you will see Jews still observing purification
rituals in front of the Western Wall.
There is a hand washing station with a sewer
cup in the basin.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
They use that sewer cup to hold water,
symbolizing the stone jaws of the pest
to clean their hands before going to see God,
thus demonstrating their belonging to God.
Therefore, you can imagine how much importance Jews
place on purification rituals.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
When you came to see God today, did you
get the chance to wash your hands and face?
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Jesus, however, used the stone jaw
used for purification rites to fill them and turn the water
into wine.
This shattered the Jewish and the disciples' preconceived
notion about the purification rites.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
The jaws used for purification were actually
filled with uncleanliness.
Imagine the water in those jaws was
used for washing hands, face, and even feet.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
People came from all directions, traveling long distance
to this wedding feast.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
And at that time, technology wasn't as advanced
as it is now.
Many people weren't wearing shoes.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
You can imagine how filthy and unclean
that water could be, filled with mud.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
But Jesus transformed these most unclean and filthy water
into the finest wine, better than any wine
served at the entire wedding feast.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Here, Jesus not only changed the material itself,
but also shattered the stereotype of cleanliness,
turning the unclean water meant to be received into a tool
to glorify Jesus.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Glorify Jesus.
So on the level of personal spiritual life--
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
These water jars were originally intended for ritual purification,
symbolizing how people use our behavior and religious rituals
to slightly cover up their own defilement.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Jesus, however, turned the water into wine,
symbolizing that he used his own blood and his own life
to become the true source of purity for humanity.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
The most shameful, unspeakable, and unclean parts of our lives,
whether failure, addictions, sins, or broken relationship,
are not forgotten in the gospel, but transformed by him
into good stories that testify to his grace.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In the grace of Christ, we can learn
to surrender our most unbearable moments,
no longer cover them up with religious rituals
or superficial good deeds, but allowing the blood of Jesus
to truly enter and renew us.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
There are some things, people and relationship,
that we might not even want to recall,
feeling they are too painful to look back on.
We might think that the time will heal all the wounds,
that they will simply fade away.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Sometimes we might be able to cover up these things
with outward act of kindness or even righteous, religious
righteous.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
But Jesus' most unexpected action
was to transform these most unclean water,
representing our most unspeakable moments in life,
into an instrument for glorifying God.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
If we are willing to offer it, we
can expect God to transform our unbearable moments in life
into moments and tools for his own glory.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Do you want to do it?
When we talk about work, we expect
God to intervene in our works as well.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
I don't know, starting from when,
we've begun to lose the hope in God's presence in our lives
and work.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Our only hope might be just, let me finish today's work
as quick as possible.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Just like the jewel of gold, even on important occasions
like weddings, we perform numerous purification rites,
just completing these elaborated rites is exhausted itself.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
I don't know starting from when, we've
stopped expecting God to intervene in our work.
It is as if our work has nothing to do with God.
I'm just here to earn money.
I'm just here to need a job to support my family.
Besides that, my job has no other meaning.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
What is the most astonishing here about Jesus
is that he transformed the water used for washing feet, which
is the jewels despised and considered utterly meaningless
into a source of glory for the host and for himself.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Seemingly, he would turn the seemingly meaningless work
in our lives into a means to glorify himself.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
The question is, are you willing to let
God intervene in our lives?
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Or we just simply want God to leave us alone.
Let's have more expectations and think more about how
God can intervene in our work.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In our faith practice, our sinner life must become real.
This water was prepared according
to Jewish ritual of purification and is
a part of the Old Testament ritual system.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Jesus did not use new vessels, but worked directly
in these purification jars, turning the water into wine.
This symbolized that he did not add a bunch of new rules,
but rather directed all the purification, sacrifice,
and festivals of the Old Testament
to a salvation he accomplished on the cross.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
For the church, this sign calls on people
not to merely outwardly observe righteous,
but to enter into the abundant faith in Christ.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Worship, baptism, communion, and fellowship,
if they lose the inner reality of being cleansed and renewed
in Christ, these may be just reduced to mere righteous.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
In this miracle, Jesus invites us
to prepare empty jars in every festival and gathering,
trusting in his intervention and waiting for him
to transform ordinary water and ordinary life
into wine full of grace and joy.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Remember the story that I mentioned at the beginning?
Jimmy stopped his suicidal thoughts
because someone showed him a small act of kindness
by wanting to take care of him.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
This is actually a result of God making
a person's inner life authentic.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Caring for others isn't about external rules
and regulations, but a genuine feeling
from the depth of one's heart.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
God used this small act to save a person's life.
Transforming an ordinary life into a wine full of surprises.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Let's pray together.
Dear Heavenly Father, thank you not only
for changing the material world, but also
for changing our inner lives.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
Let us learn and look forward to you transforming
the hardships and brokenness in our lives
into witness to your glory.
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH]
We pray in the name of Lord Jesus, amen.