Hey family, here we are again enjoying this beautiful Chicago winter. You know
for a while I thought we were gonna have a really mild winter this year and it
seemed that way all the way up until about the middle of January and wasn't
that cold, wasn't much snow, seemed like things weren't gonna be that bad and
then winter just came roaring back and it has not let up since. It has been very
cold. We've had a crazy amount of snow that we're all trying to dig out from
under and we're shoveling snow every day and I know it's probably been a little
bit tiring and challenging for all of us and I'm praying for you as you go
through it, not just the challenges of shoveling snow and encountering those
things but also just kind of the emotional challenges of being isolated
and stuck in the house and not able to do things compounded with already being
isolated because of the pandemic. I know sometimes in the winter it just seems
dark and dreary and so I'm praying for you all as you encounter just all this
winter weather that you'll stay encouraged and that you'll be able to
enjoy it at least a little bit. And we're once again gonna be looking in Matthew
today at the Sermon on the Mount. Today we're looking at Matthew chapter 7 so I
just want to start off by commending you and encouraging you to give yourself a
little round of applause or later on today make yourself a little trophy
something like that because you've come a long way. The Sermon on the Mount is
three chapters in the book of Matthew, Matthew 5, 6, and 7. It's the longest
continuous sermon that's recorded in the Gospels, the longest continuous sermon of
Jesus. There's a lot of content there and we've been going slowly through it
taking it a verse or two at a time and so I know it's taken us a while to get
through it. So I commend you for sticking with me, I commend you for your patience
and perseverance and Matthew 7 is the last chapter we're starting in this week
so there's a lot at the end of the tunnel, we're getting close to the end
but Matthew chapter 7 is full of a lot of really good truth for us. I want us to
really dig into this chapter and enjoy learning what God has for us and I know
for me studying through the Sermon on the Mount it's it's really kind of life
changing. There's so much deep and powerful truth in it and it's just been
so transformative and such a blessing for me. I pray it's been the same for you
and this Matthew chapter 7 is no different. In Matthew chapter 7 the first
section of this passage Jesus is really talking about judging others and so
that's what we're going to be talking about today, judging others and this is a
really important topic and it's really important in our culture and so we're
going to take our time and look at it over the next few weeks, go through it
kind of slowly and try to really discover the truth that God has for us
on this topic and really get a healthy understanding of what Jesus is saying in
these verses. Today we're just going to look at Matthew chapter 7 verse 1 and
verse 2 so let's read these together. Jesus says, "Judge not that you be not
judged for with the judgment you pronounce you will be judged and with
the measure you use it will be measured to you." Now these verses are very well
known Bible verses. Matthew 7 1 is often said to be one of the most popular Bible
verses in the entire Bible. A lot of people know this verse and sometimes
people say it's the most popular verse of people who are not Christians, people
who are not a part of the family of God because they love to quote it to say, "Hey
don't judge, you can't judge, Jesus said don't judge lest you be judged." So you
may have heard this verse before, maybe you've heard it as someone has said it
to you or maybe you've heard someone on TV say it or something like that. It's a
verse that people say a lot but it's also misunderstood in a lot of ways and
it's difficult to interpret. And what I believe and what I want us to examine
today is that Jesus here is not saying that we should not judge at all but he's
saying that we should exercise right judgment when we judge and what he's
really calling out is having a judgmental attitude. He does not want us
to have a judgmental attitude and what I think what most people think of when
they say judging is really a judgmental attitude. Obviously a lot of people in
our culture have a very negative perception of judgment and of judging
and so a lot of people say, "Well you can't judge others." But I think a lot of
times what people are talking about is actually a judgmental attitude that is
proud or that is hypocritical or that is self-righteous and those are definitely
things that Jesus wants us to avoid and we're going to talk about that over the
next few weeks. But Jesus is not saying that we shouldn't judge or that we
shouldn't make judgments or that we shouldn't exercise discernment. I really
don't think Jesus is saying that in this verse. And if you just have such a
negative connotation with with the idea of judgment that it's hard for you to say
the word or think about it judging something or some circumstance, then you
can just use the word discernment. Discernment is a biblical word and I
think it's a really good word for us to think about. Discernment refers to being
able to see or recognize or distinguish or apprehend things and so discernment
is a synonym of judging and it's really an important quality for us
Christians to have and to be able to exercise. So if you're uncomfortable with
the concept of judging then you can talk about discernment. I'm going to use
those two terms almost interchangeably as we discuss this. And I think to start
it's helpful to think about what judgment is. We can say, "Well judgment is
when you judge something, when you make a decision about something."
And that's true, but I think on a deeper level it helps us to understand that
judgment is ultimately comparison to a standard. It's when we compare something
to a standard and say, "Does this line up with the standard? Is this right
according to the standard?" And for Christians, for followers of Jesus, for
the subjects of the kingdom that we've talked about in the Sermon on the Mount,
that standard ultimately comes from God. It's God's truth. For people who are not
followers of Jesus, that standard could be a lot of different things. It could be
their own feelings, it could be what someone else has told them, it could be
all types of different things. It could be cultural values. And for believers and
people in the church, a lot of times that's true too. Instead of sticking to
the standard of God's truth, we start to hold on to a lot of different cultural
values or our own feelings or what someone else has taught us. And that's
not always healthy. A lot of times that can lead to really unhealthy attitudes
and unhealthy judgments. And that can lead to that judgmental attitude that we
want to avoid and that Jesus is calling us to avoid in this passage. So we want
to remind ourselves and to always be mindful of the fact that when we are
thinking about discerning something or judging something, we're talking
about comparing it to God's truth and to God's standard. And remember that God's
judgment is always rooted in God's justice. God has a standard of justice
that is above and beyond ours and God's justice transcends our idea of justice.
And we need to understand that. That God's judgment is always rooted in God's
standard of justice, not ours. And we also need to understand that God's justice is
rooted in His love. And so even when God exercises judgment, when He compares
something to a standard, when He asks us to compare ourselves to a standard,
that's always rooted in love for us. God does not do that to punish us. God does
not do that to expose our weakness or our failing. God does that because He
loves us and He wants to grow us and strengthen us and transform us into
something more beautiful than what we have been in the past. God's judgment and
justice are always rooted in His love. Now you might look at this verse on the
face of it and say, "Hey, judge not that you be not judged." I don't see anything
in there about having a judgmental attitude. So why am I saying that Jesus
is calling out having a judgmental attitude, not just calling out exercising
judgment in this passage? I want to remind you of how we interpret passages
in the Bible. We talked about this with some of the other passages in the
Sermon on the Mount that are a little bit more difficult to interpret. There's
a lot of passages in the Bible we may look at and say, "I don't fully
understand it," or "it seems confusing," or "is it saying this because it seems like
that doesn't agree with other parts of the Bible?" And so there's a lot of
principles of biblical interpretation. We went through some of those when we
talked about some of those other passages, so we're not going to go
through all of them again today. But I'm just going to point to a couple that we
can really see in this passage. And that is it's always important to examine
verses in their context, in the context of the verses around them. And that's
really helpful to look at the passage and see what the passage is saying. And
it's also helpful to examine verses in light of other scripture and other
verses and passages throughout scripture and compare and say, "Okay,
did these agree?" And that helps us to interpret a verse that may seem unusual
to us when we first see it. And this is one of those verses. If we just look at
Matthew 7, we say, "Judge not that you be not judged." Jesus is clearly
saying that we should never exercise judgment. But when we look at the context
of this passage, this section in Matthew 7, Jesus is clearly talking about judging
others and is clearly not saying that we shouldn't do it. He's just calling us to
do it in the right way. So in verse 6, he's talking about judging and knowing
when it's appropriate to say something or to reveal something to someone else.
That's an issue of judgment. In verses 15 to 20, he's talking about identifying
false teachers by the fruits and by the actions of their life. That's clearly
something where he's telling us to exercise judgment and discernment. So the
context helps us to see that, but the rest of scripture helps us to see that
too. Throughout the scripture in the Old and New Testament, God calls on us to
discern, to exercise judgment. He just wants us to do it in the right way.
There's even a verse in John 7, verse 24, where Jesus says, "Do not judge by
appearances, but judge with right judgment." So again, I think the focus of
this passage is not that we should not judge at all, but it's rather that we
should not have a judgmental attitude. And having a judgmental attitude is
really unhealthy. It's really terrible. It causes a lot of problems. And having a
judgmental attitude is when we make judgments or just try to discern things
with a spirit of pride and arrogance, when we don't exercise grace towards
other people, when we don't see how much God has forgiven us, when we don't, we're
not meek, when we're condemning of other people, when we try to sentence other
people or hold other people accountable, when we judge based upon what we can see
and think that we know someone's intent or heart based upon the outward
appearance, all those things are wrong. And they lead to hypocrisy and
self-righteousness and all of these hurtful things. And sadly, a lot of that
type of judgmental attitude is found in the church and has been found in the
church. And so Jesus is not saying that he doesn't want us to exercise discernment.
He's saying he wants us to avoid that judgmental attitude. And we're gonna
examine all of those things over the next few weeks. But today specifically, I
want us to start off by looking at some unhealthy attitudes about judgment that
we probably have on some level. And these are attitudes in the church. They're also
attitudes in culture at large. And sometimes they can kind of slip into our
way of living and our way of thinking and we don't even realize it. But they
can cause us to be unhealthy in different ways. So the first thing I want
us to think about is just the attitude that, you know, no judgment at all is
acceptable. And this is a pretty common cultural attitude that it's wrong to
judge anything or anybody. It's unkind in some way. And it can seep into our
life. Sometimes in the church as believers we can find ourselves saying,
"Is it okay for me to even make a decision about certain things or to even
try to discern what's right or what's wrong?" And I think it's clear that
judgment is a necessary part of life. It's an essential part of our daily life.
You probably already made a lot of judgments this morning. When you woke up,
you probably looked at the alarm clock and based upon what time it was, you made
a judgment decision as to whether or not you could go back to sleep or whether
you had to get up and get ready to do whatever it was you wanted to do today,
including get on your computer or your phone or your device so that you could
view the stream. You made a judgment decision. If you went outside or
if you're going to go outside later, you'll make a judgment decision then.
You'll look at your phone or something else that tells you the temperature or
maybe you'll stick your head out the door and just determine the temperature
that way and you'll make a judgment decision based upon that about what you
need to wear in order to stay safe today. And so all of us make judgment decisions
all of the time and ultimately they're essential for our life. We couldn't
function without them. We have to make them in order to be safe and that's
important. And we have to realize that the reality of our world as God has
created it is that not all actions have the same outcome. And that's something
that we don't always want to admit. We want to try to make a world in our own
minds where even if we do something that's not a good idea or it's
unhealthy, it's still going to turn out great for us. But we can't make a world
like that. We can't make our world be that way because that's not the world
God created. God created a world where not all actions have the same outcome.
And to go back to the illustration I used just a moment ago, if you go outside
on a day like today in shorts and a t-shirt, that is not going to have the
same outcome as if you go outside in a warm coat. Those are two different
actions and they're going to feel very different depending upon which one you
choose. And so making judgments helps you choose the action that's going to be
healthy and right for your life and that's a good thing. We need to do that
as humans and God wants us to do that. And the reality is that all people make
those types of judgments. So saying that, "Well, we can't make any type of
judgments. We can't discern anything that to even try is unhealthy or unkind
or something like that." That's not really a good argument because all of us have
to make those types of judgments about life just in order to function and to be
safe and to do all the things that we need to do. But maybe we say, "Okay, so
yeah, we have to make judgments about our daily life so that we can function. We
get that." But the problem is when we begin to judge other people and we begin
to maybe say something that is not affirming of someone else. Well, again, I
would say that that's an unhealthy attitude towards judgment because we
have to discern things and make decisions about other people. That's a
reality of life. Every relationship that you're in involves making some level of
discernment and judgment in that relationship. Why? Because relationships
involve trust. And to trust someone you have to have some knowledge about them.
And so any relationship, whether it's a friendship or someone at work or someone
at school or a much deeper relationship like a marriage, is going to involve
communication. It's going to involve response to that communication. And during
that process you're discerning, you're saying, "Hey, is this person someone that
I can trust? If I share the secret with them, are they going to share it with
someone else? If I become transparent or vulnerable in this way, will I be safe?"
Those are judgment decisions and all of us do that in relationships. All of us
have to make decisions about who we can trust and who we can share our life with
and what level we're going to share things with. And there's nothing wrong
with that. That's a necessary part of living life and forming relationships in
the world that we live in. And ultimately relationships would be impossible without
some form of discernment and judgment. All of us understand that in our
relationships. And again, not all actions have the same outcome. So at some point
we have to be able to discern what's going on in the life of someone else. A
simple example of this is like driving. If you pull up to a four-way stop or a
red light, one of the things that you do is you're looking at the other drivers
as they come up to the stop. And even if you have the right-of-way and it's your
turn to go, if you see a driver that isn't slowing down and looks like
they're going to blow through the stop sign or that they're going to go through
the light even though it's red, then you make a judgment call to protect yourself
and anyone who's riding in the car that you're in. And you say, "I'm not going to
go even though I have the right-of-way, even though it's my turn to go. I'm not
going to go because I see the action of someone else and it could harm me or it
could harm the people around me." That's a judgment call and we have to make
those. They're a part of our life. And even in the last year with the pandemic,
we've seen ourselves as humans making so many judgment calls where we look at
other people and their actions and say, "Hey, are their actions going to protect my
health? Are their actions going to protect the health of the people around me?" And
we make decisions based upon that. We say, "Okay, well here's what I need to do
because of what I see someone else doing." Or, "Here's a situation that I can't be
in or something that I can't go to because it might endanger my health." And
so the reality is we're all making those types of judgments and discernment-based
decisions all the time, even when they involve the actions of other people. And
that's not wrong. It's okay to make those types of decisions. Again, what we want
to avoid is being judgmental in a wrong way towards other people. So maybe we say,
"Well, okay, I get that we need to make judgments in life and even some
judgments about the actions of others are acceptable, but the problem is moral
judgments that when we judge things as good or bad, that's really a problem." And
I think that's a criticism that has been leveled at Christians and at the church
a lot that people have said the problem with Christians is that they make all
these moral judgments and they're always trying to say what's good and bad and
that's really the problem. And it just turns people off and it
makes people upset. Well again, I would say that that argument's not really a
great argument to say that no moral judgments are acceptable. The reality is
that everyone has a moral standard in their life. And honestly, sometimes we can
see our moral standard or someone else's moral standard much better by our
reactions than by our actions. What do I mean by that? Well, I mean, we might
say, "You know what? I get really irritated at someone else because they judge me and
I took some of their food out of the fridge, my family member, and they're so
mad at me about it. What's the big deal? It's just a little bit of food." We might
say, "It's not a big deal. My actions aren't that much of a problem." But
our standard is revealed by our reaction. If someone takes something from us, that's
when we reveal our true standard. We might say, "Oh, my standards are easy." But
when someone wrongs us, how do we react? And when someone steals from us, suddenly
we're angry and they need to be held accountable and they need to
pay everything back to the last penny. A lot of times we can see our moral
standards more by our reactions than by our actions. And the reality is everybody
has a moral standard. Everybody has things that they think are right and
things that they think are wrong. And everybody makes moral judgments.
Everybody looks at things in life and says, "Hey, this is right or this is wrong."
We again have seen that so much in the last year in our politics. You know, as I
said, a lot of times this claim about moral judgment not being good or healthy
is leveled against Christians and people in the church. But we've seen a lot in
the last year, a lot of moral judgments. People saying what is good, what is bad,
what is right, what is wrong. And the majority of those people are not
Christians. They're not people in the church. Many of them are not even
religious people, but they've made very strong statements about what is right
and what is wrong. And that shows us that all of us have some standard of morality,
some standard of what we think is right and is wrong. And we're willing to make
judgments based on that standard. So the real question is, what standard are we
going to compare to? It's not a question of whether or not we're going to compare
things to a standard, whether or not we think anything is right or wrong. All of
us have some things that we think are wrong and off-limits for humans. And all
of us have other things that we think are good and healthy for humans. So
that's not the question. The real question is, what standard are we
comparing to? Whose standard are we going to use? And as I said at the beginning,
for followers of Jesus, our standard is God's truth. For other people, there's a
lot of different standards. But for followers of Jesus, we want to go back to
God's truth. And we have to understand as believers that making moral judgments
and discernments is actually an essential part of our faith. Again and
again in Scripture, we're called to not be deceived. We're called to cling to the
truth. We're called to be obedient to God. We're called to live righteously. All
this stuff. Well, how do we do that if we are not able to make moral judgments and
decisions that involve discernment, decisions that involve seeing and
recognizing and distinguishing and apprehending right from wrong? And so
ultimately, we have to make moral judgments in life. And Jesus is not
banning us from doing that. He's just calling us to do it in the right way and
in a healthy way and in a way that is not unkind to others. In a way that's
respectful of others. And as we said at the beginning, in a way that is rooted
and grounded in God's love and grace. God's love and grace for us and God's
love and grace for others in the world. So like I said, I want us to close out
here seeing that Jesus is calling us to exercise right judgment and to not have
a judgmental attitude. Next week, we're gonna get more into the specifics of how
to avoid having a judgmental attitude. But for this week, I just want us to see
how important it is that we are able to discern things in life and that we're
able to make healthy judgments and healthy decisions and that we are able
to discern what is right and wrong. What's good for us and what's not good
for us. And that we're able to look at the world around us and have some
clarity about what's happening. That's so important and Jesus is calling us to
that in this verse. And that's something that we should desire and that's
something that we should practice and something that we should grow in as
believers and as followers of Jesus. We should grow in our ability to discern.
It's something that we can practice and it's a skill that we can develop by
God's grace. And so we want to do that. Let's pray. God, thank you that you give
us the ability to discern things, to see, and to distinguish, and to recognize. And
God, we are so weak and limited in ability, God. Our vision is so short and
so God, we need your help. We need your help so much in discernment, in making
judgments, in understanding what's right and wrong. And so God, I pray that you
would help us. That you would help us to grow in our ability to do that. That you
would help us to grow in our ability to look at your word and to see what your
word is saying about the issues of our life. That you would help us to grow in our
sensitivity to listening to the Holy Spirit and how you want to use the Holy
Spirit to speak to us. God, please help us to grow in discernment and in making
right judgments so that we can distinguish right from wrong in our
lives and we can have loving relationships with others. And God,
please help us to not be judgmental and unkind and disrespectful in any way to
the people around us, God. Help us to exercise right judgment and right
discernment as we go through life. In Jesus' name, Amen.