(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
Pharisees.
Religious leaders.
(speaking in foreign language)
Hello.
Okay?
(speaking in foreign language)
, right?
(laughing)
(speaking in foreign language)
Yay, got it!
Okay.
(speaking in foreign language)
'Cause it's bubbles on it.
This should be a naan.
Is it naan?
Yay!
(speaking in foreign language)
I got it.
Nice job, assistant.
Next one.
(speaking in foreign language)
Seven grain, 21 grain.
It is.
The whole wheat grain bread.
(speaking in foreign language)
Yes, I got it.
(laughing)
Next one.
(speaking in foreign language)
What is this?
It feels slimy.
Oh no, it's slime bread.
(speaking in foreign language)
It must be Chinese.
But it feels like slime.
Hold on.
(speaking in foreign language)
Tastes like a ball of bao.
But it doesn't have the ball of bao crust.
But it's slimy in the middle.
Don't worry, I'm the only one eating this bao.
It's slime in the middle.
What kind of bao is it?
Okay, I have to take a look, okay?
I'm gonna take a look.
I forfeit this round, I take a look, hold on.
Oh, I got it!
It's a (speaking in foreign language)
So usually, when I go to the bakery,
(speaking in foreign language)
It's a little bit oblong.
What threw me off, it's circular.
(speaking in foreign language)
Tricky, tricky assistant.
Or cocktail bun.
(speaking in foreign language)
Woo-hoo!
This is good.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay.
Is actually midnight snack or supper.
(speaking in foreign language)
It's happening real time.
Last supper.
(speaking in foreign language)
So start with the last supper.
Now imagine.
(speaking in foreign language)
Is that it?
That's it.
Bread.
Just bread.
(speaking in foreign language)
Bread and wine.
That's how we're starting today's story.
(speaking in foreign language)
The last supper.
Passover.
(speaking in foreign language)
Last supper.
The last supper.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay, time for supper.
Right?
(speaking in foreign language)
the Bible.
No way!
(speaking in foreign language)
Really good friend, right?
Really good friend.
Let's just see what happens, right?
(speaking in foreign language)
He's God's son.
He probably knows.
Actually, not probably.
He definitely knows.
(speaking in foreign language)
Right?
Basically, it's a group of CFO, basically.
(speaking in foreign language)
(sighing)
By Judas law.
(speaking in foreign language)
Tricky, tricky.
Midnight snack.
(speaking in foreign language)
Next time, we got Peter and Judas.
Before.
(speaking in foreign language)
His purpose.
Prophet.
(speaking in foreign language)
None of us.
So that's why we're starting here.
(speaking in foreign language)
Little side fact.
Bread of life.
(speaking in foreign language)
Deep, right?
So, we'll unpack it as we continue.
(speaking in foreign language)
Time at home.
Name that bao.
Okay?
(speaking in foreign language)
Who can name the most baos, right?
Right?
(speaking in foreign language)
Me against you.
Miss Rebecca.
(speaking in foreign language)
From all the baos you can think of.
Okay, ready?
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay?
Bao.
(speaking in foreign language)
Okay.
Bao.
(speaking in foreign language)
It's really a bao, just doesn't have the bao in it.
(laughing)
(speaking in foreign language)
Mediterranean food, you know, pita.
Is that bao?
That's why (speaking in foreign language)
Hey kids, Chinese time.
Chinese time.
(speaking in foreign language)
I know.
But it's not easy.
(speaking in foreign language)
But bao, like (speaking in foreign language)
like the hamburger, it's kind of like a sandwich.
(speaking in foreign language)
As you can hear, sandwich, (speaking in foreign language)
phonetically, (speaking in foreign language)
Sandy witch.
So, (speaking in foreign language)
That's why it's called a bao, right?
Like (speaking in foreign language)
isn't actually a sandwich bao
or like a (speaking in foreign language)
It's like a dumpling.
But (speaking in foreign language)
Wrapped around.
(speaking in foreign language)
Wrapped present.
Right?
Hello (speaking in foreign language)
Thank you so much.
Bye.
(upbeat music)