(speaking in foreign language)
- Bless the Lord.
Bless the Lord.
(speaking in foreign language)
, goodness of God. (speaking in foreign language)
Goodness of, goodness of God.
(speaking in foreign language)
An Anatomy of All the Parts of the Soul.
Spiritual blindness.
(speaking in foreign language)
Do's and don'ts.
Do not be conformed.
(speaking in foreign language)
Passive.
Passively.
(speaking in foreign language)
Be transformed.
So that you may prove.
(speaking in foreign language)
Fanny Crosby.
Worship is one of the most, one of the important act
in a life of discipleship.
(speaking in foreign language)
(soft piano music)
♪ Bless the Lord, oh my soul ♪
♪ Oh my soul, worship his holy name ♪
♪ Sing like never before, oh my soul ♪
♪ I worship your holy name ♪
♪ The sun comes up, it's a new day dawning ♪
♪ It's time to sing your song again ♪
♪ Whatever may pass, let whatever lies before me ♪
♪ Let me be singing when the evening comes ♪
♪ Bless the Lord ♪
♪ Bless the Lord, oh my soul ♪
(speaking in foreign language)
♪ Worship his holy name ♪
♪ Oh my soul, I worship your holy name ♪
♪ I worship your holy name ♪
♪ You're rich ♪
♪ You're rich in love and your soul's due anger ♪
♪ Your name is great and your heart is kind ♪
♪ For all your goodness I will keep on singing ♪
♪ 10,000 reasons for my heart to find ♪
♪ Bless the Lord ♪
♪ Bless the Lord, oh my soul ♪
♪ Oh my soul, worship his holy name ♪
♪ Sing like never before, oh my soul ♪
♪ I worship your holy name ♪
♪ And on that day ♪
♪ And on that day when my strength is failing ♪
♪ The angels meet and my time has come ♪
♪ Still my soul will sing your praise unending ♪
♪ 10,000 reasons and forever more ♪
(speaking in foreign language)
♪ Bless the Lord, oh my soul ♪
♪ Oh my soul, worship his holy name ♪
♪ Sing like never before, oh my soul ♪
♪ I worship your holy name ♪
♪ Bless the Lord, oh my soul ♪
♪ Oh my soul, worship his holy name ♪
♪ Sing like never before, oh my soul ♪
♪ I worship your holy name ♪
♪ Lord, I worship your holy name ♪
(speaking in foreign language)
I'll see you guys soon. Ciao.