(Chinese)
(Cantonese)
I can sleep until 2 or 3 am
I use this retaliation tool to treat myself
I don't know if you have the same feeling
It's exactly because I see my own work is so hard
I really want to use this tool to reduce the stress
The insomnia brought by this tool is to bring some compensation to my soul
I don't know if you have experienced this kind of life
We are so tired that we can only pay attention to our own stress
We use the tool to satisfy ourselves
Although we read the Bible every day
But we seem to not see or experience God's compassion
Not experiencing his understanding
The title of today's lecture is "Come and See"
I want to use the story of the trumpet leaf being called
To see how God lets people experience themselves
The text is in the PowerPoint
Let's read together
1, 2, 3
One day Jesus wanted to go to Galilee
He found Philae and said to her, "Follow me"
Philae was the wife of Archbishop of Barsuch, and was from the town of Andalusia
Philae found the trumpet leaf and said to her,
"What Moses wrote in the Law and what the ancestors wrote
We have seen it, and it is the son of Joseph, the son of Nazareth, Jesus"
The trumpet leaf said to her,
"Is Nazareth a good place to be?"
Philae said, "You see"
Jesus saw the trumpet leaf coming to her
And said to her, "Look, this is a man of Israel
He has no evil in his heart"
The trumpet leaf said to her,
"How do you know me?"
Jesus said to her,
"Philae said, 'I have called you,
and you are under the tree of the fruit of the woods,
and I have seen you'"
The trumpet leaf said to her,
"You are the son of God, and you are the king of Israel"
Jesus said to her,
"Because I am under the tree and I have seen you,
do you believe that you will see greater things than this?"
She said, "I am telling you again
that you will see the heaven opening
and the messenger of God coming to the people"
Let us pray together
God, we thank you for preparing our hearts,
our ears, and our eyes
so that we can speak at this time
so that we can see how you speak to us
especially when you protect the mouth of the child
When I preach,
let us see how you lead us
We thank you, we pray in the name of Jesus Christ, Amen
The background of today's story
is the story that took place on the way to the Galilee
According to John's record,
Jesus received two disciples,
one was called Andrew and the other was Peter
The next day,
he called Philae
and on the same day, he met with the trumpet leaf
Who was the trumpet leaf?
The trumpet leaf seemed to be a friend of Philae
Philae had just decided to follow Jesus
He said, "Follow me" and immediately followed
Jesus
He hurried to the trumpet leaf
to tell him a good news
that Philae had arrived
Philae was a big news to the people at that time
Because in the New Testament,
although the Jews had their own territory,
they did not have military power
nor any real autonomy
Under this pressure,
everyone was looking forward to God's promise
to execute the promise
that God would send a mighty king to save them from the trap
Generally, the Jews believed that the Savior
would use military power
to help the Israelites rebuild the long-term security of the land
So it is not hard to imagine
that when Philae was talking about his arrival,
he was very excited
He wanted to tell the trumpet leaf the good news
He also said it very clearly
He said, "We have seen it. He is the son of Joseph,
the son of Nazareth, Jesus"
I wonder if we are all excited like this in the beginning
Would we be so excited to tell others
to witness how we experienced the love of God?
How did the trumpet leaf respond?
He said, "Nazareth?
What else is there to tell?"
Why did the trumpet leaf look down on Nazareth?
Did the place offend him?
Today, Nazareth is a tourist attraction
But it used to be a small village with no reputation
on a small mountain in Galilee
And the Bible also mentions
where Nitzah was born
She was born in Bethlehem
Bethlehem is a fertile land with abundant food
and close to Jerusalem, the political center
She was the queen of David
Nazareth is a poor and unpopular place
How could she be the queen of Jerusalem?
On the other hand, there is a story about the trumpet leaf
Why did he not believe it?
Because he was saved
He was saved
By what?
Because people in the past
would sometimes live their lives under the name of savior
They tried to overthrow the Roman regime
but they often failed
For Nazareth,
is this a message?
Is this a news that deceives people's hopes?
Yes, Nazareth's suspicion of the testimony of Philae
or the fact that she has a bias
or that she does not dare to hold on to the news of Nitzah
But it seems that her suspicions are reasonable
Because when faced with suspicion, Philae did not respond
She did not try to defend herself
Her response was only three words
She said, "You come and see"
The original text is also three words
Let me read it
"Er ko kai ide"
Yes
"Come and see"
It is really translated like this
It is a word with two similar meanings
If translated into Chinese, it is "Come and see"
What does it mean?
In fact, Philae meant
"I have no answer to your question, Nazareth"
"Why don't you come and see for yourself?"
"I will go with you"
This reflects that Philae has 100% confidence
Even if she has no absolute answer
she still believes in Jesus who touched people's hearts
She will personally respond to Nathaniel's question
And Nathaniel really agreed
He followed Philae to see Jesus
to see if the Nazarethite is really coming to Cairo
He probably did not expect that this journey would change his life
Then he said, "Jesus saw Nathaniel walking over and he said to him,
'Look, this man of Israel has no deceit in his heart'
Nathaniel finally saw Jesus
But it was unexpected that Jesus could
express his true nature in front of everyone
and praised him for being a man of Israel
who has no deceit in his heart
Here, you might think of the name "Israel"
It comes from the Arabic word "Arabic"
It is the one that is related to the Bible
The Arabs have used false names to describe Jesus
They have lied to his brother, his father, and his uncle
So here, he said that Nathaniel is an Israeli herald
but he has no pre-existing deceit and fraud
How can this be considered as a praise?
Also, Jesus' praise is not a compliment
If it is a compliment
Nathaniel would not respond, "How do you know me?"
For example, since I was a kid
I have always liked to use my phone
I would watch a lot of IG reels to see how people are taking care of their kids
It turns out that encouraging babies is a lot of learning
It turns out that the praise on the surface
like saying that babies are good, babies are good, babies are great
But it is not enough to encourage babies to put in the effort
and say that babies are good, babies are great
It is not enough to help them, but instead, it harms them
Such false praise will actually hinder the development and growth of babies
What do I want to say?
I want to say that Jesus' praise has a point
It is a very important point
God's praise to Nathaniel is not on the surface
It is directly to his heart
It is not a praise that he is a good person
Or this is the virtue that Nathaniel has been working hard for his whole life
It is the theme of his life
At this moment, Nathaniel was very surprised
Because Jesus really spoke the truth about his inner self
Jesus and I have not met each other
He knows me so well, and knows me so well
Where do you know me from?
Jesus replied, "When Philip has not called you yet,
I saw you under the fig tree."
What does it mean?
What is Nathaniel doing under the fig tree?
In tradition, the rabbis like to be under the tree
because it is hot and there are trees
to preach, to read the Bible, to think, and to pray
Is Nathaniel the same?
The Bible does not explain
We do not know what happened
But what we are certain of is that under the fig tree
is a very important key
This keyword, plus the context of the story
can actually make Nathaniel surrender
What is the key to this door?
Or is this a secret between Nathaniel and the Almighty God?
Only he and Nathaniel know
Jesus is the son of God, and he is very powerful
He knows where Nathaniel has been before
He has knowledge of space and time
But what is even more powerful is his vision
that can change people's minds
In fact, this passage emphasizes the vision
You see there are three visions in the book of Hallelujah
In fact, the whole passage has seven visions
But this one has three
All are about Jesus seeing Nathaniel
Even before Nathaniel opened his mouth
Jesus had seen him, recognized him
Sisters, what does seeing God's face bring you today?
Excitement? Surprised? Or unease?
Maybe we think that our hearts are so dark
I have been in the final turn of the Lord for so many years
Jesus, my Lord, will you be disappointed?
Will you dislike me? Will you be angry with me?
Or, God, I am doing well now
I have a job, a relationship, a friend, a family, everything is going well
You and I are just right
The church is still going on, the dedication is still there
But what moved me before
Don't let me see it again, I don't want to see it again
I don't want to respond to you, God
You'd better not find me, don't see me
It turns out that being seen by God
seems to bring some uncertainty
But we should know that seeing God
is actually a more abundant meaning
In the Old Testament, seeing God
is related to the need of the persecutors
and the meaning of salvation
I remember last week we went to the church to train
A React team leader took us to see a scripture
He said the 2nd chapter of the book of Ezekiel
Brother brought us to see how God saved Moses
He saved the whole Israeli people
The whole plan was based on God seeing God in person
Even in the book of Genesis
If you remember, the man named Haggab
He was an Egyptian priest
He was driven away by Sarah
God saw his suffering
and allowed him to protect him
God's grace moved Haggab
and moved him to call Jehovah the God of seeing
The React team brought me here to sing a song
It's about seeing God
I've never heard of it, but it's a good match
You all know it, it's 139
It says here, "My body is not yet formed
Your eyes have long seen God
Your days, my last day
Are all in your hands, writing down your will
How precious your thoughts are
How abundant your prayers are"
Can you see it?
God's vision is not a cold, frozen system
It's not a boss who gives people money
That's right, God sees the evil that people do
He will judge people according to justice
But for us, God's people
Our citizens
God does not use fear to mislead us
Instead, he uses his knowledge of superhuman
and his insight into people
to arrange the best for our beloved children
He calls us to rely on him when he knows what to do
It's like I mentioned my baby
My son is learning to walk
He hasn't walked yet
I don't know if he can walk today
He's good at holding things and moving them around
Sometimes he's very naughty, playing with electric wires
He's like a little baby
My dad is always watching him work
and checking if he's in danger
He's very good at electric wires
He can even pull out the cable
and snap it off
He's very scared
My dad is observing him
and checking if he's in danger
What would he do in an emergency?
He would run away, right?
Would he let him touch him?
Is God like this?
He watches us work
He protects us in an emergency
and even runs away
Sisters
God's watching over us
is a full of love and respect
When Nathan went to Jesus
He was wearing a lot of chains and suspicions
and even disbelief
Jesus did not give up on him
Because God's watching over him
is not a weakness
On the contrary, God saw
how Nathan
even in this weakness
still responded
"Come and see"
In the weakness
he still responded
"Come and see"
Now, Nathan has experienced this hardship
This knowledge
this knowledge of transmission
even shocked him to say
"This man in front is Laban, the son of God, the king of Israel"
Each of these sentiments is a huge amount
It's like the question at the beginning
"Is it possible that Nathan is a Nazarene?"
has become unimportant
Do we have anything that keeps us close to Jesus?
Like Nathan, is there anything we don't understand?
I encourage you, sisters
to carry the question in your heart
"Come and see"
Take a look
Because Jesus is calling us
"Come and you will see"
Go forward and take a look
Test Jesus
Open up your life
to experience this faith of walking and seeing
"Come and see"
The story is almost at the end
Jesus' response to Nathan
is very encouraging
He continues
"For I say, because I saw you in the fruit of the fruitless fruit,
you will see greater things than these
He also said, I tell you,
you will see the heaven opening,
and the witness of God coming down on the Son of Man"
What does this mean?
What does greater things mean?
What does heaven opening mean?
What does the witness of God mean?
Coming down on the Son of Man?
Actually, Jesus is quoting an old scripture
in the Old Testament
When he was dreaming, he saw the sky ladder
This is in the 28th chapter of the book of Genesis
If you have time, you can take a look
There is an image
When he was dreaming, he saw the sky ladder
The witness of God came down on the Son of Man
After that, the Archon thought, "Wow, God is so powerful
He is here, I didn't know that"
He changed the place to Bethel
which means the house of God
Simply put, this dream is a powerful spiritual experience for the Archon
It allows the Archon to experience the presence of God
It is a blessing to the people on earth
Jesus redrew this picture
But the description is a bit different
Can you see it?
One is a ladder, the other is a Son of Man
The Son of Man, in the book of Genesis, is talking about Nehemiah
Actually, it is talking about Jesus himself
So the witness of God came down on Jesus
Jesus used this example to prove that he is the one who is the witness of God
He is the bridge between man and God
If we use John's word, Jesus is the road
In the Old Testament, God told the angel about the miracle
Now, Nehemiah appears
He is the ultimate miracle
Jesus is the miracle
The so-called "reincarnation"
It means a new era has begun
If we look at the Bible, the first thing we see is the image of Jesus
The bigger thing is the signs of Jesus
We are all familiar with the 5-2-2, the 5,000-man-servant, the water-changing wine, the resurrection of Lazarus
All these seven signs are shown in John's Gospel
Why did the author show it this way?
He also combined the seven "I"s in Jesus' words
You may have heard of "I am the food of life"
We just talked about "I am the light of the world"
We are all familiar with it
The "I am" echoes the "I am" in the Old Testament
"I am the food of life"
It means Jesus is talking about his "divine nature"
So what I want to say is
We need to see what we can see
How God, through his miracles and his words, tells people who he is
Just like today, the 9th chapter
The Bible already has seven different names for Jesus
Can you see it?
The word may be too small
It says "Nahahwite"
"Nahahwite" in the Bible
"Jerusalemite"
"Lazarus"
"Lazarus" in the Bible
"Jerusalemite"
The Bible is really powerful
It already has so many names in the Old Testament
But each name has a deeper meaning
The door is still one and a half
Perhaps Philip or Nathaniel knew that
Jehoiachin was going to be raised up by the cross
But I think they never thought
The place of the raising up was not a political throne
On the contrary, Jesus was going to be raised up by the cross
God wanted to show the door of the cross to the people
To show the meaning of each of the "cleansing"
Because Jehoiachin wanted the reader to understand who Jesus was
To understand the true meaning of "the door of the cross"
In the past, the Gospels were in the city of Bethlehem
In the New Testament, Christ lived among people like a scene
Today, Christ is still living with us
He still lives in us
The Bible says, "Do you believe?"
"You have to see the greater things"
It turns out that "believing" is not our end
We have to slowly pursue the greater things
God has ordered us to experience Him more
To see Him more, to see Him, to understand Him
To experience His love
I will share a story
I remember once my wife and I went on a visit
For some reason, the visit was already a milestone
In other words, after visiting this time
There should be no more chance to visit these families
That night, God gave us a feeling
Every time we visit a family
We would like to pray and bless them
We would like to ask God to take care of them and to protect them
When we went to this visit
We met this visitor
She was a homeless woman who was homeless
My wife and I prayed with her
After praying, God touched us
We asked her, "Do you believe in Jesus?"
She didn't even think about it
She said, "Yes, I do"
We asked, "Really?"
"Yes"
I was very careful at that time
Why?
Because I thought that if I invited people to believe in Jesus
They would eat lemons
So I confirmed my wish
But I didn't expect that this time
I just responded to the touch
I prayed with them
And asked them if they wanted to believe in Jesus
God arranged for my wife and I to go to the harvest together
To witness the resurrection of the human soul
She said she believed in Jesus
We immediately prayed with her
And helped her to find a suitable church
To give her a suitable church
I thought it was amazing
After that, my wife and I debriefed with other church members
We realized that it was not us who brought this woman to face God
It was God who brought this woman to face God
To give her to me, my wife, and even the baby in her womb
To witness her amazing work
To let us witness the glory of God's work
I realized more today
God seemed to be telling us
He was telling me
God had blessed my family to serve Him
I was looking for a way to go forward
I was worried that my family and my service would be dragged down
God saw through my needs
Through this visit, He seemed to be telling me
Adrian, don't look at your own limitations
Look at me with confidence
Respond to my love with love
You and your family will soon see
What I do in your lives
Today, I pray to God
I pray that God will help us to open the eyes of the Holy Spirit
When we are willing, we can see more
The Holy Spirit will help us
Through the Bible, we can witness the Holy Spirit
We can understand the truth and richness of the Holy Spirit
I pray that God will help us
to see God's presence in our lives
to see God's glory in our difficulties
to see God's work in our service
Sister Ling, next Wednesday, March 5th
is the Holy Fathers' Day
It is the beginning of the Holy Father's Day
Traditionally, the faithful will fast and pray
to practice repentance and self-awakening
until the day of resurrection
Yes, we are very busy today
We are so busy that we have no time
We don't even have time to call Jesus
It is really not easy
But are we willing to
in these 40 days of the Holy Fathers' Day
to separate our eyes from the Holy Spirit?
Will we learn not to only focus on our own busy schedule and pressure
but also to learn how to practice self-awakening
and to stop doing things
I have heard people say something
in these 40 days
They say not to drink coffee or milk tea
or not to sleep after 12 o'clock
or not to use your phone before going to bed
For me, I used to say
not to do things that are a retaliation
to put down our old habits
and use our physical feelings
to focus more
and pay more attention to Jesus
I would like to invite you to be quiet
and to pray together
We have a time to meditate
(music)
Today, let's see if we can recall
the vision of Jesus
That vision can go beyond the weakness in our hearts
and reach our true nature
God uses the eyes of His love
to look at us, who are so fragile
He doesn't want to scare us
He wants us to feel His tenderness
Are we willing to open up our lives
to put down our old habits
and weaknesses
and embrace Him?
At the same time, we are thinking
Today, we have been faithful for a while
Do we have a deeper desire
to know Jesus Christ?
The Bible tells us
that His name has many meanings
It has deep, meaningful meanings
that we may not have discovered yet
Lord, open up our mouths of the Holy Spirit
to help us
Through the words of God
Through our spiritual practice
Through our worship
Give our hearts to our Lord
Let us pray together
Lord Jesus, You are the God who can hear people's prayers
Today, we may have different thoughts
in front of you
We may not dare to look at you
We may feel very helpless
or we may not want to be so close to you
But the Lord has given us the opportunity
to look at you
Through this vision
we can see your warmth
Lord, open up our eyes
Open up our mouths of the Holy Spirit
We also want to see
the many difficulties in our lives
that are actually filled with your beautiful words
Sometimes, it may seem like wishful thinking
But I know it's not
It's a desire
When you give us the power of your eyes
we can see
that there is another perspective
and this perspective is to fulfill your beautiful words
Help us
Open up our ears
Open up our eyes
to see that
what you have given us is the best
We are weak
but we ask for your help
We pray with our hearts
to be able to
serve you, Lord Jesus
Amen
Let's stand up together
and sing "Let Yourself Go" again
I hope this can be a prayer
to the Lord Jesus
Let yourself go
I kneel and offer my life
I dare not look at you
I dare not see you
I face the ground
and discover myself
My blood is boiling
I have lost
I have been through a lot
With the power of my eyes
Let yourself go
I kneel and offer my life
I dare not look at you
I dare not see you
I face the ground
and discover myself
My blood is boiling
I have lost
I have been through a lot
With the power of my eyes
I pray that you can teach me how to live
I can hear you speak day and night
You have inspired me
I continue to seek and explore
I pray that you can teach me how to live
I look at myself
and seek you
I put my hands up
and wait for you
We let ourselves go
We tell Jesus
We humble ourselves before you