(Cantonese)
MBTI
and do many things that are against God's will
What St Paul was talking about was not people who did not believe in God
He was talking about believers
What does the Bible say?
He says, 'there shall be no obstacles in your help'
When it comes to believers
you should no longer be the same as those who did not believe in God
You should have left the darkness and sins
You should no longer do things that are the same as those who did not believe in God
You should not do things that offend God
But believers are still in the darkness
Why are believers still in the darkness?
Why are they separated from God?
It is because they are ignorant and stubborn
Not only that
Let's look at the 19th chapter
In the 19th chapter, the New Testament is even more straightforward
The New Testament says,
"Since they are ignorant, they should be free to do all kinds of things that are against God's will"
What is he talking about?
He is talking about people's choices
People should be firm in their hearts
People should be free to do all kinds of things that are against God's will
In English, he says,
"Greedy to practice every kind of impurity"
It means that you want to practice
What is he talking about?
Not just once
It is repeated over and over again
These practices may even become a habit
It turns out that believers should have left the darkness
They should have been in the light
But they deliberately chose to break the law
They went back to the darkness again and again
And separated themselves from God
When we look at this, we understand
Why did Paul use such a strict, strict, and high-level sermon?
Because it is people's will
It is people's choice
And this kind of life
The life of leaving God
The life in the darkness
Is not able to build the body of Christ
To raise Christ to glory
But I think
There is no reason for believers not to know
Why do they fall back into the darkness so easily?
Or maybe they are not willing to leave the darkness
Let's understand what darkness means
Darkness means that there is no light
God did not make darkness
God made light, but lost the light
In ancient times, light was generally used
To represent rational thinking
In Judaism, light represents life
It is mentioned in the Bible that light is Jesus himself
It is God himself
When people lose the light
It means that they leave God
Their hearts become dark
They lose their rational thinking
When they lose the light in the darkness
Their souls become anxious, anxious, and fearful
All kinds of worries come out
How do we settle these fears, worries, and pressures?
People will do many things to help themselves settle their anxieties
And what is the easiest thing to do?
It is to do the things in the world
It is the easiest thing to do
When we can do these things in the world
It is really OK
We can have a moment of peace
We can really settle some things
Then we may want to do more
We want to do more in the world
When we do more in the world
The distance between us and God will be further and further
When the distance between us and God is further and further
What will happen to our hearts?
We will continue to be in the darkness
When we are in the darkness, the anxiety will come out
In the end, we will be in an infinite cycle
We will keep practicing this mode
So why did the Bible say that our hearts become numb?
Because we have been used to practicing
We don't know how to find God
We are used to being in the darkness
Especially when we are under a lot of pressure
And when we are in trouble
We will easily want to throw up
The habit of throwing up
Will easily appear in our lives
I remember
When I was still working at the workplace
I remembered my colleagues
My colleagues love to drink
Of course, drinking is not a crime
But I want to say that they don't drink
They drink
Do you know what drinking is?
You know, right?
You don't know? I see you are looking away
That's great, you are so simple
You drink until you are drunk
They love to drink
They drink when they are happy
Because they are happy
Drinking makes them happier
What if they are not happy?
They drink even more
Because they will be sober after getting drunk
They will be drunk
They will throw up and talk nonsense
Some people will hug and kiss
It's scary when a man kisses a woman
Why do they drink when they are happy?
Why do they drink when they are not happy?
I believe
They are under a lot of pressure at work
They want to solve the pressure immediately
They are not happy
Drinking is a good way
It brings a moment of happiness
I believe they know
It's not good for your body to get drunk with alcohol
Some people drink until
They look like they won't drink anymore
They know it's not good, but they are used to it
They can't change it
They drink because they have to
That's why they are happy
They have to get drunk
To forget their pain
I think of young people
They are under a lot of pressure
At home, in their growth
Or in their studies
In their relationships
They are under a lot of pressure
They will use the way of cutting their hands
To solve their inner pain
They know it's not good to cut their hands
It hurts, right?
And if they cut their hands
They will have to wear long sleeves in summer
To cover it
They don't dare to wear short sleeves
But why do they still cut their hands?
Because the pain in their heart is too painful
They can't solve the pressure and pain
They would rather their body's pain
Can reduce their inner pain
And it seems to work
929 is a habit
Continuous practice is a habit
Yes, sisters
I don't know
Although we believe in God
Our lives are saved by God
But are there some things
We can't get rid of the darkness?
There are some things we should know
Don't do it
It's offensive to God
It's not pleasant
But are we using
Some thoughts that don't fit God's mind
Our way of life
To deal with our insecurity?
It even becomes our habit
So we inadvertently
Still stay in the darkness
In the darkness
And make us
Get farther and farther away from God?
Sister Ling
I don't know what method you are using
To deal with your pressure
What method
To deal with your insecurity?
These methods
These life styles
Have they made you
Get farther away from God?
Let's continue
When we say
There are still these old life styles
Or these habits
That make us fall into the darkness
How can we return to the light?
In the 20th chapter
It says
"But what you learned from Christ is not like this"
"But"
Usually
The word "but"
Is used to make a strong comparison
I want to tell the believers
Believers
You shouldn't be like this
You should be like Christ
You shouldn't be like what I said
Like the believers
To be like Christ
There is a verse that says
I want to use the New Testament to make it clearer
The New Testament says
"You must have heard of his testimony"
"And have received the teaching in him"
"For the truth is in Jesus"
The Bible uses the word "if"
As if it is a conditional sentence
A question sentence
No
This is a very solid statement
What does it say?
"For the truth is in Jesus"
"And have received the teaching in him"
And "receive"
He uses the word "receive"
Receive is not just about knowing
Or knowing the truth
It also includes the truth
There is a very special verse
He says
"The truth is in Jesus"
It's very interesting
In the book of Paul
The name "Jesus"
Is not used often
Because it is usually used to mean
Jesus Christ
Or Jesus Christ
The name "Jesus"
Is very rare in the book of Paul
I believe Paul wanted to tell the believers
Jesus is a man who can live
And speak the truth
The believers should follow Jesus
Not just to hear the truth
But to listen to the teachings
Or to understand
And to carry out the teachings
The truth
Not just to hear
But to carry it out
Then
In 22-24
He tells us
How to carry out the teachings of Jesus Christ
In these three verses
There are three uncertainties
They are "discard"
"renew"
And "re-enact"
Let's first look at
"re-enact" and "discard"
Because these two words are actually one word
I found that the translation of "New Testament of Japan" is clearer
No need to explain so much
He says in "New Testament of Japan"
"Discard" means to remove the old man
This old man belongs to your past lifestyle
"Discard" means to follow the old man
"The lust of the heart is growing day by day"
We need to discard
What is "discard"?
It's about our old lifestyle
Until we no longer follow
The lifestyle of the non-believers
Or the non-believers
Of course
Not all non-believers have problems
They are all wrong
What is he talking about?
That lifestyle is to follow the lust of the heart
Those who have problems
Those who offend God
The lifestyle of the non-believers
We need to leave
If you have the opportunity
You can also look at the following 25-32 chapters
There are more examples
About what is not in line with God's will
What is offending God
Those things will lead the believers to leave God
Farther and farther
What do the believers need to do?
They need to leave
They need to stop this lifestyle
Yes, they need to stop
They can't have this lifestyle anymore
This kind of habit
Then we look at "discard"
As I said, it's a pair
It's like wearing clothes
Except for a dirty shirt
You need to wear a new shirt
What is this shirt?
It is to follow the image of God
I don't know what you think of when you hear this
You should think of God's creator
Adam and Eve are made according to God's image
Yes, we should be like Adam and Eve
Made according to God's image
We can be a new person
Just like Adam and Eve in the beginning
At the time of Eden
They are no longer separated from God
Very close to God
We can live out the purpose of God's creation
Our life can live out God's will
But because of sin
We are separated from God
But Jesus Christ's redemption
Let us return to God's embrace again
Jesus Christ is the way, the truth, and the life
Lead us back to God's embrace
And the punishment that Jesus suffered
We should live out God's will
So that we can return to God's embrace
And become holy
Yes, we should stop our old behavior
Stop, don't do it again
We should be a new person
We should do the old things
Don't do the dirty things
But we should do the things that are in harmony with God's will
And the last word is
"Renew"
In English, it means to be renewed in the spirit of your mind
It's not just about renewing our mind
It's our mind
Are we willing to be changed by God?
Are we willing to use a new way
A renewed way
To live out a new person, a new way of life?
Why do we need to renew?
Why do we need to use new things?
Because the old things are not compatible
It's like when you upgrade your phone and computer
But you don't upgrade, you buy a new one
You don't need to update the iOS, right?
I don't know, I don't know
Why do we need to change?
To upgrade or to change a new phone or a new computer
Because we need to adapt to the new era
I have the courage to ask
Is there anyone still using their phone
To type and type in but not able to go online?
Is there anyone still using this type of phone?
Watchman, you seem to want to raise your hand
We are basically normal
Of course, there are some people who really need it
Because they have two phones
Maybe one of their phones is really just for typing
But I believe most of us are using a smartphone
Smartphone
Yes, because of the need of the times
If we are just using a phone for typing
Our life is actually quite difficult
Just going to a restaurant, you may not be able to eat
Because the restaurant is ordering food
You have to do the dishes yourself
No one serves you
Yes
Because we need to adapt to a new life
So we need to upgrade
Yes, today, we believe in God
We are new people, we need to upgrade and change
Only by being able to adapt to a new life
Can we be able to express God's will
It's very interesting
These three groups of words
If we just look at "disappear" and "rebirth"
We can understand what they mean
But it's very interesting
You will find that "disappear" is above
"rebirth" is below
"rebirth" is in the middle of "disappear"
Yes, this is an important expression
"rebirth" is very important
Because our heart is affecting our brain
Our brain is affecting how we walk
This is how people should work
Your heart is first
Think about it
If I want to buy a new computer
My brain needs to think
To decide the price
Who is the cheapest
Then I will buy it
This is how it should work
So, the word "rebirth" is in the middle
It's very important
If we don't want to
It's very difficult to take action to coordinate
Also, the word "rebirth"
The original Chinese character is a present tense
Yes, it's very interesting
"Disappear" and "rebirth" are past tense
The present tense has a continuous meaning
It means to keep rebirthing
It's not enough to rebirth once
We need to keep rebirthing
Why?
Why do we need to keep rebirthing?
I believe it's because
Our old habits
Our old lifestyle
Have been with us for too long
These habits are easy to get out of
We need to be gifted
To keep rebirthing our heart
To remind us again
How to live out the Christian lifestyle
Just like when we go to a restaurant
We need to count the K-codes before we order
At first, we are not used to it
We want to ask the waiters to order
But we need to count the codes
When we are asked to do so
But as we count the codes
Maybe today
You will count the codes naturally
We need to get used to it
We need to practice
Because the old thinking is very rigid
We need to break the old thinking
And create a new habit
We need to learn from our habits
Don't let the old thinking come out so easily
Ask God first
Ask the Heavens
Or think about
This habit, this response
Is it in conflict with the principles of the Bible?
We need to practice
Ask the Heavens more
Don't let the old thinking come out so easily
We need the help of the Holy Spirit
We need the Holy Spirit's reminder
So that we can have the right choice
And make a right choice
Sisters
We really need the Holy Spirit
And rely on God
So that we can live out the Christian lifestyle
It may not be easy
Because we have lived for so many years
We have so many habits and cultures
It is hard for us to get rid of them
But we can change
We can practice
We can practice and change our old habits
Create a new habit
A habit that we can rely on the Heavens
And pray to God
Don't rely on yourself
Lastly, I would like to share my experiences
The reminders that the Heavens give me in my life
I am a person who is afraid of doing the wrong things
Because I always did the wrong things when I was young
What would happen if I did the wrong things?
Have you ever experienced doing the wrong things?
Have you ever done the wrong things?
Wow, you are really good at it
You are wrong
Usually, people will scold you for doing the wrong things
I was always scolded when I was young
I have a low self-image
I always thought I was a useless person
I was always criticized
So I really want to do well
Because I am afraid of doing the wrong things
Because I will be scolded if I do the wrong things
So I really want to work hard
To do better things
So that I won't be scolded
But I will bring this pattern or habit
into my appearance
I also have this tendency
It sounds like nothing
But it's not
When I really want to do well
No matter what I arrange
Whether it's a meeting or a speech
Or if there is a problem in my life
I will deal with it immediately
I want to think more
Plan better
Do better
The best is to deal with all the problems
And settle them
When I settle all these things
I won't feel insecure
I won't be scolded if I do well
I will have this pattern of doing things
Now I am learning
It's quite tiring to do this all the time
Doing everything well
It's tiring for my life
Now I am learning
Do I have to do something immediately?
Do I have to deal with things immediately?
Do I have to go beyond all these things?
Or should I pray first?
To give up the difficulties I face
Or the difficulties that the sisters face
I remember I told the sisters
At the beginning of the year
I don't remember if I said this on this platform
I remember I said this on React
The lesson I want to learn in 2024
Is to learn to let go
I should learn to let go
Don't hold on to things so tightly
Don't rely on your own efforts
I have to practice
How to let go and give to God
Recently, a brother shared with me
The situation of his sisters
I was very worried
Just like me in the past
I have a habit of saying
"You have a problem? We should talk about it"
"We should make an appointment"
I said we should make an appointment
To solve these problems
Don't make the relationship
Too tense
Or maybe a lot of things are just misunderstandings
I hope we can solve it quickly
I said we should make an appointment
But the brother said
"I don't know what to do"
"We should try to talk about it"
"We are all grown up now"
"We are all mature now"
"We can try to solve it"
He told me not to interfere
I thought
"Yes, you are all grown up"
"You are all mature"
"Why can't I trust you with these things?"
"I should trust you"
"You have the ability to solve it"
"Yes, God has mentioned me"
"I should trust you"
"You have the ability to solve it"
"I should learn to let go"
To me, it was a new experience
It was my habit
I jump in when I have something to talk about
But now I am learning
I am learning
I give my head to God
I realize that
I don't have to do too much
I have the opportunity to grow
It is a lesson of trust and communication
I trust my sisters
They carry a lot of things
They do things well
I trust them
I don't know, sisters
Do you have anything to update?
I don't know what word you have created in the beginning of 2024
It is the end of 2024
Do you have any word to create?
I don't know what you have to update
I hope you can practice new habits
These habits will help you to be closer to God
These habits will help us to leave the darkness
These habits will help us to be closer to God
I don't know if you have any
Sisters, sometimes I feel it is not easy
Because we have lived for so many years
Many things are very considerate
Many things come out naturally
There are some ways to respond
But some things, some ways
May not be in harmony
Maybe these habits
May lead us to leave God
We need the Holy Spirit to remind us
We need a new perspective
A new way
To bring Christ out
I know it is not easy
But we can practice
To make us more accustomed
To rely on God
Not on ourselves
I will put the Bible on the table
Sisters, I don't know
What is your life situation?
Are there any things
That make us stay in the darkness?
Next Sunday is Christmas
It is the day of the resurrection of Christ
Christ is the true light
He will shine on the darkness
He will shine on those who are trapped
He will take people out of the darkness
Into a wonderful light
Would you like to invite Christ
Into your life again?