[Music]
Hello, everyone
My name is Lee Tien-kwan
I am a teacher at the Catholic Academy of the Holy See
I teach systematic theology
Today I would like to introduce a book
about the study of the Five Elements
Many people have asked me
what books to introduce
when I teach or share this topic
So today I would like to introduce a book
that is often referred to as "church"
in the Chinese language
or "theology"
Today I would like to introduce a book
that is based on the study of the Five Elements
or even a broader study
of the Five Elements, called "Pentecostalism"
It is a broader study
and is not often mentioned in the Chinese language
This book is called "Global Pentecostalism"
The title is
"The New Phase of Christian Social Engagement"
It is written by two scholars
They are not members of the Five Elements
One is Donald E. Mueller
He studies religious and social science
The other is Ted Yamamori
He is an NGO that deals with poverty
When the two of them work together
they want to conduct research
on developing countries
especially on Christian churches
that are developing rapidly
and have no police support
but are active in serving society
and even bringing about social transformation
in the church
In their research
they found that 85% of the churches
were the Five Elements and the Holy Spirit
So they changed the title of the book
to "Pentecostalism"
The book is based on
the study of the Five Elements
in a global way
Because when we study the Five Elements
or the Pentecostalism
especially in the Chinese language
we use the "three-wave theory"
We say that the United States is the center
and the "made in USA" is the direction
But today many people
are looking at it from a global perspective
They found that
the Pentecostalism
is not only the development of the United States
the development of the "one, two, three waves"
but also the development of different revival movements
in the world
So they divided the groups
into five major groups
The first group is the classical Pentecostalism
which is the five-fold tradition
The second group is the individualistic
but five-fold-style
or the local-style
The third group is the spiritual movement
or the third-wave-influenced
The fourth group is the individualistic
but the five-fold-style
or the local-style
The fifth group is very special
It is very rare to see
It is a group of individual believers
who participated in a special meeting
and had spiritual experience
Because of this experience
they also had many faith-filled activities
From a global perspective
it is a rich study of the three-wave theory
of the Pentecostalism
Especially the local churches
which are not influenced by the West
This is a great criticism of the three-wave theory
The second feature is that
this book is studied by non-Pentecostalists
or the people of the Bible
They mainly use cross-scientific research
especially religious psychology
The study of the three-wave theory
shows us a broader direction of the Pentecostalism
especially in the university
not limited to the diocese or church
There are also many scientific integrations
They use social theories
such as Marx, Jurgen, Sigmund Freud
to study the three-wave theory
Of course, the authors
or the two authors
emphasize that
these social theories
often weaken religious phenomena
But from their perspective
I think they have a breakthrough
In addition to social theories
they also use the email theorem
to study worship
and how to integrate the whole community
into a single theory
They are also careful
to avoid neglecting
or denying some supernatural works
This is a key point or breakthrough
in their research
This book emphasizes
the Christian social engagement
As I said
85% of the church
is Pentecostal and spiritual
In fact, it means
that many of our understanding of the Pentecostalism
is based on the doctrine of the Holy Spirit
or they emphasize the aspect of the Holy Spirit
But today, from a global perspective
when we look at this data
they are not conservative
Christian believers
They are very involved in society
and participate in the transformation of society
So in this book
they call these Christian believers
or Pentecostal believers
"progressive Pentecostalism"
which means they are progressive
or they are believers who are in favor of Pentecostalism
This is a new perspective
of the Pentecostalism research
and the Pentecostalism church
It is very interesting
It compares the Pentecostalism
with the Pentecostalism in Latin America
There is a quote
that I think is worth reading
It says
"Liberation theology opted for the poor
at the same time that the poor were opting for Pentecostalism"
In fact, it says
that in Latin America
the reformation of society was the doctrine of the Holy Spirit
But in the public sphere
many people's needs
whether they are sick
or in economic need
are not satisfied by the doctrine of the Holy Spirit
but by the Five-Day Feast
or the Church of the Holy Spirit
Their social programs
such as orphanages, medical care
social support
and even job hunting
have been extended to
Protestant ethics
Pentecostal ethics
and many other economic topics
which are also very important
in the Five-Day Feast
Here you can see
the uniqueness of this book
At the end, there are two bullet points
The first bullet point is that
this book is very special
It introduces Hong Kong
Of course, when these two authors
visited Hong Kong and Singapore
they were a bit skeptical
whether they were developing countries
But they did research on these churches
They studied the Church of the Holy Spirit
the Pentecostal Church
At first, they were a bit skeptical
But gradually they found that
they did not want to establish an organization
but to lead by the Holy Spirit
So they did not need to raise funds
They did not want to establish a church
but to build a group of people
who love each other because of God's love
This made them very optimistic
Of course, they also visited a pastor
in Hong Kong to explain the doctrine
The pastor was a PhD student
in an important Canadian school
Of course, he was not a pastor of the Five-Day Feast
But he saw that there were many new ideas
about the Five-Day Feast
This is also a very important point
in this book
Of course, they also visited the Holy See
the Holy See in the Central Park
So this is worth mentioning
The second bullet point is that
if you are interested in the Five-Day Feast
you can read two more extended translations
The first is the "Pentecostalism" published in 1997
This is a global study of the Five-Day Feast
It has already broken the "Three-Wheel Theory"
It was published in 1997
The other one is a new one
It is a handbook on Pentecostal theology
This book is very good
because it covers almost all the topics
of the Five-Day Feast
Each chapter is written by a research expert
or a book expert
It is only about ten pages
You can understand the whole topic
It is very worth reading
I hope that when you are interested in Pentecostalism
you can read the above book
Thank you
[Music]